<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.1.2//EN" 
   "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.1.2/docbookx.dtd">
<chapter>
 <chapterinfo>
  <pubdate>Last modified: $Date$ by $Author$</pubdate>
  <authorgroup>
   <author>
    <firstname>Glenys</firstname>
    <surname>Thomson</surname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Diogo</firstname>
    <surname>Meyer</surname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Kristie</firstname>
    <surname>Mather</surname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Jill</firstname>
    <surname>Hollenbach</surname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Alex</firstname>
    <surname>Lancaster</surname>
   </author>
   <author>
    <firstname>Steve</firstname>
    <surname>Mack</surname>
   </author>
  </authorgroup>
  
 </chapterinfo>
 
 <title>The HLA region</title>
 
 <para condition="main">Here we give a summary of the HLA (human
  leukocyte antigen) system in humans, the major histocompatiblity
  complex (MHC) in humans. The HLA classical class I and II genes are
  a set of closely linked, highly polymorphic genes involved in the
  immune response. The HLA genes also influence susceptibility to over
  200 diseases, including autoimmune diseases, cancers, and infectious
  diseases.</para>

 <para condition="main;anthro-book">A number of functional and
  population features implicate selection as an important factor
  maintaining the extensive HLA variation. Although the precise nature
  of this selection is not known, response to a wide variety of
  pathogens is believed to be a major evolutionary pressure. Recent
  advances in genomics, combined with increasing knowledge of
  structure-function of HLA molecules, provides new tools for
  exploring HLA polymorphism and an opportunity to address fundamental
  questions about HLA sequence variation, immunity, and disease. Such
  detailed information has not previously been available and is
  critical for a complete understanding of the immune system,
  autoimmune and infectious diseases, transplantation, and development
  of T-cell therapies and vaccines.</para>

 <sect1>
  <title>Map of region</title>

  <para condition="main;anthro-book">The HLA region maps to
   ch. 6p21.31. It consists of 3.6 Mb of DNA and contains 224
   identified genes, 128 of which are predicted to be expressed,
   arranged in three major gene clusters (The MHC Sequencing
   Consortium 1999, Rhodes and Trowsdale 1999). Only some of the HLA
   region genes are involved in the immune response. Much of our
   interest is in the HLA classical class I (A, B, and C) (1.8 Mb) and
   class II (DR, DQ, and DP) (1.2 Mb) genes, which flank the class III
   region (see <xref linkend="hla-map.figure"/>).</para>

  <figure id="hla-map.figure">
   <title>Map of the HLA region (adapted from Rhodes and Trowsdale 1999)*</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="hla-map.png" align="center"/>
    </imageobject>
    
    <caption>
     <para>*Class I &ndash; ovals: classical (Ia) filled, non-classical (Ib) stippled, pseudogenes open. </para>
     <para>Class II&ndash;rectangles: B genes light, A genes dark.</para>
     <para>Allele numbers are from <ulink url="http://www.anthonynolan.com/HIG/index.html">http://www.anthonynolan.com/HIG/index.html</ulink>, as of Oct. 13, 2000.</para>
    </caption>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <para condition="main">The six classical class I and II loci are
   highly polymorphic and encode structurally homologous products
   which are expressed on the surface of antigen presenting cells. HLA
   molecules are receptors which capture peptide fragments of antigen
   that help T cells recognize and respond to foreign antigens. The
   division into class I and II molecules is based on their structure,
   tissue distribution, source of peptide antigen, and the function of
   responding T cells (McCluskey and Peh 1999, Little and Parham
   1999). Each of the class II DR, DQ, and DP regions contains at
   least two genes, denoted A and B respectively, e.g., DRA1,
   DRB1. The class III region includes immune system and non-immune
   system loci encoding, e.g., complement proteins, Factor B, C2, C4,
   and tumor necrosis factors, TNFA and B.</para>

  <para condition="main;anthro-book">The recombination distance
   between the most distant of the HLA classical loci, the class I A
   locus and the class II DPB1 locus is 3.7 cM (Carrington 1999). The
   HLA region in fact extends beyond these boundaries; e.g., the
   non-classical class I gene involved in hemochromatosis, HFE, maps 4
   Mb from HLA-A (Rhodes and Trowsdale 1999, <ulink
   url="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/</ulink>).</para>
  
 </sect1>

 <sect1 condition="main">
  
  <title>Structure and function of class I and class II molecules</title>

  <para> The processed self and foreign peptide fragments presented by
   the classical HLA molecules (see <xref
   linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>) usually consist of 8&ndash;10
   amino acids (class I) or 12&ndash;20 amino acids (class II), and
   are of either intracellular or extracellular origin
   respectively. Class I and II genes are distantly related at the
   sequence level, but the protein structures are quite similar, and
   both are members of the immunoglobulin superfamily. The classical
   class I molecules (A, B, and C) are comprised of a heavy chain,
   encoded by the HLA region, and a light chain, encoded by the
   invariant &beta;2-microglobulin gene on ch. 15 (<xref
   linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>). The extracellular portion of the
   heavy chain is divided into 3 domains: &alpha;1, &alpha;2, and
   &alpha;3, each about 90 amino acids long. The &alpha;1 and &alpha;2
   domains form a groove bordered by two &alpha;-helices with a
   &beta;-pleated sheet floor. It is in this groove, referred to as
   the antigen recognition site (ARS), that the peptide fragment is
   bound. The classical class II molecules (DR, DQ, and DP) are
   composed of an &alpha; and a &beta; chain (from the A and B genes
   respectively) in a non-covalent association (<xref
   linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>). The extracellular portion of
   each chain consists of two domains (&alpha;1, &alpha;2 and &beta;1,
   &beta;2), each about 90 amino acids long. The ARS is formed by the
   &alpha;1 and &beta;1 domains.</para>

  <figure id="hla-structure.figure">
   <title>Class I and class II structure and antigen presentation</title>
   <mediaobject>
    <imageobject>
     <imagedata fileref="hla-structure.png" align="center"/>
    </imageobject>
   </mediaobject>
  </figure>
  
  <para>An MHC molecule binds only to peptides conforming to certain
   structural requirements. A particular MHC allele is thus only able
   to present a subset of the available peptides to T cells. Peptide
   motifs important for binding to HLA molecules, including critical
   residues, e.g., position 57 of DQB1, have been defined by sequence
   analysis of naturally processed peptides, analysis with synthetic
   peptides, and predictive inference of binding preference based on
   similarity of peptide-binding environments. While some of the most
   highly polymorphic HLA amino acid residues line the groove of the
   ARS, conferring unique peptide- and TCR-binding properties on each
   MHC molecule, clusters of highly conserved amino acid residues are
   found outside the groove and at both ends of the ARS.</para>

  <para> Class I molecules are expressed on most cells and interact
   with CD8+ (cytotoxic) T cells, playing a critical part in tissue
   graft rejection as well as in the immune response to viruses and
   intracellular pathogens, and cancerous cells. Class II molecules
   are expressed only on a restricted subset of immune system cells,
   e.g., macrophages and B-cells, and interact with CD4+ (helper) T
   cells, exerting an immune system response through the production of
   various lymphokines, such as IL-2, affecting, among other things, B
   cell differentiation and antibody production.</para>

  <para>During the maturation of the immune system, T-cell clones are
   deleted or rendered anergic to self peptides in the context of HLA
   presentation. Autoimmune disease is thought to result when there is
   a breakdown in self-tolerance. Molecular mechanisms have been
   proposed for the direct role of HLA molecules in the cascade of
   autoimmune events leading to type 1 diabetes (previously referred
   to as insulin dependent diabetes mellitus&mdash;IDDM) and other
   autoimmune diseases.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1>
  <title>HLA polymorphism</title>
  
  <para condition="main;anthro-book">The polymorphism of many of the
   HLA genes and MHC genes in other species, is extraordinary (<xref
   linkend="hla-map.figure"/>); e.g., 320 alleles are currently
   described for the class II DRB1 gene, and 399 for the class I B
   gene, with much of the variation present at the protein level. The
   genetic variation is concentrated in the amino acid residues of the
   ARS (see e.g., Little and Parham 1999). Alleles at HLA-A, for
   example, differ from each other by up to 20&ndash;30 amino
   acids. In contrast to these highly polymorphic loci, there are also
   HLA region loci which show very little polymorphism, e.g., the
   non-classical class I genes, some class II genes such as DRA1, and
   the complement class III genes.</para>

  <para condition="main;anthro-book">Point mutations generating new
   variation and genetic exchange (recombination or gene conversion)
   reassorting extant polymorphism into new combinations have played
   key roles in creating HLA diversity (Little and Parham 1999). For
   class I genes, generation of variants at the B locus appears to be
   more rapid than at the A or C loci. HLA variation shows population
   structure; some alleles differ in frequency between ethnic groups,
   others are unique to a specific ethnic or geographic group,
   particularly those of the highly polymorphic class I B and class II
   DRB1 genes (see e.g., Imanishi et al. 1992, Charron 1997).</para>

  <para condition="main">To explain the extensive polymorphism at the
  HLA loci, Klein (1987) proposed a <quote>trans-species</quote>
  hypothesis whereby ancestral allelic polymorphism is maintained,
  presumably by balancing selection, after species divergence. First
  applied to rodent species, this theory is also supported by evidence
  in primates where, for example, certain chimpanzee alleles are more
  closely related to specific human alleles than they are to other
  chimpanzee alleles. This segregation of alleles across species into
  <quote>allelic lineages</quote> is based primarily on sequence
  homology and serological specificities, although these groupings for
  the class I HLA-A locus have also been correlated with functional
  attributes such as peptide binding specificities (Jakobsen et
  al. 1998). For class I, allelic lineages are seen most clearly at
  the less polymorphic loci A and C, however at even the most
  polymorphic class II locus, DRB1, the alleles can be divided into 13
  distinct allelic lineages. Phylogenetic studies support the idea
  that many of these lineages are very old, but that alleles within
  each lineage have been generated recently in hominoid evolution
  (Bergstrom et al. 1998).</para>

  <para condition="main">Molecular typing methods, for example using
   PCR (polymerase chain reaction) and SSOP
   (sequence-specific-oligonucleotide probes), are now the standard
   for typing class II loci (see e.g., Middleton 1999). The greater
   degree and type of variability of HLA class I compared to class II
   loci has made molecular typing more difficult than initially
   expected by researchers in the field. Recently, molecular typing
   methods have also been applied to class I loci (see e.g., Cao et
   al. 1999). For molecularly defined alleles, the first two numbers
   of the allele designation refer to the serological type of the
   allele, so that DRB1*0401 and 0402 are subtypes of DR4. This is
   indicative of the increased resolution of alleles available with
   molecular typing.</para>

  <para condition="main"> Microsatellites in the HLA region share the
   characteristics of microsatellites found elsewhere in the genome,
   including high density, high mutation rates, and high
   polymorphism. The utility of microsatellites for the identification
   of HLA region disease genes has been demonstrated (see e.g.,
   Foissac et al. 1997 for review, Carrington et
   al. 1999). Identification of single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs)
   across the HLA region in diverse ethnic groups is in progress
   (Geraghty et al. 1999).</para>
  
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1 condition="main;anthro-book">

  <title>Selection in the HLA region</title>

  <para> Allele frequencies within a population for serologically
   typed HLA class I A, B, and C and the class II DR locus, and for
   molecularly typed class II DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1, are often more
   even than expected under neutrality, suggesting that some form of
   balancing selection is operating on these genes (see e.g., Hedrick
   and Thomson 1983, Salamon et al. 1999, Valdes et al. 1999). In
   contrast, the distribution of DPB1 alleles rarely differs
   significantly from neutrality expectations; usually there is a
   fairly common allele, which may differ between populations.</para>

  <para>From the examination of class I and II genes across species,
   nonsynonymous amino acid substitutions per site (dn) are
   proportionally more common than synonymous substitutions (ds) in
   the ARS, indicative of balancing selection maintaining the
   extensive variation (Hughes and Nei 1988, 1989). Regions not
   involved in peptide binding typically show dn &lt; ds, the pattern
   expected under purifying selection.</para>

  <para> The specific mechanism of the selection acting on MHC
   variation has not yet been identified, although models invoking
   heterozygote advantage are strong candidates, since individuals
   heterozygous for HLA present a wider range of foreign peptides to T
   cells (Parham and Ohta 1996, Edwards and Hedrick
   1998). Observations on the pathogens <emphasis>Plasmodium
   falciparum</emphasis> (malaria), human and simian immunodeficiency
   viruses (HIV and SIV), Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), and hepatitis B
   have indicated that HLA restricted cytotoxic T-cell responses may
   influence the evolution of the host-pathogen relationship. HLA
   associations with infectious diseases may differ between geographic
   regions and reflect pathogen variation. This may account for some
   of the differences seen in HLA allele frequencies between
   geographical areas.</para>

  <para> Other mechanisms proposed to explain MHC variability are
   disassortative mating and maternal-fetal incompatibility. There is
   evidence of maternal-fetal incompatibility in humans, and
   disassortative mating for MHC in mice (Penn and Potts 1998) and in
   humans (Ober et al. 1997, Génin et al. 2000), although it is not
   seen in all studies (Hedrick and Black 1997). Multiple mechanisms
   are probably responsible for HLA diversity (Edwards and Hedrick
   1998, Meyer and Thomson 2001).</para>
 </sect1>
 
 <sect1>
  <title>HLA linkage disequilibrium</title>

  <para condition="main;anthro-book">Significant linkage
   disequilibrium (LD) between alleles at different loci is observed
   across the HLA region (see e.g., Imanishi et al. 1992, Charron
   1997). Disequilibrium is in many cases nearly complete between the
   tightly linked class II DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1 loci. For example,
   almost all DR3 haplotypes in many ethnic groups are
   DRB1*0301-DQA1*0501-DQB1*0201.  The class I B and C loci also
   exhibit very high LD, while less closely linked loci show medium
   levels of LD (e.g., class I A and B). The observed levels of
   overall LD for HLA data are incompatible with neutrality
   expectations.</para>

  <para condition="main">Huttley et al. (1999) used data
   from many laboratories on ~5000 microsatellites from <!-- the Utah
   and Amish ? --> CEPH families to examine LD levels across the
   genome of 54 independent chromosomes. They identified ten regions
   that showed higher LD than the HLA region and concluded that the
   pattern of LD was consistent with the action of natural selection
   on loci in these regions.</para>
 </sect1>

 <sect1 condition="main">
  <title>HLA associated diseases</title>
  
  <para> Genes in the HLA region are known to influence susceptibility
   to many diseases. These include complex autoimmune diseases such as
   type 1 diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis (RA), and multiple sclerosis
   (MS); Hodgkin disease and other cancers; infectious diseases
   including malaria, tuberculosis, and AIDS, and diseases of unknown
   etiology such as narcolepsy (Tiwari and Terasaki 1985, Thorsby
   1997). In some cases the HLA classical class I and II genes have
   been implicated as directly involved in disease, e.g., ankylosing
   spondylitis (class I), type 1 diabetes, RA, MS, celiac disease, and
   narcolepsy (class II). In other cases, the association with
   classical HLA genes was due to LD, as with hemochromatosis. The HLA
   associated diseases are in general genetically complex. They can
   involve multiple HLA and non-HLA loci and exhibit incomplete
   penetrance, genetic heterogeneity within the HLA region, and
   synergistic effects. Type 1 diabetes exhibits all of these features
   (Thomson 1997, 2001a). The class II genes DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1 all
   contribute to type 1 diabetes. Genetic variation additional to
   DR-DQ is also required to explain all of the HLA region
   contribution to disease.</para>

  <para>Population and evolutionary aspects of a genetic region are
   highly relevant to the study of Mendelian and complex diseases.
   These relate to our ability to localize and identify disease
   predisposing variants, and to our understanding of the mechanisms
   by which some disease predisposing genes can become relatively
   common in a population.</para>

 </sect1>
</chapter>

<!--
Local variables:
sgml-local-catalogs: ("catalog")
sgml-indent-step: 1
sgml-indent-data: 1
End:
-->