<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- <section>
<title></title>
<para><phrase role="strong">Human Genetic Variation</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Kenneth K. Kidd, Judith R. Kidd, Glenys Thomson, Diogo Meyer</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Natures of the different types of polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A terminology note</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">DNA polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para>Biallelic polymorphisms (SNPs and InDels)</para>
<para>Multiallelic polymorphisms (STRPs and VNTRs)</para>
<para>Haplotypes</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Polymorphism detection methods</phrase></para>
<para>Introduction</para>
<para>Polymerase chain reaction</para>
<para>Gel electrophoresis</para>
<para>Resequencing</para>
<para>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis</para>
<para>Denaturing high performance liquid chromatography</para>
<para>SSCP</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Typing methods</phrase></para>
<para>Gel electrophoresis-based</para>
<para>Non-gel-based</para>
<para><phrase role="strong"> Overview of the distribution of variation</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in the genome</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in populations</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in a gene of interest: &nbsp;HLA</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong"> Methods for analysis of genetic variation</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Background</phrase></para>
<para>Statistical aspects of genetics</para>
<para>Simple rules of probability</para>
<para>Likelihood and maximum likelihood</para>
<para>Genotype-phenotype relationships</para>
<para>Gene frequency in a population</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Calculation of allele frequencies and heterozygosity</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Hardy-Weinberg ratios</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Measuring genetic variation among populations</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Measuring non-randomness of alleles on chromosomes</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Tests of neutrality (or selection)</phrase></para>
<para>
<phrase role="strong">Gene mapping&#x2014;Linkage studies, TDT, etc</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">References</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">I. Natures of the different types of polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A. &nbsp;A terminology note</phrase></para>
<para> The term <emphasis>polymorphism</emphasis> means &#x201c;many forms&#x201d;. &nbsp;Thus, it applies to the gene or site in the DNA and not to a single allele. &nbsp;There is a common misuse of the term to apply to the less common allele (&#x201c;The frequency of the polymorphism was 5% in patients.&#x201d;) This is incorrect; a polymorphism does not have a frequency but does have a heterozygosity. &nbsp;Another common misuse is to apply the term to any site that varies, as in the term <emphasis>SNP</emphasis>, when nothing is known about the heterozygosity of the polymorphism. &nbsp;The term <emphasis>polymorphism</emphasis> is meant to apply to sites/genes with &#x201c;common&#x201d; variation. &nbsp;Specific guidelines differ among authors, but a common rule is that the most common allele must have a frequency of less than 99%. &nbsp;For a two-allele polymorphism, this means the less common allele has to have a frequency of at least 1%. &nbsp;If the less common allele is less frequent than this, the allele can be called a rare variant and the locus is not polymorphic.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">B. &nbsp;DNA polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para> Markers such as variation at protein and blood group loci were initially used in the analysis of genetic traits; however most were of limited use owing to low levels of variation, low heterozygosity. Early in the 1980s, these markers began to be replaced with DNA polymorphisms. &nbsp;About then was the discovery of the first restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP). &nbsp;Such polymorphisms are detected by the ability of a segment of DNA to be cut, or not, by a specific restriction enzyme that recognizes between 4-6 specific DNA base pairs and then visualized by the Southern blotting technology with a specific cloned piece of DNA used as a probe. &nbsp;Two important advances in molecular biology have since made possible the rapid development of highly informative markers for genetic mapping: the discovery of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) methodology and the discovery that microsatellite markers exist across the genome and can be PCR amplified. </para>
<para>&nbsp;There are at least two classes of polymorphic markers that we shall deal with - those that are by their nature biallelic, and those which tend to be multiallelic. &nbsp;Among the biallelic polymorphisms are single nucleotide polymorphisms and insertions (or deletions); the multiallelic polymorphisms include micro- and mini- satellites. &nbsp;There is a third class of polymorphisms that consists of combinations of two or more polymorphisms from either or both of the first two classes; these are called haplotypes. &nbsp;&nbsp;We shall describe each class separately.</para>
<para></para>
<para> 1. &nbsp;Biallelic polymorphisms &nbsp;(SNPs and InDels)</para>
<para></para>
<para> Single-nucleotide<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>polymorphisms (SNPs) are the most common type of human DNA genetic variation, occurring on average 1 per 1,000 base pairs.(See Figure I.B.1) Insertion/deletion polymorphisms are more rare, but otherwise similar analytically to SNPs. &nbsp;They are both mostly biallelic and less informative than microsatellites; however, they are more frequent, mutationally more stable than microsatellites, and more amenable to automation and DNA chip technology. &nbsp;By &#x201c;mutationally more stable&#x201d; we mean that SNPs and InDels generally can be considered as one-off events. &nbsp;That is, they are caused by a single mutational event that occurred once in the history of a species. &nbsp;We do not expect to see recurrent mutations at the same site except as extremely rare events. &nbsp;We can determine the ancestral state in almost all cases simply by determining the genotype of our nearest phylogenetic relatives, the other great apes, following the logic in Iyengar et al. (1998) (see also Hacia et al., 1999). &nbsp;In nearly all cases, we have found that we share a single allele with them, and, by inference, this is the <emphasis>ancestral</emphasis> or original allele in humans and the other allele is the <emphasis>derived</emphasis> allele. </para>
<para></para>
<para>Figure I.B.1. SNPs: Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms</para>
<para></para>
<para>The actual mutational mechanism for the two kinds of polymorphisms is different. &nbsp;A SNP is caused initially by a change of one base to another on one single chromosome of one single person in the world. &nbsp;That change is probably due to a relatively simple mistake in the cell's DNA-replicating machinery. &nbsp;Thus, for example an A (adenosine) may be substituted for a C (cytosine) in a certain position in the DNA sequence. &nbsp;As in any polymorphism, if the mutational event occurs in a germ line cell, it may be transmitted to offspring and either dropout or increase over successive generations to a detectable or polymorphic frequency in the population and species. &nbsp;In the case of an InDel, there are several mechanisms. &nbsp;A very short InDel (1-3 bp) may be caused by simple replicating mistakes just as SNPs are. &nbsp;A second type of InDel has a much more complicated mechanism of "mutation". &nbsp;These are called inserted elements and tend to be considerably longer. &nbsp;Some of these longer elements may be PolII or PolIII transcribed elements that are inserted more or less randomly into the genome. &nbsp;The inserted elements belong to various families of DNA ranging in length from perhaps 100-7,000 bp or longer and they seem to be inserted more-or-less randomly throughout the genome. &nbsp;Some of the longer elements (<emphasis>long interspersed elements,</emphasis> <emphasis>lines</emphasis>) exist in the genome 50,000 times. &nbsp;Whereas some of the shorter elements (<emphasis>short interspersed elements, sines</emphasis>) exist in the genome 500,000-1,000,000 times. &nbsp;They may be present as either <emphasis>fixed</emphasis> (present on all chromosomes) or polymorphic insertions. &nbsp;Alternatively, an element (having been inserted and becoming fixed) may be deleted on one single chromosome, and the deletion condition might rise in frequency, becoming polymorphic. &nbsp;Because some of these elements are not excised precisely, there is often a small vestige sequence left behind - a footprint. &nbsp;Thus, these "interspersed" elements may be polymorphic coming (insertions) or going (deletions). It is important to note that not all of this huge number of inserted (or inserted and subsequently deleted) elements is polymorphic - only a very small percentage of them seem to be so. &nbsp;Most of these interspersed elements were inserted long ago in primate evolution and are completely fixed in the genome of humans; only the recently inserted (or deleted) elements will possibly be polymorphic. &nbsp;&nbsp;Other InDels have other mechanisms such as unequal recombination where meiotic recombination is not perfectly symmetric and the products of recombination have a deletion on one chromosome and a corresponding insertion on the other chromosome. &nbsp;There are undoubtedly many other mechanisms. &nbsp;But these are probably the most common for SNPs and InDels.</para>
<para>SNPs are very common in the genome, probably existing at a frequency of &gt;1/1000 bp. &nbsp;InDels are thought to be less common and may occur at a similar rate to STRPs and VNTRs (see below). &nbsp;Very small indels (1 or 2 base pairs) may be more common, but still less common than SNPs. &nbsp;The commonness of SNPs makes them extremely useful in linkage and gene mapping studies. &nbsp;There will nearly always be a marker in the genomic region of interest. &nbsp;&nbsp;However, the fact that they (along with InDels) have only two alleles (and hence low heterozygosity - maximum heterozygosity = 50%) means that they will be less informative for such studies. &nbsp;"Less informative" in this context means that in many families there will be no variation at a given polymorphic site - i.e., the alleles are not segregating in those families. &nbsp;(Furthermore, Murphy's Law states that the polymorphic site nearest the gene for the trait being mapped will not vary in the most informative families for the trait.) &nbsp;In addition to their frequent occurrence, the fact that SNPs are very stable (i.e., essentially no recurrent mutations) makes them very useful for human population and evolutionary studies. &nbsp;Wherever a derived allele is seen (be it in Africa or Patagonia), that allele is identical by descent with every other such allele. &nbsp;Such identity means that these polymorphisms are very good markers of migration, admixture or random genetic drift. &nbsp;The ability to determine polarity of the polymorphism (ancestral or derived) is important to interspecies and other evolutionary studies.</para>
<para></para>
<para> 2. &nbsp;Multiallelic polymorphisms (STRPs and VNTRs)</para>
<para></para>
<para> Microsatellites consist of approximately 10&#x2014;50 copies of particular DNA sequence motifs ranging from 1-6 nucleotide base pairs that occur in tandem repetition. &nbsp;(See Figure I.B.2) These repeat sequences occur frequently and randomly across the human genome. &nbsp;When the repeat number is polymorphic, microsatellites are called <emphasis>short tandem repeat polymorphisms (STRPs).</emphasis> &nbsp;STRP loci usually have multiple alleles and high levels of variation, i.e., high heterozygosity. &nbsp;They have rapidly replaced RFLP markers in gene mapping (especially disease genes) studies owing to these features and to their ease of typing, including the small amount of template DNA required. &nbsp;Remember that heterozygosity can never exceed 50% for a biallelic marker whereas STRPs can easily have heterozygosities &gt;75%.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;Figure I.B.2. STRP: Short Tandem Repeat Polymorphism</para>
<para></para>
<para>Microsatellites are named by analogy with larger minisatellite arrays (also referred to as variable number of tandem repeats&#x2014;VNTRs). VNTRs are also highly polymorphic and powerful markers in forensic and paternity studies (DNA fingerprinting). (See Figure I.B.3) However, they are less common than STRPs and are not evenly distributed throughout the genome. Their larger sequence motifs make them less amenable to PCR technology and use in genomic screening analyses. &nbsp;STRPs and VNTRs, on the other hand, tend to be much more dynamic than the biallelic SNPs and InDels. &nbsp;The mutation rates are higher, there are more alleles, and it is usually impossible to determine which is the ancestral allele. &nbsp;Very often, if there is an STRP or VNTR at a given position in <emphasis>Homo sapiens,</emphasis> there is also an STRP or VNTR at the homologous position in the genomes of the other great apes. &nbsp;However, even when the copy number is overlapping and alleles seem to be shared between species and or genera, it has been shown (see Deinard and Kidd, 1995) that the mutations giving rise to the alleles have recurred. &nbsp;Another way of stating this is that the coalescent of the alleles is recent and distinct across the species. &nbsp;Even within humans it may be impossible to state that alleles of the same number of repeated units are &#x201c;identical by descent&#x201d; because mutations can increase and decrease the repeat number. &nbsp;In general, STRP loci with a small number of repeat units have low mutation rates and those with a large number have a higher mutation rate. This correlates with the number of alleles seen in a population and with the observations in haplotypes that a particular haplotype will be characterized by a single STRP allele when the STRP has a low number of repeats. &nbsp;[example: DRD2] &nbsp;Thus, the mutation rates for STRPs may vary by three orders of magnitude in humans. &nbsp;</para>
<para></para>
<para>&nbsp;Figure I.B.3. The DRD4 VNTR</para>
<para></para>
<para>The actual mutational mechanisms generating STRPs and VNTRs are generally poorly understood, but with some hand waving, we shall describe some possibilities. &nbsp;Both of these types of polymorphism are characterized by their tandem nature - they are multiple repetitions of either short or longer blocks of DNA several to many times. &nbsp;The most tempting explanations are that the STRPs are a "stuttering" effect of the replicating mechanism where the enzyme responsible for replicating has trouble "counting" or keeping track of how many copies of a given sequence it is making. &nbsp;The VNTRs, on the other hand, seem most likely to be caused by unequal recombination. </para>
<para>STRPs, VNTRs, and InDels occur in the genome less often than do SNPs, However, when they do occur in a region of interest, the heterozygosity of the STRPs and VNTRs can be high (often ranging from 70%-90%). &nbsp;This high average heterozygosity means that these polymorphisms are extremely informative for linkage or mapping studies. &nbsp;(That is, the polymorphism is likely to be segregating in every family of interest.) &nbsp;While the mutation rate may be high, it is generally low enough that transmission in most families will be faithful. &nbsp;On the other hand, because the mutation rate is relatively high, the utility for human population and evolutionary studies is somewhat to greatly reduced relative to that of SNPs. &nbsp;The inability to infer polarity is a disadvantage for studies of evolution (gene evolution or human evolution). &nbsp;</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">&nbsp;</phrase>3. &nbsp;Haplotypes</para>
<para></para>
<para>There is a final form of variation that we can study: &nbsp;Polymorphisms of any type can be studied individually and combined into groups of two or more polymorphisms tightly clustered on the chromosome  - <emphasis>haplotypes</emphasis>. &nbsp;If two or more polymorphisms exist in close proximity in the DNA (e.g., 1 to several thousands of bases apart), they can be studied jointly as a haplotype. &nbsp;A haplotype is the <emphasis>haploid genotype</emphasis> of the alleles at polymorphisms along a rather short stretch of the chromosome. &nbsp;For example, consider three two-allele polymorphisms: &nbsp;the first has alleles named 1 and 2, the second has alleles named A and B, and the third has alleles named 5 and 6. &nbsp;These alleles can occur on a chromosome in any of the following eight possible combinations:</para>
<para>(a) 1-A-5</para>
<para>(b) 1-B-5</para>
<para>(c) 1-A-6</para>
<para>(d) 1-B-6</para>
<para>(e) 2-A-5</para>
<para>(f) 2-B-5</para>
<para>(g) 2-A-6</para>
<para>(h) 2-B-6.</para>
<para>If alleles 1, A, and 6, for example, have been inferred from the sequence in other great apes to be ancestral, then haplotype (c) (1-A-6) is the ancestral haplotype (or ancestral chromosome); and haplotype (f) (2-B-5) is the <emphasis>triply derived</emphasis> haplotype. &nbsp;Because recombination is very infrequent in in molecularly very short regions, each of the possible haplotypes can be considered for analytic purposes as a separate allele exactly analogous to alleles at any other polymorphism (SNP, InDel, etc.). &nbsp;We can compute the haplotype frequency, haplotype heterozygosity, etc. &nbsp;Additionally, there is an aspect to haplotypes not available at single polymorphisms, <emphasis>linkage disequilibrium (LD).</emphasis> &nbsp;In the equilibrium state, allele 1 should be associated with alleles 3 and 5 exactly in proportion to their respective frequencies. &nbsp;In nature, however, equilibrium very rarely exists within sufficiently small segments of DNA. &nbsp;Thus we are afforded the opportunity to study how often and in what ways allele 1 is not randomly associated with alleles A and 5, or to study linkage disequilibrium. &nbsp;LD is, thus, a characteristic of a population, not of an individual, and is dependent on the frequencies of the alleles at each polymorphism composing the haplotype. &nbsp;Analytic methods for testing for the amount of LD and its significance will be discussed in Section III. &nbsp;Important aspects of haplotypes are that LD for a given length of DNA differs in different parts of the genome and that LD at a specific locus often differs in different populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">C. &nbsp;Polymorphism Detection Methods</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Introduction</para>
<para></para>
<para>Since all, or almost all, detection and typing methods start with the <emphasis>Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</emphasis> and involve gel electrophoresis, we shall first describe very briefly those technologies and then some of the most commonly used post-PCR procedures.</para>
<para></para>
<para><emphasis>a. &nbsp;Polymerase chain reaction. &nbsp;</emphasis>DNA is collected - with all of the problems of sample design - from cell cultures, blood samples, cheek swabs, hair follicles, forensic evidence such as skin under the nails of a victim of violence, etc., and purified from "contaminating" proteins or chemicals. In the case of humans, once that has been done one has about 6 billion bp of DNA (3x109 bp, or one haploid genome, from each parent). &nbsp;The first step is to isolate the DNA of particular interest (i.e., the polymorphic fragment) from all the rest for further scrutiny. &nbsp;The technique for this is PCR (Mullis and Faloona, 1987). &nbsp;In PCR we imitate nature <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (with several cute twists) by using the same enzyme (PolI) the cells use to replicate or repair DNA to replicate <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> millions-fold specific regions of DNA. &nbsp;The cute twists include causing the replication to begin and end at specific sites, and then amplifying the DNA between those sites dozens of times with the consequent doubling of the amount of DNA at each replication (hence "Polymerase chain reaction"). &nbsp;More specifically, the PCR reaction is:</para>
<para></para>
<para> DNA is initially and by default double stranded but the two strands are separated (denatured) by heating to a temperature of 88-100C. &nbsp;If the temperature is then lowered, the double strandedness will be reestablished (reannealing) because double strandedness is the preferred or default condition of genomic DNA. &nbsp;(Total genomic DNA will reanneal very slowly because it is very complex.) If a pair of synthetic oligonucleotides ("oligo", single stranded DNA usually about 18-24 bases long and exactly complementary to the 5' end of each strand of each fragment of DNA to be amplified), is present in the reaction tube at high concentration, the reannealing will preferentially favor the reannealing of a shorter oligonucleotides to each of the long strands rather than the reannealing of the two long complementary strands. &nbsp;The PolI enzyme will then "prime" off the end of the 3' end of the oligo and generate the second strand from "loose" nucleotides (G, A, T, and C) provided in the reaction. &nbsp;The temperature is then again raised to separate the two strands, lowered to allow reannealing of the oligos and extension once again allowed to proceed. &nbsp;Usually there are three temperatures for the complete reaction: &nbsp;94C to denature, 52-64C for oligo reannealing, and 72C for extension between the oligos. &nbsp;Another of the "cute twists" is that the enzyme, PolymeraseI, used for most of these reactions has been isolated from a bacterium, <emphasis>Thermus aquaticus,</emphasis> allowing the enzyme to retain its activity at high temperatures. (On the Life at High Temperatures by Thomas D. Brock Web site &lt;http://www.bact.wisc.edu/bact303/b27&gt; one can see a picture of the home of &nbsp;<emphasis>Thermus aquaticus.)</emphasis> </para>
<para></para>
<para>That, in a nutshell is PCR, and it is at this point that one of the many errors in polymorphism typing can occur. &nbsp;If one is typing an InDel, VNTR, or STRP of a heterozygous individual whose two alleles differ considerably in length (i.e., 300 bp more or less), it often happens that there is preferential PCR amplification of the shorter allele. &nbsp;In such a case, all homozygotes - long or short - will amplify properly, but all or some heterozygotes will amplify as homozygotes of the shorter type. &nbsp;&nbsp;For these and other errors of typing, there are often laboratory methods that can be used to minimize them, if they are detected. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;We shan&#x2019;t discuss those methods here, however we shall describe in Section III some of the statistical methods of determining whether some of the systematic typing errors may have occurred. </para>
<para>Having amplified to abundance the particular fragment of DNA that contains the polymorphism of interest, it is now necessary to detect which alleles are in each sample - to type the samples. &nbsp;There are at least three major techniques for typing the PCRed samples: &nbsp;Many of the detection and typing methods utilize gel electrophoresis.</para>
<para></para>
<para><emphasis>b. &nbsp;Gel electrophoresis (agarose or acrylamide)</emphasis>. &nbsp;Gel electrophoresis is probably the oldest and still most commonly used method of separating two DNA fragments of differing length (InDels, VNTRs, and STRPs). &nbsp;The technique depends on the fact that DNA carries a negative charge and that various gel matrices have specific sieving qualities. &nbsp;In practice DNA (in our case the PCR product) is applied to one end of a gel and a direct current is applied across the gel. &nbsp;The DNA is pushed/pulled though the gel from the negative pole toward the positive pole. &nbsp;Larger fragments move more slowly than smaller fragments and two fragments will separate in the matrix over time in the current. &nbsp;It remains only to stain the DNA so that the fragments can be visualized and photographed. &nbsp;</para>
<para>There is a vast number of detection methods that range in complexity, comprehensiveness, time required, and expense. &nbsp;They include sequencing, DHPLC, DGGE, SSCP and many others. </para>
<para></para>
<para>Resequencing</para>
<para></para>
<para>Of course the most obvious and comprehensive method of polymorphism detection is <emphasis>resequencing </emphasis>a number of people for a given region of the genome and simply noting every difference in the sequences. &nbsp;There is an increasingly used variant of the resequencing method - <emphasis>in silico </emphasis>resequencing. &nbsp;<emphasis>In silico</emphasis> resequencing is data mining of the public databases. &nbsp;Wherever two or more independent clones have been sequenced, the two (or more) sequences can be compared and differences tested for polymorphism. &nbsp;As noted earlier, the sequence difference itself is not necessarily a polymorphism; the frequencies in the population determine whether it is a polymorphic site. Very often the sequence differences arise from an underlying error rate in the sequencing procedure or from the accidental sequence of a very rare variant. &nbsp;In those cases, of course, no polymorphism exists. &nbsp;Nevertheless, a fair number of the discrepant sequences result from real polymorphic differences between the clone donors. &nbsp;Strategy for resequencing (e.g., number of different samples, origin of the samples, length of the sequence) is determined by the specific research questions being posed. &nbsp;Examples: (1) If variation is found by resequencing only a few samples, that variation is likely to be present at high frequency in the population in which it was found. &nbsp;The smaller the sample, the higher the heterozygosity is likely to be - polymorphisms involving uncommon alleles (and/or variants) are likely to be missed. &nbsp;Conversely, the larger the sample, the more likely one is to find polymorphisms, even if they have low heterozygosity in the population. &nbsp;(2) The population origin of the samples to be resequenced also determines the number of polymorphisms found, but in a different way: On average, samples from Africa will contain more variation than samples from Europe, Europe more than those from East Asia, and East Asia more than those from native Americans. &nbsp;Not only does the amount of variation decrease with increasing distance from Africa, but the variation that does exist is largely a successive subsetting of that in Africa. If the study is one of a particular population, it might be best to look for variation in that population. &nbsp;If, on the other hand, the study requires variation in all populations around the world, it might be best to search for the polymorphisms in aboriginal Americans. &nbsp;(3) Length of the sequence is often determined by less theoretical and more physical factors. &nbsp;For example, if coding sequence variation is of most interest, the length of the sequence will be determined by the length of an exon or of a cDNA clone. &nbsp;More basically, length may be determined by the maximum length possible with a given sequencing technology, etc.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) </emphasis>detects polymorphisms by taking advantage of the capacity of DNA to form <emphasis>heteroduplexes.</emphasis> &nbsp;A heteroduplex is a chimeric double stranded DNA. &nbsp;During the course of PCR, the double stranded DNA is denatured into two single strands. &nbsp;Since each person has two copies of his/her DNA (one from the mother, <emphasis>M</emphasis>, and one from the father, <emphasis>F) </emphasis>and each is double stranded, each individual&#x2019;s DNA will thus contain four single strands of DNA upon denaturation. &nbsp;If these strands are allowed to slowly reanneal, (or renature), the products will be <emphasis>MM, MF, FM, </emphasis>and <emphasis>FF. &nbsp;</emphasis>The MM and FF products are <emphasis>homoduplexes</emphasis> and the MF (or FM) products are <emphasis>heteroduplexes. </emphasis>&nbsp;The homoduplexes contain no mismatches. &nbsp;The heteroduplex, however, may contain one (or more) mismatches if the individual is a heterozygote&#x2014;that is, if the individual received one allele from the mother and a different allele from the father. &nbsp;If the heteroduplex contains a mismatch, the DNA will denature at a lower temperature than will a homoduplex or a heteroduplex without a mismatch. &nbsp;Denaturation can be promoted chemically as well as by termperature and the denaturation is dependent on concentration of the denaturing compound (in the case of DGGE, urea). &nbsp;Reannealed DNA is loaded on a gradient gel with the urea concentration in the gel increasing with distance from the origin. &nbsp;Electrophoresis is begun and as the DNA migrates through the matrix, it will eventually reach the place in the matrix where the urea concentration is high enough to begin to denature the DNA. &nbsp;When denaturation begins, the DNA is immobilized in &nbsp;the matrix. &nbsp;If the DNA is perfectly complementary, the denaturation point will be further along than if there is a mismatch in the heteroduplex. &nbsp;The DNA in the matrix (gel or column) can be stained and the distance the DNA progressed through the gel determined. &nbsp;The heteroduplex DNA of a heterozygote will be stalled in the gel at a point closer to the origin than will the homoduplexes, and a variant will thus be detected. &nbsp;</para>
<para></para>
<para>Denaturing high performance liquid chromatography</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Denaturing High Pressure Liquid Chromatography (DHPLC)</emphasis>(Xiao and Oefner, 2001)<emphasis> </emphasis>also depends on the formation of heteroduplexes, but DHPLC is non-gel based. &nbsp;In DHPLC a capillary tube is packed with tiny alkylated particles. &nbsp;DNA is injected into the column and forced chemically and electrically through the column; under certain chemical conditions double stranded DNA will be retained by the column and single stranded DNA will elute through the column. &nbsp;Additionally, under completely denaturing conditions, the double stranded DNAs will not only remain in the column, but will be separated in the column based on sequence content as well as length, allowing discrimination of the two homozygotes. &nbsp;Detection is by laser induced fluorescence.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Single Strand Conformation Polymorphisms</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Single Strand Conformation Polymorphisms (SSCP)</emphasis> is both the name of the method and the name of the type of polymorphism detected. &nbsp;SSCP depends on the formation of secondary structure by single stranded DNA&#x2014;it folds back on itself, forming loops. &nbsp;This secondary structure will cause the DNA to slow its movement through a gel during electrophoresis. &nbsp;When single stranded or denatured DNA (PCR product of an individual sample) is loaded onto a gel and electrophoresis begun, the DNA enters the gel and eventually begins to form secondary structure. &nbsp;If the different strands of DNA have different sequences, the secondary structures will be slightly different and, consequently, mobility over distance in the gel will be different. &nbsp;Thus, mobility differences between the single strands of an individual or among individuals will be indicative of variation within the specific PCR product.</para>
<para></para>
<para> There are many other methods of detecting polymorphisms and more are coming on line every day. &nbsp;Most of them use principles described above. &nbsp;</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">D. &nbsp;Typing methods</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para> Almost any way used to discover polymorphisms can be used also to type those polymorphisms in individuals. &nbsp;However, most of the methods for detection mentioned above are generally far too costly (time and money) for high throughput and the interpretation of results are also very time consuming. &nbsp;Many other methods of typing have been developed and we shall describe some of them here.</para>
<para></para>
<para>1. &nbsp;Gel electrophoresis-based typing</para>
<para></para>
<para>As described above gel electrophoresis is used to force DNA through a gel-like matrix. &nbsp;DNA is inserted into a well in the gel near the positive pole and the negatively charged DNA will migrate through the gel from the negative pole toward the positive pole. &nbsp;When DNA fragments are of varying length, they will migrate across the field at varying speeds with the longer fragments of DNA migrating more slowly through the gel than shorter fragments. &nbsp;All the DNA of the same length remains in a tight band as it migrates through the gel. &nbsp;The amount of separation between different size fragments (bands) of DNA will depend on the sieving qualities of the gel, relative size differences of the DNA fragments, and amount and duration of the current. &nbsp;Many polymorphisms are length polymorphisms (STRPs, VNTRs, InDels), and the regions containing such polymorphisms can be PCR amplified and the products run on a gel. &nbsp;The various alleles will separate under gel electrophoresis gels, and it remains only to devise a way to visualize the differences in length of the DNA in the gel. &nbsp;Since intercalating dyes such as Cybr Green and Ethidium Bromide will cause DNA to fluoresce under UV light allowing the DNA in a gel to be visualized directly under UV light. &nbsp;Sometimes the size differences are so small that UV discrimination is not possible. &nbsp;In those cases the gel matrix can be changed to polyacrylamide which has much finer sieving qualities, and one end of the DNA fragments can be labeled, with a fluor. &nbsp;In this way very tiny size differences can be visualized.</para>
<para></para>
<para>There is at last one pitfall in gel based typing: &nbsp;The co-migration of two bands. &nbsp;Sometimes either oligos will prime products from two regions of the genome (due to homology of the oligos to more than a single location in the genome.). &nbsp;The may often be the case when DNA from a gene family is being amplified. &nbsp;If the co-amplified DNA is of the same length as one of the expected alleles in the deliberately amplified DNA, the end result in a gel is that we will see correctly the homozygotes with the co-migrating band as homozygotes, all heterozygotes will correctly appear as heterozygotes, however the homozygote of the type without the co-migrating band will appear to the a heterozygote. &nbsp;A second type of gel error can occur especially when the size difference between alleles is very small - one, two, or three bases. &nbsp;There are certain gel matrices (such as polyacrylamide) that have extremely fine sieving qualities - so fine that single base differences in size can be discerned. &nbsp;When such gels are used, gel to gel differences may make discrimination of alleles very close in size difficult or make identifying two identical alleles on different gels problematic. &nbsp;When there is not a difference in size between two alleles (SNP), it is sometimes possible to induce a difference that will be detectably by gel electrophoresis as described above for InDels, VNTRs and STRPs. &nbsp;As we said earlier, an SNP, the most common type of polymorphism, is a single base pair change at a specific site in the DNA. Enzymes (called <emphasis>restriction enzymes </emphasis>exist in nature that recognize and cut DNA at very specific short sequences (usually 4-12 bp and often palindromic). If the changed site either produces or abolishes a restriction site, one can use the enzyme to reduce the size of the allele containing the site relative to the allele that does not contain the site and proceed with gel electrophoresis as described above. &nbsp;Polymorphisms recognized in this way are a subset of SNPs - <emphasis>restriction fragment length polymorphisms (RFLPs).</emphasis> (See Figure I.D.1). &nbsp;Unfortunately, there is also a possible error associated with this procedure: The restriction enzyme reaction may not proceed to completion (i.e., not all of the fragments with the restriction are actually cut). &nbsp;The effect of this incomplete reaction (or <emphasis>partial digestion)</emphasis> is that all homozygotes of the large size fragment will be scored correctly, all heterozygotes will be scored correctly, however the homozygotes of the smaller size fragment will be scored as heterozygotes (because some of the fragments that should have been shortened by the enzyme were not). &nbsp;</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>2. &nbsp;Non-gel typing methods</para>
<para></para>
<para>Among the PCR but non-gel based methods of typing polymorphisms are some that are particularly useful when there is neither a size difference between alleles nor is a size difference inducible by restriction enzyme. &nbsp;These include a number of procedures based on differential florescent color tagging of the two alleles: <emphasis>Florescence polarization (FP)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>TaqMan.</emphasis></para>
<para>Florescence polarization depends on the ability of perfectly complementary single stranded DNAs to anneal with each other and of Taq polymerase to extend from primers. &nbsp;PCR as described above is again the first step in FP typing. &nbsp;The PCR product is purged of leftover reagents from the PCR reaction and fluor-labeled single base nucleotides - each different nucleotide is labeled with a different colored fluor - are added to the reaction along with a synthetic oligo very similar to those used for PCR; however, this oligo ends at, but does not include, the polymorphic site. &nbsp;With the addition of a special polymerase and cycling the temperatures to denature (separate the double strands of the DNA) and anneal, the enzyme extends off the oligo by adding the base <emphasis>(single base extension)</emphasis> that is complementary to the specific allele(s) present. &nbsp;Detection of what color base has been added depends on the effect of anchoring a fluor to the DNA compared to that fluor loose in the solution. If a fluor is anchored by being incorporated into the sequence of the oligo, laser light passed through it is polarized; if the fluor is not anchored onto an oligo, the light passes through it unpolarized. &nbsp;The ratio of polarized to unpolarized light determines which base was added to fill in the polymorphic site. &nbsp;In any given reaction, if only one fluor is polarized, that sample is a homozygote and the type of homozygote is determined by the color of the polarized fluor (that is the wavelength or the polarized signal). &nbsp;If there are two different fluors that are polarized, the individual is a heterozygote.</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>DASH </emphasis>is a non-gel-based SNP typing system (Howell et al., 1999) that depends on the property of certain dyes (e.g., Cybr green or Ethidium Bromide) to intercalate <emphasis>double stranded DNA, </emphasis>and to fluoresce only when intercalated and stimulated with UV light. &nbsp;In the DASH procedure, two 20 to 25 bp long synthetic oligos are designed to compliment each of the alleles exactly. &nbsp;The oligos are designed such that the variable site is in the middle. &nbsp;Then very short DNA fragments (about 50 bp) are PCR amplified with the variable site also in the middle. &nbsp;The typing is done in duplicate with one oligo (identical to one of the alleles) used in one reaction and the other allele-specific oligo used in the other. &nbsp;The PCR product is denatured (caused to become single stranded), and the allowed to anneal to one of the allele-specific oligos. &nbsp;&nbsp;The resulting product will fluoresce under UV light. &nbsp;The temperature of the reaction is then slowly raised until the oligo denatures (or drops off) causing the dye to cease to fluoresce. &nbsp;&nbsp;The temperature at which the oligo denatures depends on how well matched the oligo is to the PCR product. &nbsp;If there is a mismatch in the oligo at the variable site, the oligo denatures at a lower temperature than if the match is perfect. &nbsp;The procedure is repeated with the second allele-specific oligo. &nbsp;If the sample being typed is a homozygote matching the first oligo, when that oligo is used the fluorescence will disappear at a high (relatively) temperature when the first oligo is annealed and heated and at a lower temperature if the second oligo is annealed and heated. &nbsp;If the sample being typed is from a heterozygote, the fluorescence will significantly decrease at a lower temperature and then disappear altogether at a higher temperature in both reactions. &nbsp;If the sample being typed is a homozygote matching the second allele-specific oligo, the fluorescence will disappear altogether at a lower temperature in the reaction with the first allele-specific oligo and in the second reaction with the second allele-specific oligo disappear altogether at a higher temperature. &nbsp;The amount of fluorescence is measured continuously as the temperature is gradually raised and the second derivative of the fluorescence and temperature is plotted. &nbsp;A homozygote has a single high peak in the reaction with the perfectly matching oligo and a single low peak in the reaction with the mismatching oligo; and a heterozygote has two peaks&#x2014;one at each temperature in both reactions.</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>TaqMan</emphasis> is a method of typing SNPs developed by ABI that takes advantage of the annealing properties of perfectly matched DNA and the capacity of quencher dye in close proximity to a fluor to quench the fluor&#x2019;s signal. &nbsp;PCR of the region containing the site to be typed proceeds in the usual way, except that there is an additional oligo in the reaction mix. &nbsp;This extra oligo is designed to be allele-specific in that it is a perfect complement of one of the alleles being typed. &nbsp;In addition, the primer has a fluor on one end and a quencher on the other. &nbsp;Initially the fluor and quencher are in close proximity because the distance between them is maintain constant and close by the primer to which they are both attached - the fluor does not fluoresce. &nbsp;During the annealing phase of the PCR cycle, this third primer anneals perfectly to the sequence it complements. &nbsp;If there is no perfect complement in the reaction, the oligo will not anneal. &nbsp;During the extension phase, the Taq Polymerase that generates the product from the template DNA, upon coming to an oligo annealed to the strand it is amplifying, will &#x201c;chew&#x201d; away, or cleave, the interfering oligo, thus separating the quencher from the fluor. &nbsp;This is repeated at every cycle. &nbsp;By the end of the PCR cycling, if the sample DNA contains the allele complementing the allele-specific oligo, the reaction mix will fluoresce in the wavelength of the fluor attached to the allele-specific oligo. &nbsp;This detection procedure can be done in duplicate with a single allele-specific oligo in each reaction, or it can be done in a single reaction with both allele-specific oligos, each with a different fluor.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The use of <emphasis>microarrays</emphasis> is one of the most potentially useful methods of high throughput typing coming on line today. &nbsp;For polymorphism typing, microarrays are a still-emerging technology so not all the details are worked out yet. &nbsp;However a thumbnail sketch of microarray typing once again would start with PCR reactions, or PCR reactions multiplexed with several sets of primers in one tube with DNA from one individual. &nbsp;This pool of PCR products for each individual is then micro-spotted at high density such that there may be as many as 6,000 spots of pooled DNA on a single 1 x 3 inch slide. &nbsp;This could correspond to duplicate spots of DNA from 3,000 samples. &nbsp;&nbsp;Slides can be made in duplicate, triplicate or however many as necessary for the number of PCR products in each individual DNA PCR product pool. &nbsp;Once again we shall rely on fluor-labeling in different colors of fluor. &nbsp;This time, however, we would add two oligos to the mix, each with a different color fluor attached directly to the fluor. &nbsp;The two oligos are designed such that the final base at the 3' end of the oligo corresponds to one or the other of the variable bases in the polymorphism. &nbsp;If conditions are perfect, the oligo will only anneal to the DNA with an exact match. &nbsp;Thus, either oligos of one color will anneal (homozygote), oligos of both colors will anneal (heterozygote), or only oligos of the second color will anneal (the opposite homozygote). &nbsp;The excess reagents are washed off, and the slide is read by a microreader. &nbsp;Because multiple copies of the slides are made of pooled samples, a second, third, fourth, etc. set of oligos can be <emphasis>hybridized</emphasis> to the second, third, fourth, etc. slide.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">II. &nbsp;Overview of the distribution of variation</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Patterns of variation may be may be considered in several ways - across the genome, in or between populations, or in a particular locus/gene of interest. &nbsp;In the first case it is the genomic location of the polymorphism (telomeric, centromeric, intragenic, in areas of particular nucleotide content, etc.) that is of interest. &nbsp;In the second case, it is the frequency of the alleles in different populations around the world - populations of higher or lower endogamy, more or less admixture, defined geographically, linguistically, by self-report, or in any other way - that is of interest. &nbsp;And in the third case, variation in a gene may cause a disorder or susceptibility to a disorder, may be important in personal identification, or may even be selectively advantageous.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A. Variation in the genome</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Much work is ongoing to identify sites of variation in the human genome. &nbsp;The number of sites in the genome that show variation among individuals is in the millions. &nbsp;The SNP Consortium and others have identified more than 2 million sites across the genome with variation. &nbsp;Work is ongoing to determine whether the variation is polymorphic with an appreciable heterozygosity or whether one of the forms seen is just a rare variant (or even a sequencing error). &nbsp;Databases such as dbSNP &lt;http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/SNP/index.html&gt;, The SNP Consortium &lt;http://SNP.cshl.org/index.html&gt;, and HGBASE &lt;http://hgbase.cgr.ki.se/&gt; all maintain and regularly update information on SNPs and other polymorphisms. &nbsp;There are other types of variation  -  STRPs, VNTRs  - that are not so routinely cataloged in these databases but can be found in GDB &lt;http://www.gdb.org/gdb/gdbtop.html&gt; and the Marshfield database &lt;http://research.marshfieldclinic.org/genetics&gt;, for example. &nbsp;Moreover, most of the SNP surveys are based on relatively few individuals; consequently, many less common variants or variants restricted to particular groups or peoples in a specific geographic region may not have been found. &nbsp;Conversely, some of the SNPs found could be based on observing a very rare variant and not be likely to show variation in subsequent samples. &nbsp;In fact, both under- and over-counting do occur. &nbsp;It is possible that virtually every nucleotide varies at least once among the 6 billion humans = 12 billion genomes present on the earth. &nbsp;A more relevant question than how many sites vary is how many sites show common variation. &nbsp;That question is unanswerable as yet, but the number is certainly large. &nbsp;But, what is meant by <emphasis>common</emphasis>? &nbsp;The appropriate measure for quantifying variation at a site is heterozygosity.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Heterozygosity may be measured as either the <emphasis>observed</emphasis> proportion of heterozygotes in a population, or that proportion <emphasis>expected</emphasis> based on Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and given the allele frequency. &nbsp;This estimate for the population is easily calculated as <emphasis>2pq</emphasis> for a biallelic locus or as <emphasis>1-&#x3a3;p</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>i</subscript></emphasis><emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> for a multiallelic locus. &nbsp;The value of a polymorphism as a research tool depends on the type of study to be undertaken but in general heterozygosities should be greater than 0.2 for a marker to be very useful. &nbsp;Because SNPs are biallelic, the largest heterozygosity for a single SNP is 0.5. &nbsp;For multiallelic polymorphisms, such as the STRPs, heterozygosities can be &gt;0.7 and some are &gt;0.9 because there are many distinguishable alleles and none is very common.</para>
<para></para>
<para>While the global level of variation and the numbers of common variants cannot yet be addressed precisely, the average level of variation in a European population has been addressed in various studies. &nbsp;The standard way to measure overall amounts of variation is as nucleotide diversity, often represented by &#x3c0; (Nei and Li, 1979; see also Li, 1997). &nbsp;This is the probability that in two copies of a DNA sequence taken at random from the population a specific nucleotide position will have two different nucleotides. &nbsp;It is logically analogous to heterozygosity in individuals &#x2013; the probability that the maternal copy of a gene, the one inherited from one's mother, differs from the paternal copy of the gene, the one inherited from one's father. &nbsp;Alternatively, nucleotide diversity can be considered to be the average number of nucleotide differences per site between two randomly chosen sequences. &nbsp;Numerous estimates of &#x3c0; in global samples of modern humans have now been generated (reviewed in Przeworski et al. 2000, Wall and Przeworski 2000; Yu et al. 2001), with consistent estimates falling near the early value of 0.11% as estimated by Li and Sadler (1979). &nbsp;This would translate to an average of one heterozygous site every 900 basepairs in an individual. &nbsp;Polymorphic nucleotide positions would occur even more commonly in the population since any one site will be homozygous at least half the time. &nbsp;(Because SNPs are biallelic, the largest heterozygosity for a single SNP is 0.5.) &nbsp;Clearly, there is a great deal of DNA sequence variation that is common and normal. &nbsp;In the context of this common normal variation neither allele can be considered "wild type". &nbsp;Only in the context of rare, usually deleterious, mutations is the normal allele the "wild type".</para>
<para></para>
<para>As genomic locations and heterozygosities in at least some populations are known, researchers are beginning to address questions of how the variation is distributed around the genome and how the variation is organized in local regions of the genome.</para>
<para></para>
<para>There have been recent reports that mutations (the ultimate source of most polymorphisms) tend to occur in regions of high recombination. &nbsp;One might infer, therefore, that polymorphisms should aggregate in regions of high recombination. &nbsp;There is not much data as yet on this subject.</para>
<para></para>
<para>In several recent papers the question of how the variation is organized in local regions of the genome has been addressed (Daly et al., 2001; Reich et al., 2001). &nbsp;The general finding is that across short segments of DNA, on the order of 10 kilobases, varying sites are associated so that chromosomes with a particular allele at one site will tend to have some particular allele at each of the other sites within the region. &nbsp;This non-random arrangement of DNA variants along the chromosome is referred to as linkage disequilibrium (LD). &nbsp;The particular combinations of alleles at the nearby sites are called haplotypes. &nbsp;Interestingly, the evidence for European populations is that only a small number of the combinations of alleles, i.e., haplotypes, actually occurs and a subset of those accounts for &gt;90% of all copies in the population. &nbsp;However, the span of this set of associated markers appears to have discrete boundaries defining blocks of sequence with strong LD within the block but essentially no LD between the blocks. &nbsp;The length of a block of DNA showing strong LD appears to be different for different parts of the DNA; some blocks can extend for over 100 kb. &nbsp;An active area of research currently is how general these initial findings are for different parts of the genome and for different populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> As an example of linkage disequilibrium and haplotypes, consider the following. &nbsp;For three SNPs with equal allele frequencies, p<subscript>i</subscript> = q<subscript>i </subscript>&nbsp;= 0.5, there are 8 (=2<superscript>3</superscript>) possible haplotypes at equal frequencies of 1/8 if there is no linkage disequilibrium. &nbsp;If there is LD, then some of those haplotypes occur more frequently than expected by chance and others less frequently, even absent.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">B. &nbsp;Variation among populations</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para> Discussions of how many sites show common variation, how much variation there is at a specific site, how variation is distributed along the genome, and how variation is organized in locally are all population dependent. &nbsp;In all areas for which we have information different populations differ. &nbsp;Table II.B.1 gives the allele frequencies in 33 populations from around the world. &nbsp;The frequency of the Rsa+ allele (restriction site present) varies from high values &gt;90% in African and Native American populations to low values of &lt;20% in some East Asian populations. &nbsp;The heterozygosity at this site varies from zero (the Rsa+ allele is fixed, i.e., the Rsa- allele is not seen) up to 0.47, close to the maximum possible value of 50%. &nbsp;Clearly, any quantitative measures of allele frequency or heterozygosity for this polymorphic site must reference some specific population.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Table II.B.1. RsaI restriction site polymorphism at ADH1B. This is an example of gene frequency variation among populations for a SNP in an intron (non-coding segment). The Fst for this site is 0.409 which is unusually large, probably because selection has operated on a nearby coding region SNP. The ANCESTOR is inferred (Iyengar et al., 1998) based on the identical sequence chimpanzees gorillas, and organutans.</para>
<para></para>
<para> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;2N &nbsp;f(Rsa+) f(Rsa-) &nbsp;het</para>
<para> 0 ANCESTOR &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;1.0 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;0 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">AFRICA</phrase></para>
<para> 1 Biaka Pygmy &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;138 &nbsp;&nbsp;.935 &nbsp;.065 &nbsp;.122</para>
<para> 2 Mbuti Pygmies &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;78 &nbsp;&nbsp;.974 &nbsp;.026 &nbsp;.051</para>
<para> 3 Yoruba &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;144 &nbsp;&nbsp;.986 &nbsp;.014 &nbsp;.028</para>
<para> 4 Ibo &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;96 &nbsp;&nbsp;.979 &nbsp;.021 &nbsp;.041</para>
<para> 5 Hausa &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;74 &nbsp;&nbsp;.919 &nbsp;.081 &nbsp;.149</para>
<para> 6 Ethiopian Jews &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;62 &nbsp;&nbsp;.903 &nbsp;.097 &nbsp;.176</para>
<para> 7 African Amer &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;178 &nbsp;&nbsp;.893 &nbsp;.107 &nbsp;.191</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">MIDDLE EAST</phrase></para>
<para> 8 Yemenite Jews &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;78 &nbsp;&nbsp;.910 &nbsp;.090 &nbsp;.164</para>
<para> 9 Druze Unrelated &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;144 &nbsp;&nbsp;.736 &nbsp;.264 &nbsp;.389</para>
<para>10 Samaritans &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;78 &nbsp;&nbsp;.731 &nbsp;.269 &nbsp;.393</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">EUROPE</phrase></para>
<para>11 Adygei &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;104 &nbsp;&nbsp;.721 &nbsp;.279 &nbsp;.402</para>
<para>12 Russians, Vologda &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;94 &nbsp;&nbsp;.745 &nbsp;.255 &nbsp;.380</para>
<para>13 Finns &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;64 &nbsp;&nbsp;.812 &nbsp;.188 &nbsp;.305</para>
<para>14 Danes (unrelateds) &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;96 &nbsp;&nbsp;.688 &nbsp;.312 &nbsp;.429</para>
<para>15 Irish &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;190 &nbsp;&nbsp;.795 &nbsp;.205 &nbsp;.326</para>
<para>16 Eur.Mixed &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;182 &nbsp;&nbsp;.692 &nbsp;.308 &nbsp;.426</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">EAST ASIA</phrase></para>
<para>17 Chinese, S.F. &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;108 &nbsp;&nbsp;.185 &nbsp;.815 .302</para>
<para>18 Chinese, Taiwan &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;98 &nbsp;&nbsp;.143 &nbsp;.857 &nbsp;.245</para>
<para>19 Hakka &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;84 &nbsp;&nbsp;.190 &nbsp;.810 &nbsp;.308</para>
<para>20 Japanese &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;98 &nbsp;&nbsp;.153 &nbsp;.847 &nbsp;.259</para>
<para>21 Ami &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;80 &nbsp;&nbsp;.350 &nbsp;.650 &nbsp;.455</para>
<para>22 Atayal &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;84 &nbsp;&nbsp;.179 &nbsp;.821 &nbsp;.294</para>
<para>23 Cambodians &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;48 &nbsp;&nbsp;.396 &nbsp;.604 &nbsp;.478</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">PACIFIC</phrase></para>
<para>24 Nasioi Melanesians &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;46 &nbsp;&nbsp;.696 &nbsp;.304 &nbsp;.423</para>
<para>25 Micronesians &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;64 &nbsp;&nbsp;.625 &nbsp;.375 &nbsp;.469</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">SIBERIA</phrase></para>
<para>26 Yakut &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;98 &nbsp;&nbsp;.755 &nbsp;.245 &nbsp;.185</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">NORTH AMERICA</phrase></para>
<para>27 Cheyenne &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;112 &nbsp;&nbsp;.982 &nbsp;.018 &nbsp;.035</para>
<para>28 Pima, Arizona &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;100 &nbsp;&nbsp;1.00 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;0 &nbsp;0</para>
<para>29 Pima, Mexico unrelated &nbsp;104 &nbsp;&nbsp;.942 &nbsp;.058 &nbsp;.109</para>
<para>30 Maya &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;102 &nbsp;&nbsp;.990 &nbsp;.010 &nbsp;.02</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">SOUTH AMERICA</phrase></para>
<para>31 Ticuna &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;132 &nbsp;&nbsp;1.00 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;0 &nbsp;0</para>
<para>32 Rondonian Surui &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;84 &nbsp;&nbsp;1.00 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;0 &nbsp;0</para>
<para>33 Karitiana &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;106 &nbsp;&nbsp;1.00 &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;0 0</para>
<para></para>
<para> When we consider the average heterozygosity for a single population, averaging across many different polymorphic loci, we see a general pattern of greatest heterozygosity in the sub-Saharan African populations with average heterozygosity among non-African populations decreasing with increasing distance from Africa. &nbsp;The lowest average heterozygosity is seen in small isolated populations and in South American populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> In general, one can quantify the variation among populations as the standardized variance, F<subscript>st</subscript>, calculated as &#x3c3;<subscript>p</subscript><superscript>2</superscript>/(), where &nbsp;and &nbsp;are the average allele frequencies among the populations and &#x3c3;<subscript>p</subscript><superscript>2</superscript> is the variance of the allele frequency across the populations studied. &nbsp;Note, even for this measure of variation the value will depend on the set of populations for which allele frequencies are available. &nbsp;F<subscript>st</subscript> is basically the ratio of the variation at a locus in one population compared to the average variation at that locus across all the populations - it is, thus, a measure of the <emphasis>interpopulation</emphasis> difference for a given polymorphic locus, or the ability of that polymorphism to discriminate between populations. &nbsp;F<subscript>st</subscript> can range in value from 0 (which occurs when all populations have exactly the same allele frequency) to 1 when each population is at fixation (that is, has an allele frequency of 1.0) but different populations are fixed for different alleles.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The range of F<subscript>st</subscript> values for nearly 100 SNPs across 33 populations (the same ones that are in Table II.B.1) is 0.04 to nearly 0.4. &nbsp;Figures II.B.1 and II.B.2 give examples of allele frequency variation for the 4 SNPs with the lowest F<subscript>st</subscript> values and the 4 SNPs with the highest F<subscript>st</subscript> values. &nbsp;The frequency of one allele at each biallelic locus is presented in the graphs. &nbsp;Because these 33 populations originate from around the world, it is likely that this range is representative of the global range for neutral variation affected only by random genetic drift. &nbsp;The F<subscript>st</subscript> values for all such loci form a single distribution.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.1.</phrase> Population variation for SNPs with low interpopulation variation. The Fst values are 0.041 for D4S10 TaqI"A", 0.046 for HOXB4 MspI, 0.049 for D13S2PstI, and 0.052 for DBH MwoI"A".</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.2.</phrase> Population variation for SNPs with high interpopulation variation. The Fst values are 0.255 for D4S10 Hind3"b", 0.268 for DRD2 Taq "d", 0.295 for PAH XmnI, and 0.374 for MSO-1 AvaI.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Haplotype frequencies vary among populations just as allele frequencies at individual sites. &nbsp;Populations that are geographically close tend to have similar haplotype frequencies. &nbsp;Figure II.B.3 shows the haplotype frequencies for different regions of the world for haplotypes at PAH based on six polymorphic sites spanning the gene. &nbsp;Linkage disequilibrium also varies among populations as a function of several factors, several of which involve the demography - past and present - of the populations and even of the ancestral populations of present day populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.3</phrase>. &nbsp;PAH 6-site haplotype frequencies by geographic region. &nbsp;The number of populations in each region is given in parentheses. &nbsp;The alleles comprising each haplotype are listed in the order of the sites across the gene.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Our observations on the molecular extent of disequilibrium in various regions of the genome and in various populations are the opposite of the average heterozygosity variation around the world. &nbsp;The molecular extent tends to be shortest in African populations and longest in Native American populations, as was seen at PAH (Kidd et al., 2000). &nbsp;Other factors are also operating such that LD extends over shorter intervals in all populations near telomeres and longer intervals near centomeres, though there are exceptions. &nbsp;Biological factors that may be responsible for the genomic distribution of variation and LD include many that are positional (such as whether the DNA is coding or non-coding regions, intragenic or intergenic).</para>
<para></para>
-->

<appendix>
  <appendixinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
	<firstname>Glenys</firstname>
	<surname>Thomson</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>Diogo</firstname>
	<surname>Meyer</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>Kristie</firstname>
	<surname>Mather</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>Jill</firstname>
	<surname>Hollenbach</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </appendixinfo>

  <title>The HLA region</title>

    <para>Here we give a summary of the HLA (human leukocyte antigen)
     system in humans, the major histocompatiblity complex (MHC) in
     humans. The HLA classical class I and II genes are a set of
     closely linked, highly polymorphic genes involved in the immune
     response. The HLA genes also influence susceptibility to over 200
     diseases, including autoimmune diseases, cancers, and infectious
     diseases. A number of functional and population features
     implicate selection as an important factor maintaining the
     extensive HLA variation. Although the precise nature of this
     selection is not known, response to a wide variety of pathogens
     is believed to be a major evolutionary pressure. Recent advances
     in genomics, combined with increasing knowledge of
     structure-function of HLA molecules, provides new tools for
     exploring HLA polymorphism and an opportunity to address
     fundamental questions about HLA sequence variation, immunity, and
     disease. Such detailed information has not previously been
     available and is critical for a complete understanding of the
     immune system, autoimmune and infectious diseases,
     transplantation, and development of T-cell therapies and
     vaccines.</para>

    <sect1>
      <title>Map of region</title>

      <para> The HLA region maps to ch. 6p21.31. It consists of 3.6 Mb
      of DNA and contains 224 identified genes, 128 of which are
      predicted to be expressed, arranged in three major gene clusters
      (The MHC Sequencing Consortium 1999, Rhodes and Trowsdale
      1999). Only some of the HLA region genes are involved in the
      immune response. Much of our interest is in the HLA classical
      class I (A, B, and C) (1.8 Mb) and class II (DR, DQ, and DP)
      (1.2 Mb) genes, which flank the class III region (see
      <xref linkend="hla-map.figure"/>).</para>

      <figure id="hla-map.figure">
	<title>Map of the HLA region (adapted from Rhodes and Trowsdale 1999)*</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="hla-map.png" align="center"/>
	  </imageobject>

	  <caption>
	    <para>*Class I &#x2013; ovals: classical (Ia) filled, non-classical (Ib) stippled, pseudogenes open. </para>
	    <para>Class II&#x2013;rectangles: B genes light, A genes dark.</para>
	    <para>Allele numbers are from <ulink url="http://www.anthonynolan.com/HIG/index.html">http://www.anthonynolan.com/HIG/index.html</ulink>, as of Oct. 13, 2000.</para>
	  </caption>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para> The six classical class I and II loci are highly
       polymorphic and encode structurally homologous products which
       are expressed on the surface of antigen presenting cells. HLA
       molecules are receptors which capture peptide fragments of
       antigen that help T cells recognize and respond to foreign
       antigens. The division into class I and II molecules is based
       on their structure, tissue distribution, source of peptide
       antigen, and the function of responding T cells (McCluskey and
       Peh 1999, Little and Parham 1999). Each of the class II DR, DQ,
       and DP regions contains at least two genes, denoted A and B
       respectively, e.g., DRA1, DRB1. The class III region includes
       immune system and non-immune system loci encoding, e.g.,
       complement proteins, Factor B, C2, C4, and tumor necrosis
       factors, TNFA and B.</para>

      <para> The recombination distance between the most distant of
      the HLA classical loci, the class I A locus and the class II
      DPB1 locus is 3.7 cM (Carrington 1999). The HLA region in fact
      extends beyond these boundaries; e.g., the non-classical class I
      gene involved in hemochromatosis, HFE, maps 4 Mb from HLA-A
      (Rhodes and Trowsdale 1999, <ulink
      url="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/</ulink>).</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>

      <title>Structure and function of class I and class II molecules</title>

      <para> The processed self and foreign peptide fragments
      presented by the classical HLA molecules (see <xref
      linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>) usually consist of 8&#x2013;10
      amino acids (class I) or 12&#x2013;20 amino acids (class II),
      and are of either intracellular or extracellular origin
      respectively. Class I and II genes are distantly related at the
      sequence level, but the protein structures are quite similar,
      and both are members of the immunoglobulin superfamily. The
      classical class I molecules (A, B, and C) are comprised of a
      heavy chain, encoded by the HLA region, and a light chain,
      encoded by the invariant &#xf062;2-microglobulin gene on ch. 15
      (<xref linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>). The extracellular
      portion of the heavy chain is divided into 3 domains: &#xf061;1,
      &#xf061;2, and &#xf061;3, each about 90 amino acids long. The
      &#xf061;1 and &#xf061;2 domains form a groove bordered by two
      &#xf061;-helices with a &#xf062;-pleated sheet floor. It is in
      this groove, referred to as the antigen recognition site (ARS),
      that the peptide fragment is bound. The classical class II
      molecules (DR, DQ, and DP) are composed of an &#xf061; and a
      &#xf062; chain (from the A and B genes respectively) in a
      non-covalent association (<xref
      linkend="hla-structure.figure"/>). The extracellular portion of
      each chain consists of two domains (&#xf061;1, &#xf061;2 and
      &#xf062;1, &#xf062;2), each about 90 amino acids long. The ARS
      is formed by the &#xf061;1 and &#xf062;1 domains.</para>

      <figure id="hla-structure.figure">
	<title>Class I and class II structure and antigen presentation</title>
	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="hla-structure.png" align="center"/>
	  </imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </figure>

      <para>An MHC molecule binds only to peptides conforming to
      certain structural requirements. A particular MHC allele is thus
      only able to present a subset of the available peptides to T
      cells. Peptide motifs important for binding to HLA molecules,
      including critical residues, e.g., position 57 of DQB1, have
      been defined by sequence analysis of naturally processed
      peptides, analysis with synthetic peptides, and predictive
      inference of binding preference based on similarity of
      peptide-binding environments. While some of the most highly
      polymorphic HLA amino acid residues line the groove of the ARS,
      conferring unique peptide- and TCR-binding properties on each
      MHC molecule, clusters of highly conserved amino acid residues
      are found outside the groove and at both ends of the ARS.</para>

      <para> Class I molecules are expressed on most cells and
      interact with CD8+ (cytotoxic) T cells, playing a critical part
      in tissue graft rejection as well as in the immune response to
      viruses and intracellular pathogens, and cancerous cells. Class
      II molecules are expressed only on a restricted subset of immune
      system cells, e.g., macrophages and B-cells, and interact with
      CD4+ (helper) T cells, exerting an immune system response
      through the production of various lymphokines, such as IL-2,
      affecting, among other things, B cell differentiation and
      antibody production.</para>

      <para>During the maturation of the immune system, T-cell clones
      are deleted or rendered anergic to self peptides in the context
      of HLA presentation. Autoimmune disease is thought to result
      when there is a breakdown in self-tolerance. Molecular
      mechanisms have been proposed for the direct role of HLA
      molecules in the cascade of autoimmune events leading to type 1
      diabetes (previously referred to as insulin dependent diabetes
      mellitus&#x2014;IDDM) and other autoimmune diseases.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>HLA polymorphism</title>

      <para>The polymorphism of many of the HLA genes and MHC genes in
      other species, is extraordinary (<xref
      linkend="hla-map.figure"/>); e.g., 320 alleles are currently
      described for the class II DRB1 gene, and 399 for the class I B
      gene, with much of the variation present at the protein
      level. The genetic variation is concentrated in the amino acid
      residues of the ARS (see e.g., Little and Parham 1999). Alleles
      at HLA-A, for example, differ from each other by up to
      20&#x2013;30 amino acids. In contrast to these highly
      polymorphic loci, there are also HLA region loci which show very
      little polymorphism, e.g., the non-classical class I genes, some
      class II genes such as DRA1, and the complement class III
      genes.</para>

      <para>Point mutations generating new variation and genetic
      exchange (recombination or gene conversion) reassorting extant
      polymorphism into new combinations have played key roles in
      creating HLA diversity (Little and Parham 1999). For class I
      genes, generation of variants at the B locus appears to be more
      rapid than at the A or C loci. HLA variation shows population
      structure; some alleles differ in frequency between ethnic
      groups, others are unique to a specific ethnic or geographic
      group, particularly those of the highly polymorphic class I B
      and class II DRB1 genes (see e.g., Imanishi et al. 1992, Charron
      1997).</para>

      <para>To explain the extensive polymorphism at the HLA loci,
      Klein (1987) proposed a &#x201c;trans-species&#x201d; hypothesis
      whereby ancestral allelic polymorphism is maintained, presumably
      by balancing selection, after species divergence. First applied
      to rodent species, this theory is also supported by evidence in
      primates where, for example, certain chimpanzee alleles are more
      closely related to specific human alleles than they are to other
      chimpanzee alleles. This segregation of alleles across species
      into &#x201c;allelic lineages&#x201d; is based primarily on
      sequence homology and serological specificities, although these
      groupings for the class I HLA-A locus have also been correlated
      with functional attributes such as peptide binding specificities
      (Jakobsen et al. 1998). For class I, allelic lineages are seen
      most clearly at the less polymorphic loci A and C, however at
      even the most polymorphic class II locus, DRB1, the alleles can
      be divided into 13 distinct allelic lineages which are highly
      correlated with the serological DR specificities. Phylogenetic
      studies support the idea that many of these lineages are very
      old, but that alleles within each lineage have been generated
      recently in hominoid evolution (Bergstrom et al. 1998).</para>

      <para>Molecular typing methods, for example using PCR
      (polymerase chain reaction) and SSOP
      (sequence-specific-oligonucleotide probes), are now the standard
      for typing class II loci (see e.g., Middleton 1999). The greater
      degree and type of variability of HLA class I compared to class
      II loci has made molecular typing more difficult than initially
      expected by researchers in the field. Recently, molecular typing
      methods have also been applied to class I loci (see e.g., Cao et
      al. 1999). For molecularly defined alleles, the first two
      numbers of the allele designation refer to the serological type
      of the allele, so that DRB1*0401 and 0402 are subtypes of
      DR4. This is indicative of the increased resolution of alleles
      available with molecular typing.</para>

      <para> Microsatellites in the HLA region share the
       characteristics of microsatellites found elsewhere in the
       genome, including high density, high mutation rates, and high
       polymorphism. The utility of microsatellites for the
       identification of HLA region disease genes has been
       demonstrated (see e.g., Foissac et al. 1997 for review,
       Carrington et al. 1999). Identification of single nucleotide
       polymorphisms (SNPs) across the HLA region in diverse ethnic
       groups is in progress (Geraghty et al. 1999).</para>

    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>Selection in the HLA region</title>

      <para> Allele frequencies within a population for serologically
      typed HLA class I A, B, and C and the class II DR locus, and for
      molecularly typed class II DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1, are often more
      even than expected under neutrality, suggesting that some form
      of balancing selection is operating on these genes (see e.g.,
      Hedrick and Thomson 1983, Salamon et al. 1999, Valdes et
      al. 1999). In contrast, the distribution of DPB1 alleles rarely
      differs significantly from neutrality expectations; usually
      there is a fairly common allele, which may differ between
      populations.</para>

      <para>From the examination of class I and II genes across
      species, nonsynonymous amino acid substitutions per site (dn)
      are proportionally more common than synonymous substitutions
      (ds) in the ARS, indicative of balancing selection maintaining
      the extensive variation (Hughes and Nei 1988, 1989). Regions not
      involved in peptide binding typically show dn &lt; ds, the
      pattern expected under purifying selection.</para>

      <para> The specific mechanism of the selection acting on MHC
      variation has not yet been identified, although models invoking
      heterozygote advantage are strong candidates, since individuals
      heterozygous for HLA present a wider range of foreign peptides
      to T cells (Parham and Ohta 1996, Edwards and Hedrick
      1998). Observations on the pathogens <emphasis>Plasmodium
      falciparum</emphasis> (malaria), human and simian
      immunodeficiency viruses (HIV and SIV), Epstein-Barr virus
      (EBV), and hepatitis B have indicated that HLA restricted
      cytotoxic T-cell responses may influence the evolution of the
      host-pathogen relationship. HLA associations with infectious
      diseases may differ between geographic regions and reflect
      pathogen variation. This may account for some of the differences
      seen in HLA allele frequencies between geographical
      areas.</para>

      <para> Other mechanisms proposed to explain MHC variability are
      disassortative mating and maternal-fetal incompatibility. There
      is evidence of maternal-fetal incompatibility in humans, and
      disassortative mating for MHC in mice (Penn and Potts 1998) and
      in humans (Ober et al. 1997, Gnin et al. 2000), although it is
      not seen in all studies (Hedrick and Black 1997). Multiple
      mechanisms are probably responsible for HLA diversity (Edwards
      and Hedrick 1998,<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>Meyer and
      Thomson 2001).</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>HLA linkage disequilibrium</title>

      <para> Significant linkage disequilibrium (LD) between alleles
       at different loci is observed across the HLA region (see e.g.,
       Imanishi et al. 1992, Charron 1997). Disequilibrium is in many
       cases nearly complete between the tightly linked class II DRB1,
       DQA1, and DQB1 loci. For example, almost all DR3 haplotypes in
       many ethnic groups are DRB1*0301-DQA1*0501-DQB1*0201.  The
       class I B and C loci also exhibit very high LD, while less
       closely linked loci show medium levels of LD (e.g., class I A
       and B). The observed levels of overall LD for HLA data are
       incompatible with neutrality expectations.</para>

      <para>Huttley et al. (1999) used data from many laboratories on
      ~5000 microsatellites from the Utah and Amish CEPH families to
      examine LD levels across the genome of 54 independent
      chromosomes. They identified ten regions that showed higher LD
      than the HLA region and concluded that the pattern of LD was
      consistent with the action of natural selection on loci in these
      regions.</para>
    </sect1>

    <sect1>
      <title>HLA associated diseases</title>

      <para> Genes in the HLA region are known to influence
      susceptibility to many diseases. These include complex
      autoimmune diseases such as type 1 diabetes, rheumatoid
      arthritis (RA), and multiple sclerosis (MS); Hodgkin disease and
      other cancers; infectious diseases including malaria,
      tuberculosis, and AIDS, and diseases of unknown etiology such as
      narcolepsy (Tiwari and Terasaki 1985, Thorsby 1997). In some
      cases the HLA classical class I and II genes have been
      implicated as directly involved in disease, e.g., ankylosing
      spondylitis (class I), type 1 diabetes, RA, MS, celiac disease,
      and narcolepsy (class II). In other cases, the association with
      classical HLA genes was due to LD, as with hemochromatosis. The
      HLA associated diseases are in general genetically complex. They
      can involve multiple HLA and non-HLA loci and exhibit incomplete
      penetrance, genetic heterogeneity within the HLA region, and
      synergistic effects. Type 1 diabetes exhibits all of these
      features (Thomson 1997, 2001a,). The class II genes DRB1, DQA1,
      and DQB1 all contribute to type 1 diabetes. Genetic variation
      additional to DR-DQ is also required to explain all of the HLA
      region contribution to disease.</para>
    </sect1>
</appendix>

<appendix>
  <appendixinfo>
    <authorgroup>
      <author>
	<firstname>Glenys</firstname>
	<surname>Thomson</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>Diogo</firstname>
	<surname>Meyer</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>John</firstname>
	<surname>Chen</surname>
      </author>
      <author>
	<firstname>Richard</firstname>
	<surname>Single</surname>
      </author>
    </authorgroup>
  </appendixinfo>
  
  <title>Methods for analysis of genetic variation</title> 
  
  <remark>in the process of being marked-up in a structured way!</remark>

<!--
    <section>
      <title>Background</title>

      <formalpara>
	<title>1. Statistical Aspects of Genetics</title> 
	
	<para> Both parameter estimation and hypothesis testing are
	relevant.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
	<title>2. Simple rules of probability are sufficient for most probability calculations in genetics:</title>

	<para>&nbsp;the probability of both of two independent events
	is the product of their separate probabilities; &nbsp;the
	probability of either of two mutually exclusive events is the
	sum of their separate probabilities. For example, the
	probability that a sibling of a child affected with a
	recessive trait will also be affected is the probability that
	both of the &nbsp;parents transmit the variant
	allele. &nbsp;If the two parents are both phenotypically
	normal, they must both be heterozygous. So, the probability of
	both transmitting the allele for the trait is  x  =
	.</para>
      </formalpara>

      <formalpara>
	<title>3. &nbsp;Likelihood and Maximum Likelihood</title>
	
	<para>One important concept to distinguish from probability is
	likelihood. &nbsp;Likelihood is the concept used to consider
	different hypotheses given a set of data. &nbsp;The likelihood
	of a hypothesis given a set of data is defined as being
	proportional to the probability of the data given that
	hypothesis.</para>
      </formalpara>
      
      <para> L(hypothesis|data) is proportional to P(data|hypothesis)</para>

      <para>A likelihood ratio is defined as
      L(H<subscript>0</subscript>|D)/L(H<subscript>1</subscript>|D) =
      P(D|H<subscript>0</subscript>)/P(D|H<subscript>1</subscript>). &nbsp;Thus,
      one can consider hypothesis 0 being more or less likely than
      hypothesis 1 given a set of data depending on whether the ratio
      is greater than 1 or less than 1. &nbsp;This leads to the
      concept that the best hypothesis is the one that has the
      greatest likelihood, the one under which the observed data are
      the most probable.</para>

      <para>4. &nbsp;Genotype:Phenotype relationships must be
      considered in all problems; the simplest qualitative ones
      (dominance, recessivity, co-dominance) may not apply if more
      than two alleles are present or more than one locus is involved
      in the phenotype.</para>

      <formalpara>
	<title>5. &nbsp;Gene frequency in a population</title>

	<para>Given phenotypes for a sample of individuals from a
	population one wishes to estimate the frequency/frequencies of
	the alleles. &nbsp;First, one needs to determine the
	relationships between genotypes and the observed
	phenotypes. &nbsp;Let us assume codominance as is often (but
	not always) the case for molecular markers. &nbsp;This equates
	to a 1:1 relationship between genotype and phenotype and
	common sense says that we can count the alleles in the sample
	and that the frequencies in the sample are our estimate of the
	frequencies in the population. &nbsp;In fact, that gene
	counting estimate is the maximum likelihood
	estimate. &nbsp;How can you demonstrate that?</para>
      </formalpara>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Calculation of allele frequencies and heterozygosity</title>

      <para> Allele frequencies are generally calculated by gene
      counting assuming that each phenotype (what is seen: the
      laboratory typing result) is equivalent to a
      genotype. &nbsp;These are used in the test for H-W
      ratios.</para> <para> The standard statistic to describe amount
      of variation is heterozygosity. &nbsp;Why do we want to quantify
      the amount of variation? &nbsp;There are several reasons, most
      of which involve statistical power that increases with
      heterozygosity. &nbsp;For example, in linkage mapping studies in
      families researchers want markers that will be informative
      (=heterozygous) in most members of any family being
      studied. &nbsp;The STRP markers with their large numbers of
      alleles are the markers of choice for this purpose. &nbsp;In
      association studies researchers also want markers that are
      capable of subdividing the population into moderately large
      groups, but using markers with low mutation rates. &nbsp;STRPs
      with their high mutation rates are not so useful, but SNPs are
      even though their maximum heterozygosity is 50%. &nbsp;(Note,
      many recent papers on SNPs refer to the &#x201c;minor allele
      frequency&#x201d;. &nbsp;This terminology is a neologism that
      should be avoided. &nbsp;The word <emphasis>minor</emphasis>
      means &#x201c;less important&#x201d; NOT &#x201c;less
      frequent&#x201d;. &nbsp;Use of heterozygosity as a statistic
      completely avoids this erroneous terminology.)</para>

      <para> Mathematically, heterozygosity is defined as the expected
      frequency of individuals that would be heterozygous in a large
      population given the allele frequencies for the
      population:</para>

      <para> &nbsp;H=1-&#xf053;p<subscript>i</subscript><superscript>2</superscript></para>

      <para>The statistic applies to two-allele systems and to
      multi-allele systems since the
      p<subscript>i</subscript><superscript>2
      &nbsp;</superscript>represent the expected frequencies of
      homozygotes for each of the i alleles.</para>
    </section>

    -->

    <sect1>
      <title>Hardy-Weinberg Ratios</title>

      <sect2>
	<title>Introduction</title>

	<para> Mendelian genetics was rediscovered in the early
	1900's. The Hardy-Weinberg law is the foundation of population
	genetics, and was derived independently in 1908 by an English
	mathematician Hardy and a German physician
	Weinberg. R.C. Punnett brought to the attention of Hardy a
	remark of Yule (a geneticist)&#x2014;Mr. Yule is reported to
	have suggested as a criticism of the Mendelian position that
	if brachydactyly (short fingeredness) is dominant &#x201c;in
	the course of time one would expect, in the absence of
	counteracting factors, to get 3 brachydactylous individuals to
	1 normal.&#x201d; Of course we now understand that Yule is
	confusing the Mendelian 3:1 ratio in an F1 cross (Aa x Aa
	gives 3A-:1aa) with population features.</para>

	<para> Basically we want to consider whether or not Mendelian
	segregation causes changes in the genetic structure of a
	population. We want to consider the effect of this factor
	acting in isolation from all other possible factors, so we
	assume:</para>

	<orderedlist>
	  <listitem>
	    <para>random mating (sexually reproducing diploid)
	population</para>
	  </listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>mutation and migration rates are negligible (no
	mutation, no migration)</para></listitem>
	  
	<listitem>
	    <para>no selection</para></listitem>
	
	  <listitem>
	    <para>segregation according to Mendelian rules</para></listitem>
	  
	  <listitem>
	    <para>non-overlapping generations</para></listitem>

	  <listitem>
	    
	    <para>infinite population size, i.e., the population size
	is so large that we can ignore small chance variations in
	allele frequencies, so we can predict exactly what the allele
	frequencies will be in a future generation, this is known as a
	deterministic model, e.g., the equivalent when a coin is
	tossed is that you would get exactly 50% heads and 50% tails,
	not a distribution of values as seen in reality with a finite
	sample size (stochastic model).</para></listitem>
	</orderedlist>

	<para> The importance of the Hardy-Weinberg law is that if
	there are no counteracting forces, then the frequencies of
	alleles do not change in a population. In other words,
	variation in a population, under a Mendelian system, tends to
	be maintained. We contrast this to the previously believed
	blending inheritance where genetic variation is decreased each
	generation. Further, the expected genotype frequencies each
	generation are determined by the allele frequencies, and are
	termed Hardy-Weinberg proportions (HWP). Continued random
	mating leads to the same genotype (and allele) frequencies,
	hence the term Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Hardy-Weinberg proportions (HWP)</title>

	<para> We consider initially a two allele system, but the
	results extend easily to multiple alleles. The two alleles are
	A and a with respective frequencies p and q (p+q=1, so note
	that we have only one independent variable). If gametes
	combine at random then the frequencies of the three genotypic
	classes in the next generation are:</para>

	<literallayout>
AA &nbsp;Aa &nbsp;aa
p2 &nbsp;2pq &nbsp;q2</literallayout>

	<para>(Note that the 2 for the heterozygote class comes about
	since there are two ways a heterozygote can form, each with
	probability pq, the father can supply the A allele and the
	mother the a allele, or vice versa.) Using gene (allele)
	counting, with f(.) denoting frequency, such that f(A) = f(AA)
	+ f(Aa)/2, and assuming we can distinguish the heterozygote
	from the two homozygote classes, we obtain,</para>

	<informalequation> f(A) = p2 + pq = p(p + q) = p.</informalequation>

	<para> Thus, we have demonstrated that under the assumptions
	of the Hardy-Weinberg law, the allele frequencies in the
	offspring generation are the same as those in the parental
	generation. This results from the fact that there are no
	forces operating to cause systematic change in allele
	frequencies, since the two alleles in this case are considered
	to be selectively equivalent (neutral with respect to each
	other). Further, it follows that in all subsequent
	generations, the genotypic distribution will remain p2AA,
	2pqAa, q2aa. With overlapping generations, there is rapid
	convergence to the HWP. For a multi-allelic system, the
	results are exactly equivalent, with the expected homozygote
	genotype frequencies given by pi2, where pi is the allele
	frequency for the ith allele, and the expected heterozygote
	genotype frequencies are given by 2pipj, with i&lt;j. Although
	complicated in words, the Hardy Weinberg law is ,
	statistically speaking, a simple statement about independence
	of allele frequencies at a locus.</para>

      <para>For example, we consider the ABO blood group system: A
	is dominant to O, B is dominant to O, A and B are
	co-dominant. For the following allele frequencies, A = 0.30, B
	= 0.10, O = 0.60, the HWP are:</para>
      
      <informaltable>
	  <tgroup cols="3">
	    <colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colname="col2" colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colname="col3" colwidth="5.5cm"/>

	    <thead>
	      <row>
		<entry>Blood type</entry>
		<entry>genotypes</entry>
		<entry>Frequency</entry>
	      </row>
	    </thead>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>A</entry>
		<entry>AA, AO</entry>
		<entry>(0.3)2 + 2(0.3)(0.6) = 0.45</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>B</entry> 
		<entry>BB, BO</entry>
		<entry>(0.1)2 + 2(0.1)(0.6) = 0.13</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>AB</entry>
		<entry>AB</entry>
		<entry>2(0.1)(0.3) = 0.06</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>O</entry>
		<entry>OO</entry>
		<entry>(0.6)2 = 0.36</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</informaltable>

	<para>(Note in this case that the allele frequencies cannot be
	estimated by gene (allele) counting, since allele O is
	recessive. The allele frequencies in this case are estimated
	by an iterative procedure.)</para>

	<para> For sex-linked (X chromosome) genes, females are
	diploid and males are haploid, and the HWP are</para>


	<para> &nbsp;females &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;males</para>
	<para> AA &nbsp;Aa &nbsp;aa &nbsp;&nbsp;A &nbsp;a</para>
	<para> p2 &nbsp;2pq &nbsp;q2 &nbsp;&nbsp;p &nbsp;q.</para>
	
	<para>If the female and male initial allele frequencies are
         equal, then these equilibrium frequencies are reached in one
         generation. If they are unequal, then a rapid convergence to
         the above equilibrium takes place.</para>

	<para> Due to the finite size of samples, observed genotype
	frequencies are not expected to be in exact HWP. Two
	illustrative examples using the codominant MN blood group
	system are shown below, which have the same allele frequencies
	f(M) = 0.6, f(N) = 0.4, and hence the same HWP, but very
	different observed genotype frequencies (the first very close
	to HWP, the second very different from HWP):</para>

	<para> MM MN NN</para>
	<para>(1) obs. freq. 0.35 0.5 0.15</para>
	<para>(2) obs. freq. 0.56 0.08 0.36</para>
	<para>exp. H-W 0.36 0.48 0.16</para>

	<para> The strength of the Hardy-Weinberg law is that much of
	the variation in natural populations follows HWP; its weakness
	is that selection, etc., have to be very strong to detect
	deviations from HWP.</para>
      </sect2>

      <sect2>
	<title>Testing fit to HWP</title>

	<para>There are two important issues with regard to HWP
          testing. First is testing the overall fit of a
          sample. Traditionally, a large sample goodness-of-fit
          chi-square is performed when the number of genotypes is
          small relative to the sample size. With the development of
          modern molecular technology, the situation is often
          different from this. For instance, over 400 alleles have
          been described at the HLA class I B locus, although not all
          these alleles are seen in any one population. However, it is
          not uncommon for researchers to distinguish more than a few
          dozen alleles in a reasonable-sized sample for the HLA class
          I and class II loci. Therefore, in many studies the
          genotypic matrix is relatively sparse and some simulation
          approaches, e.g. Guo and Thompson (1992), are more
          appropriate than their asymptotic counter parts in testing
          for overall fit of HWP.</para>

	<para> The second issue is testing at the individual
	heterozygote level. For a given sample, beside the overall
	fit, researchers are often interested in knowing which
	individual heterozygote significantly deviates from its HW
	expectation, especially when the genotype matrix is relatively
	large. If one rejects the overall fit, which heterozygote(s)
	is/are responsible for the deviation? If one does not reject
	the overall fit, are there consistent and significant patterns
	of deviation at the individual level, which were not detected
	by an overall test? This is especially relevant when genetic
	data are available from more than one population. By comparing
	patterns across populations, consistent deviations, which may
	not be strong enough to be found in the overall tests of an
	individual sample, could be detected. This will allow
	researchers to generate future hypothesis on the mechanisms
	causing such patterns and facilitate further study of this
	genetic region.</para>

	  <sect3>
	    <title>The chi-square test</title>

	  <para> The basis of the chi-square test is to calculate
	  expected genotype values based on HWP for individual
	  genotype values and test for fit to HWP using an overall
	  test. When expected genotype counts are &gt;=5 calculate the
	  individual chi-square value for this genotype, i.e.,
	  (O-E)<superscript>2</superscript>/E, where O is observed and
	  E is expected for that genotype, and add together the
	  contributions of each genotype. If there are no rare
	  genotypes (expected &lt;5), the degrees of freedom (d.f.)
	  for the overall chi-square test are given by k(k-1)/2, where
	  k is the number of alleles in the sample under study. This
	  comes from the formula, d.f. = number of categories - 1 -
	  number of independent parameters estimated from the data
	  needed to determine the expected values (in this case k-1,
	  since if we know k-1 allele frequencies we can determine the
	  kth allele frequency). Since the number of categories
	  (genotypes) in this case is k (homozygotes) + k(k-1)/2
	  (heterozygotes) = k(k+1)/2, from which we subtract 1 (since
	  given the frequencies of all except one of these categories
	  we can always determine the frequency of the remaining
	  category given the sample size), and subtract (k-1) (the
	  number of independent allele frequencies need to estimate
	  the HWP), to give the d.f. = k(k-1)/2.</para>
	  
	  <para> As examples we consider a 2 allele case, &nbsp;as
	  above, with a range of observed (O) genotype frequencies,
	  all with p = 0.6, q = 0.4, and all with sample size N = 100
	  individuals. In all cases the expected (E) HWP genotype
	  counts are 36, 48, and 16. Next to the observed numbers in
	  each case the (O - E) values are given. The d.f. = 1 in each
	  case for the overall chi-square test. For a chi-square
	  distribution with 1 d.f., the cut-off points, i.e.,
	  rejection of the null hypothesis of fit to HWP are 3.84
	  (5%), 6.64 (1%), and 10.83 (0.1%). If the overall chi-square
	  value is greater than one of these values, then the null
	  hypothesis of overall fit to HWP for these genotypes is
	  rejected with the type 1 error (probability you have made a
	  mistake) given in parentheses.</para>

	  <informaltable>
	    <tgroup cols="4">
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="3cm"/>
	      <tbody>
		<row>
		  <entry>AA</entry> 
		  <entry>Aa</entry>
		  <entry>aa</entry>
		  <entry>chi-square value</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>35 (1)</entry>
		  <entry>50 (2)</entry>
		  <entry>15 (1)</entry>
		  <entry>0.17</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>32 (4)</entry>
		  <entry>56 (8)</entry>
		  <entry>12 (4)</entry>
		  <entry>2.78</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>31 (5)</entry>
		  <entry>58 (10)</entry>
		  <entry>11 (5)</entry>
		  <entry>4.34, p&lt;0.05</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>29 (7)</entry>
		  <entry>62 (14)</entry>
		  <entry>9 (7)</entry>
		  <entry>8.51, p&lt;0.01</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>27 (9)</entry>
		  <entry>66 (18)</entry>
		  <entry>7 (9)</entry>
		  <entry>14.06, p&lt;0.001</entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </informaltable>

	  <para>The individual genotype contributions
	  (O-E)<superscript>2</superscript>/E can each be
	  asymptotically tested against a chi-square distribution with
	  1 d.f., to determine which genotypes are contributing to
	  significant deviation from HWP.</para>

	  <para> With a 3 allele system, there are 6 genotype classes
	  (A1A1, A1A2, A1A3, A2A2, A2A3, A3A3) and if all have
	  expected values &gt;=5, the overall chi-square will have 3
	  d.f.</para>

	  <para> When expected genotype counts are &lt;5 a lumped
	  category of observed and expected values for all these
	  genotypes needs to be formed, and test fit to null
	  hypothesis (no deviation from HWP) of this chi-square value
	  with 1 degree of freedom and output p value. The chi-square
	  value from this category is added to the cumulative
	  chi-square value from the genotypes &gt;=5 class to give the
	  overall chi-square value which is tested against the null
	  hypothesis of fit to HWP, degrees of freedom equals the
	  number of genotypes falling into &gt;=5 class minus the
	  number of independent parameters estimated. In the case of
	  the highly polymorphic HLA data, with high allele numbers
	  and many sparse cells, this calculation may result in zero
	  or negative d.f. (for which a test of significance cannot be
	  applied). In this case, an appropriate strategy is to just
	  subtract the number of alleles seen in the genotypes &lt;=5
	  category. If this still gives a problem, the rarer alleles
	  need to be appropriately combined.</para>

	  <para> For the above Pearson&#x2019;s goodness of fit test,
	  the general rule of thumb about the validity of the
	  asymptotics is that the expected cell counts need to be at
	  least 5 (Cochran 1954), although it is found that the rule
	  tends to be conservative (Bradley et al. 1979). Several
	  corrections to this goodness of fit test have been proposed
	  to improve the approximation when small sample expectations
	  exist in the sample. Yates (1934) suggested using the
	  continuity correction, 1/2, i.e., (absolute value (0 - E) -
	  1/2)2/E. Emigh (1980) showed that in some cases a correction
	  of 1/4 performs better.</para>

	  <para> Elston and Forthofer (1977) derived the likelihood
	  ratio statistic for HWP testing. It was based on comparison
	  of two maximum likelihoods of a sample coming from the
	  multinomial distribution of genotype counts with (L0) versus
	  without (L1) the HWP constraint. When the null hypothesis is
	  true, i.e., HWP, the test statistic, G2 (= -2ln(L0/L1)),
	  follows a chi-square distribution, with k(k-1)/2 d.f.</para>


	  <para>Below is an example of a contingency table with
	  genotypic observed and expected counts, illustrating the
	  problem of sparse cells (the data is for the DPA1 locus of
	  the HLA region, from a Filipino population). The identity of
	  the alleles (0102, 0103&#x2026;) present in each genotype
	  are given on the margins, and genotypes with expected counts
	  &lt;5 are shown in bold. Notice how the expected values for
	  individual genotypes are often very low. These inflate the
	  chi-square values and may result in spurious rejection of
	  the null hypothesis.</para>

 	  <informaltable frame="none">
	    <tgroup cols="7">
	      <colspec colname="col1" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col2" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col3" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col4" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col5" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col6" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <colspec colname="col7" colwidth="2cm"/>
	      <tbody>
		  <row>
		  <entry colsep="1">0102</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry colsep="1">0103</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.2</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">2.2</phrase></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry colsep="1">0104</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>1/<phrase role="strong">0.2</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry colsep="1">02011</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>3/<phrase role="strong">2.8</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.9</phrase></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry colsep="1">02022</entry>
		  <entry>1/<phrase role="strong">0.7</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>23/20.5</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.7</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>14/12.7</entry>
		  <entry>46/47.0</entry>
		</row>
		<row rowsep="1">
		  <entry colsep="1">0401</entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>2/<phrase role="strong">0.9</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>1/<phrase role="strong">0.6</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>3/<phrase role="strong">4.2</phrase></entry>
		  <entry>0/<phrase role="strong">0.1</phrase></entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry colspec="1"></entry>
		  <entry>0102</entry>
		  <entry>0103</entry>
		  <entry>0104</entry>
		  <entry>02011</entry>
		  <entry>02022</entry>
		  <entry>0401</entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </informaltable>

	  <para>In this example sparse cells are fairly common, even
	  though &nbsp;this is by no means a particularly polymorphic
	  HLA locus. The problem is particularly serious in the cases
	  where polymorphism is greater.</para>
	</sect3>

	<sect3>
	  <title>Exact tests</title>

	  <para>Levene (1949) described the conditional sampling
           distribution for Hardy Weinberg populations. An algorithm
           for generating the exact distribution of samples drawn from
           a population in HWP was proposed by Louis and Dempster
           (1987). Using this algorithm, one could develop an exact
           test for HWP, analogous to Fisher&#x2019;s 2x2 exact
           test. This approach can be applied to an arbitrary number
           of alleles, especially when sample sizes are small. It
           provides a reliable alternative to the standard goodness of
           fit test and methods that require corrections. Below is an
           example of a test for deviations from HWP using such an
           exact test.</para>

	  <para>Consider a sample of 40 individuals, where the
	  genotype counts for a biallelic locus are: n(AA) = 5, n(Aa)
	  = 9, and n(aa) = 26. &nbsp;The total count for each allele
	  is: n(A) = 19 , and n(a) = 61. Using the expression given by
	  Levene (1949) we compute the probability of obtaining this
	  set of genotypes, conditional on the observed counts of
	  alleles, under the null hypothesis of no association
	  (i.e. HWP). The probability of this combination is
	  0.0205</para>

	  <para>The challenge now is to decide whether the probability
           associated to this outcome is particularly low. This can be
           done by comparing the probability of this specific
           genotypic combination with that of all other possible
           combinations. This is summarized in the table below. All
           genotypic possibilities, conditional on the observed number
           of alleles, are listed and sorted by their
           probabilities.</para>

	<informaltable frame="none"> 
	  <tgroup cols="5" align="right"> 
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	    <colspec colwidth="4.5cm"/>
	    <tbody>
	      <row>
		<entry>AA</entry>
		<entry>a</entry>
		<entry>aa</entry>
		<entry>Probability</entry>
		<entry>Cumulative Probability</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>9</entry>
		<entry>1</entry>
		<entry>30</entry>
		<entry>0.0000</entry>
		<entry>0.0000</entry>
	      </row>
	      
	      <row>
		<entry>8</entry>
		<entry>3</entry>
		<entry>29</entry>
		<entry>0.0000</entry>
		<entry>0.0000</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>7</entry>
		<entry>5</entry>
		<entry>28</entry>
		<entry>0.0001</entry>
		<entry>0.0001</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>6</entry>
		<entry>7</entry>
		<entry>27</entry>
		<entry>0.0023</entry>
		<entry>0.0024</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>5</entry>
		<entry>9</entry>
		<entry>26</entry>
		<entry>0.0205</entry>
		<entry>0.0229 &lt; - observed data</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>0</entry>
		<entry>19</entry>
		<entry>21</entry>
		<entry>0.0594</entry>
		<entry>0.0823</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>4</entry>
		<entry>11</entry>
		<entry>25</entry>
		<entry>0.0970</entry>
		<entry>0.1793</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>1</entry>
		<entry>17</entry>
		<entry>22</entry>
		<entry>0.2308</entry>
		<entry>0.4101</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>3</entry>
		<entry>13</entry>
		<entry>24</entry>
		<entry>0.2488</entry>
		<entry>0.6589</entry>
	      </row>
	      <row>
		<entry>2</entry>
		<entry>15</entry>
		<entry>23</entry>
		<entry>0.3411</entry>
		<entry>1.0000</entry>
	      </row>
	    </tbody>
	  </tgroup>
	</informaltable>

	<para>The probability of the observed genotypes is among the
	  5% lowest ways to distribute genes into genotypic
	  categories, so we reject the null hypothesis that the
	  genotypes fit HWP.</para>
	
	<para> However, with an increase in the number of alleles
	  and sample size, the number of possible configurations of
	  samples using the above algorithm grows exponentially. It
	  becomes computationally cumbersome or even infeasible. To
	  avoid complete enumeration, Guo and Thompson (1992)
	  developed two simulation approaches to perform an
	  approximate exact overall HWP test. In their conventional
	  Monte Carlo approach, gametes were permuted to generate new
	  genotypes and the Monte Carlo p value of the observed sample
	  can be estimated by comparing Levene&#x2019;s probabilities
	  of the sample and those from different permutations.</para>

	  <para> In the Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) approach of
	  Guo and Thompson (1992), a finite and irreducible Markov
	  chain of states of genotype counts was generated using the
	  Metropolis algorithm (Metropolis et al. 1953), where the
	  transition probabilities between any two states were a
	  function of the ratio of probabilities of being in each of
	  them. The equilibrium distribution of the Markov chain was
	  set to have the same allele frequencies as those in the
	  observed sample and the HWP genotype probabilities. After a
	  &#x201c;dememorization&#x201d; period, the p value was
	  estimated by calculating the fraction of times the Markov
	  chain was in any states which had equal or lower probability
	  than the observed one.</para>

	  <para> In Chen and Thomson (1999) the variance for the
           disequilibrium coefficient in the individual Hardy-Weinberg
           test has been determined. An exact test using a statistic
           based on this variance has been developed (Chen et
	  al. 1999).</para>
	</sect3>
      </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Testing fit to HWP of HLA data</title>

      <para> The Guo and Thompson (1992) overall test, and the Chen et
       al. (1999) exact test of individual heterozygote deviations
       from HWP, have been applied to HLA class II genotype data in 26
       populations (Chen et al. 1999). Eighty of the 99 overall tests
       fitted HWP (73% for DRB1, 89% for DQA1, 81% for DQB1, and 81%
       for DPB1), deviations were both locus and group specific. The
       individual test results indicated that the departure was partly
       due to recent admixture. Evidence for selection as a cause of
       deviation from HWP was also observed; the fact that the DQB1
       allele *0301 was involved in significant individual
       heterozygote deficiencies in eight samples could well implicate
       selection.</para>

      <para>In many cases the genotypes showing significant deviation
       contain alleles suspected of being the result of admixture or
       recent origin within the group. It is possible that admixture
       has effectively caused the deviation from HWP, suggesting its
       very recent history to the group, perhaps within one
       generation. Other explanations for the deviation from HWP,
       including non-random mating patterns with regard to admixed
       individuals within the ethnic group, must also be
       considered. On the other hand, significant deviations from HWP
       are also seen in populations which showed very little evidence
       for any admixture, e.g., the Mixe, an amerindian group from
       Oaxaca, Mexico (Hollenbach et al. 2001). These deviations could
       be due to the impact of selection pressures from infectious
       diseases on these genes. </para>

      <para>&nbsp;Testing for fit to HWP can also serve a useful role
       in assessing the initial quality of typing results. Should
       deviations from expectations occur, it is possible to look
       again at the raw data and the methods employed to generate
       them, and if deemed necessary repeat typing and use alternative
       methods to confirm results. This may be particularly relevant
       for HLA typing in non-Caucasian populations, where new alleles
       which may not be detected by the typing system are more likely
       to occur.</para>

      <para> Also, we have to caution here that the individual
       heterozygote testing approach is most useful if one has an a
       priori hypothesis about one or a few heterozygotes in the
       sample, regarding their excess or deficit from HWP. By applying
       the method to all heterozygotes, we face the problem of
       multiple tests, and some results merely reflecting type 1
       error. Therefore any p values need to judged with
       care. However, the approach is still of general interest and
       validity in detecting patterns and generating future
       hypotheses.</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

<!--
  <section>
    
    <title>Measuring genetic variation among populations</title>

    <para>Genetic variation among populations is generally measured as
      F<subscript>st</subscript> = &#x3c3;
      <subscript>p</subscript><superscript>2</superscript>/p-bar
      q-bar, as noted in section II.B. The theory underlying this
      standardized variance derives from consideration of random
      genetic drift. Random genetic drift is simply the accumulated
      sampling error for transmission of alleles from generation to
      generation in a finite population. If there is no selection
      operating and a single population divides into two populations,
      both with the identical allele frequencies, the allele
      frequencies will gradually diverge over the generations if there
      is no migration (exchange of alleles) between them. This is
      easily measured as an increase in the variance in the frequency
      of an allele across the two (or more) diverging
      populations. With all populations starting at the same allele
      frequency, p<subscript>0</subscript>, and maintaining a constant
      population size, N, the variance at time t in generations of
      independent random genetic drift is expected to be</para>

    <para>
     <emphasis>V</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>t</subscript></emphasis> = &nbsp;</para>

    <para>sum(i=1,n)((pi - p-bar)2/(n-1)</para>

    <para>&nbsp;<emphasis>p</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>0</subscript></emphasis> (1 - <emphasis>p</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>0</subscript></emphasis>) (1 - <emphasis>e</emphasis><emphasis><superscript>-t/2N</superscript></emphasis>)</para>


    <para>while the mean gene frequency p-bar;over all populations</para>

    <para>p-bar = sum(i=1,n)(pi)/n</para>

    <para>is expected to remain constant and equal to <emphasis>P</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>0</subscript></emphasis>. Taking</para>

    <para>V<subscript>t</subscript>/P<subscript>0(1-P<subscript>0</subscript></subscript>) ? V<subscript>t</subscript>/p-bar(1-p-bar) = f<subscript>t</subscript></para>
    
    <para>as a measure of variation, which corresponds to F<subscript>st</subscript> in Wright's notation:</para>

    <para>f<subscript>t</subscript> &nbsp;1 - <emphasis>e</emphasis><emphasis><superscript>-t/2N</superscript></emphasis></para>

    <para>The limiting value of f<subscript>t</subscript> (f) for
    <emphasis>t</emphasis> = infinity is 1 where all populations are
    fixed for one allele or the other.</para>

    <para><emphasis>N</emphasis> must be estimated as effective
    population size, not census size. It can be important to consider
    the effect of the sex ratio of reproducing individuals, which is
    sometimes different from 1:1. The harmonic mean of the numbers of
    reproducing animals in the two sexes,
    <emphasis>N</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>M</subscript></emphasis>
    and
    <emphasis>N</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>F</subscript></emphasis>,
    is used (Wright, 1931):</para>

    <para>1/N<subscript>h</subscript> = (1/N<subscript>M</subscript> + 1/N<subscript>F</subscript>)/2</para>

    <para>Twice the harmonic mean of males and females,
    <emphasis>2N</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>h</subscript></emphasis>,
    is the effective population size:</para>

    <para>N<subscript>e</subscript> = 4N<subscript>M</subscript>N<subscript>F</subscript>/(N<subscript>M</subscript> + N<subscript>F</subscript>)</para>

    <para>The variation on <emphasis>N</emphasis> over generations is also accounted for by taking harmonic means.</para>

    <para>Unbiased estimates of
    <emphasis>V</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>t</subscript></emphasis><subscript>
    </subscript>and of <emphasis>p</emphasis> do not necessarily give
    rise to an unbiased estimate of <emphasis>f</emphasis>. Moreover,
    the sampling properties of the static <emphasis>f</emphasis> are
    not known. An approximation that has frequently been used and is
    satisfactory when the average gene frequencies are between .05 and
    .95, is to use, instead of gene frequencies, their angular
    transforms:</para>

  <para>&#x3b8; = sin<superscript>-1</superscript>(sqrt p)</para>

    <para>This, unlike the binormal variate, <emphasis>p</emphasis>(1
    - <emphasis>p</emphasis>)/<emphasis>N</emphasis>, has variance
    independent of <emphasis>p</emphasis>:</para>

    <para>V<subscript>q</subscript> = 1/4N</para>

    <para>From this angular transform one can also derive an estimate
    of F<subscript>st</subscript>. Note, in Wright's notation the t
    does not relate to time but to the total population as though it
    were not subdivided (see below).</para>

    <para> These estimates of F<subscript>st</subscript> can be
    related to the underlying parameter of time in generations and
    effective population size as -ln (1 - F<subscript>st</subscript>)
    &nbsp;t/2N<subscript>e</subscript> (Kidd and Cavalli-Sforza,
    1974). Thus, divergence between populations increases with time
    but more slowly for larger population sizes. From this inverse
    relationship to population size one readily sees the basis for
    what is often referred to as "founder effect" or "bottleneck
    effect" &nbsp;this is simply the same as random genetic drift but
    at the end of the scale of very small population sizes over a
    short time period. It is a quantitative phenomenon on a continuum
    and not a qualitatively different phenomenon.</para>

    <para>When populations are being studied for genetic
    similarity/difference, many different statistics based on gene
    frequency differences have been proposed but the most commonly
    used measures are based on estimates of
    F<subscript>st</subscript>. Reynolds et al. (1983) proposed an
    estimator of F<subscript>st</subscript> that has excellent
    statistical properties and can be applied to multiple loci with an
    arbitrary number of alleles.</para>

    <para>The F statistics of Wright (1921) (see, for example, a
    standard population genetics textbook such as Hartl and Clark,
    1997, for discussion) can be considered in different
    ways. Originally they were defined to quantify inbreeding in
    structured populations. Systematic inbreeding, say preferential
    mating of first or second cousins, will increase the proportion of
    homozygotes in the population over what would be expected in a
    randomly mating population as predicted by the Hardy-Weinberg
    ratios. Wright drew the analogy with substructured populations
    where the structuring imposes a level of inbreeding, albeit not
    among close relatives. His F statistics measure the decrease in
    heterozygosity (increase in homozygosity) in a level of the
    population hierarchy relative to the heterozygosity if there were
    random mating at the more inclusive level. Thus, the subscripts in
    F<subscript>st</subscript> refer to the reduction in
    heterozygosity in the <phrase
    role="strong">s</phrase>ubpopulations relative to that expected
    for the <phrase role="strong">t</phrase>otal population:</para>

    <para>F<subscript>st</subscript> = H<subscript>t</subscript> -
    H<subscript>s</subscript>/H<subscript>t</subscript></para>
  </section>
-->

    <sect1>

      <title>Measuring non-randomness of alleles on chromosomes</title>
      
      <para>The description of genetic variation at the population
    level usually begins with consideration of allelic variation at a
    single gene locus, as discussed above. &nbsp;The next step is to
    consider genetic variation at two or more loci simultaneously,
    including non-random associations. &nbsp;Gametic disequilibrium
    (usually referred to as linkage disequilibrium LD) describes the
    non-random association of alleles at different genetic
    loci. &nbsp;While linkage disequilibrium can be more generally
    referred to as &#x201c;gametic phase disequilibrium&#x201d;, or,
    in other words, the non-random occurrence in gametes of alleles at
    two or more loci. &nbsp;In general it is immaterial whether the
    two loci are linked. &nbsp;In practice, and in almost all of the
    literature today, it is used only for linked loci. &nbsp;Thus, it
    can also be defined as the non-random occurrence on chromosomes in
    the population of alleles at two or more loci.</para>

    <sect2>

      <title>Tests for Linkage Disequilibrium and its statistical
      significance</title>

      <para> One can estimate the frequencies of haplotypes in a
       population and can measure the amount of
       non-randomness. &nbsp;It is important to distinguish the
       existence of non-randomness from specific statistics used to
       measure that non-randomness. &nbsp;There are several different
       statistics in use today and considerable debate about which is
       &#x201c;correct&#x201d;. &nbsp;The classic pairwise gametic
       disequilibrium parameter, usually denoted D, is given by the
       difference between the observed frequency of a gametic type and
       the frequency expected on the basis of random association of
       alleles in gametes. &nbsp;Consider two genes (denoted
       <emphasis>A</emphasis> and <emphasis>B</emphasis>), with two
       alleles each (A, a and B, b), and four gametic types (also
       referred to as haplotypes): AB, Ab, aB, and ab. &nbsp;The
       frequencies of the four gametes (denoted f(AB) etc.) can be
       described in terms of the allele frequencies pA (pa= 1 - pA)
       and pB (pb = 1 - pB) at the two loci, and the gametic
       disequilibrium parameter D, as follows:</para>

      <para>f (AB) = pA pB + D,</para>
      <para>f (Ab) = pA pb - D,</para>
      <para>f (aB) = pa pB - D,</para>
      <para>f (ab) = pa pb + D,</para>
      
      <para>where D = f(AB) - pA pB = f(AB) f(ab) - f(Ab)
       f(aB). &nbsp;D can be either positive or negative, depending on
       which specific alleles are referenced. &nbsp;If D = 0 (a state
       referred to as gametic or linkage equilibrium) then the alleles
       at the two loci are randomly associated. &nbsp;If D &gt;&nbsp;0
       the allele A occurs more often with allele B than expected by
       chance (and hence a with b), while if D &lt;&nbsp;0 alleles A
       and b (and hence a and B) are preferentially
       associated. &nbsp;The possible value of D in a two-locus system
       is constrained by the fact that &nbsp;&nbsp;the frequency of
       any haplotype is constrained as 0 &#x2264; p<subscript>AB
       &nbsp;</subscript>&#x2264; &nbsp;min(p<subscript>A ,
       </subscript>p<subscript>B</subscript>) &nbsp;and thus the
       disequilibrium coefficient is constrained by</para>

	<para>-p<subscript>a</subscript>p<subscript>b</subscript>,
	-p<subscript>A</subscript>p<subscript>B</subscript> &#x2264;
	p<subscript>AB</subscript> &#x2264;
	p<subscript>A</subscript>p<subscript>b</subscript>,
	p<subscript>a</subscript>p<subscript>B</subscript>. Consequently,
	interpretation of D values is dependent on the allele
	frequencies. To avoid this, the normalized gametic
	disequilibrium D' = D/Dmax is often considered, where Dmax is
	equal to either the lesser of pA pb or pa pB if D is positive,
	and the lesser of pA pB or pa pb if D is negative (Lewontin,
	1964). The advantage of this measure over D is that it
	has a range from -1 to +1, regardless of the allele
	frequencies. Unfortunately, for both D and D' the values
	are not related to statistical significance and are dependent
	on allele frequencies. Therefore, several other measures
	are being used: &#x3b4;, &#x394; = r,
	r<superscript>2</superscript>,
	d<superscript>2</superscript>. These are reviewed by
	Devlin and Risch (1995) except for
	d<superscript>2</superscript>, used by Kruglyak (1999),
	which is closely related to
	D<superscript>2</superscript> and to
	r<superscript>2</superscript>:
	d<superscript>2</superscript> = D<superscript>2
	</superscript>/ [f(1-f)]<superscript>2 </superscript>and
	d<superscript>2</superscript> = r<superscript>2</superscript>
	m(1-m) / [f(1-f)]<superscript>2</superscript> , where f
	is the variant frequency and m is the marker allele
	frequency. Note, this is referenced to the locus of the
	"variant". The correlation coefficient, r = D / (pA pa
	pB pb)_, with a range from -1 to +1, is often used, as well as
	r2 with a range from 0 to +1. An example from the HLA
	region is the association between alleles at the A, B and DR
	loci. The combinations A1-B8 and B8-DR3 have fairly high
	normalized disequilibrium values (D&#x2019; = 0.65 and
	D&#x2019; = 0.73, respectively).</para>

      <para> There is a relationship between D and the recombination
      fraction c between two loci. (Various symbols are used for
      the recombination fraction; the most common symbol in human
      genetics is &#x3b8;.) &nbsp;In the absence of drift and
      selection, changes in gamete frequencies over generations only
      occur by recombination in individuals heterozygous at both loci
      under consideration. In fact, the value of D decreases by a
      fraction (1-c) each generation under random mating and a neutral
      model. &nbsp;Thus the LD in this case converges to zero (random
      association of alleles) with time as (1 - c)n, where n is the
      number of generations. &nbsp;The more loosely linked are two
      loci, the faster the decay of gametic disequilibrium. &nbsp;On
      the other hand, for very tightly linked loci gametic
      disequilibrium may exist for a very long time.</para>

      <para>It is possible, although relatively rare, that unlinked
      loci can be in significant LD, and that very closely linked loci
      may be in linkage (gametic) equilibrium. The value of LD is
      often expected to change each generation. Further, a population
      at genetic equilibrium can have significant LD (e.g., under
      various selection schemes). The term <emphasis>linkage
      disequilibrium</emphasis> is thus an unfortunate choice and the
      term <emphasis>gametic disequilibrium</emphasis> is preferable,
      although also not perfect. &nbsp;However, the term
      <emphasis>linkage disequilibrium</emphasis> is commonly used and
      simply abbreviated LD. &nbsp;There are two important points to
      remember: (1) that tight linkage or molecular proximity does not
      automatically mean there will be LD and (2) that unlinked loci
      can show LD for a variety of reasons.</para>

      <para>Linkage disequilibrium can occur in populations as a
       consequence of a number of factors (see Hedrick 1983 for
       review): (1) mutation&#x2013;when a new mutant arises, it
       occurs in one individual and is in linkage disequilibrium with
       all polymorphic loci in the population; (2)
       selection&#x2013;either acting directly on the two loci, or
       transient linkage disequilibrium can also be created with
       neutral loci via a hitchhiking event with a selected locus
       (Thomson 1977); (3) migration or admixture&#x2013;generation of
       linkage disequilibrium by these forces requires that the
       allelic frequencies of both loci in the two populations be
       different, and this difference must be substantial to generate
       very much linkage disequilibrium; and (4) random genetic
       drift&#x2013;while the expected value of pairwise linkage
       disequilibrium due to drift over many generations is zero, the
       variance is large for closely linked loci in small
       populations.</para>

      <para>The amount of linkage disequilibrium observed in a
      population is also affected by a number of factors: (1)
      recombination&#x2013;significant linkage disequilibrium may be
      maintained for a long time between very closely linked loci; (2)
      selection&#x2013;if the selection is sufficiently strong
      compared to the recombination rate linkage disequilibrium can be
      maintained at an equilibrium state, and will occur transiently
      with a hitchhiking event; (3) non-random mating&#x2013;high
      levels of inbreeding and self-fertilization in plants can retard
      the rate of approach to linkage equilibrium; and (4) population
      demographics&#x2013;a small founder population or a bottleneck
      in the recent past can cause significant linkage disequilibrium
      due to genetic drift for closely linked loci, and while less
      linkage disequilibrium will be generated by genetic drift in a
      rapidly growing population (Slatkin 1994), any linkage
      disequilibrium present before or during the early phase of the
      expansion will persist. &nbsp;</para>

      <para>&nbsp;As seen in Section II, the pattern of LD at many
      loci argues that human populations in sub-Saharan Africa have
      little LD beyond a few kb while all non-African populations tend
      to have much more LD and to share the same
      haplotypes. &nbsp;Thus the evidence argues that most LD in
      non-African populations was produced by a founder effect (a very
      large amount of random genetic drift caused by a quite small
      population size) associated with the expansion of modern humans
      out of Africa.</para>

      <para> The definition of LD is "easily" extended to accommodate
      more than two alleles at a locus or more than two loci:
      non-randomness on chromosomes in the population across however
      many loci and/or among however many alleles. &nbsp;However,
      statistics to quantify LD become more problematic in such
      cases. &nbsp;All of the above are defined for a pair of
      specified alleles at a pair of loci. &nbsp;For multiallelic
      loci, one must choose one allele at each locus and then pool all
      other alleles. &nbsp;This gives n<subscript>1</subscript> x
      n<subscript>2</subscript> different pairwise measures for two
      loci with n<subscript>1</subscript> and
      n<subscript>2</subscript> alleles,
      respectively. &nbsp;Interpreting such a set of LD statistics is
      not simple or obvious. &nbsp;When considering three or more
      loci, higher order disequilibrium terms are also needed (see
      Robinson et al. 1991a). &nbsp;For example, in a three-locus
      system a gametic frequency can be expressed in terms of the
      three-allele frequencies, the three pairwise gametic
      disequilibria, and a single measure of third order gametic
      disequilibrium. &nbsp;However, when multi-allelic loci are
      included or multiple (&gt;3) sites are included, the pairwise
      values and the higher order disequilibrium terms become
      difficult to interpret. &nbsp;Many papers now present data for
      multiple sites in a haplotype as all possible pairwise
      comparisons. &nbsp;</para>

      <para>To date only one measure attempts to measure
      non-randomness in a general manner for an arbitrary number of
      sites with an arbitrary number of alleles at each: the
      permutation test based &#x3be; (Zhao et al., 1999). &nbsp;While
      that measure has not been generally used by researchers studying
      LD in humans, it illustrates the distinction between the
      pairwise measures and the general concept of non-randomness of
      alleles on chromosomes in a population.</para>

      <para>General population level observations are that there is an
      overall proportionality between linkage disequilibrium and the
      inverse of the recombination distance (Huttley et
      al. 1999). &nbsp;This rule however breaks down in very closely
      linked regions (Reich et al. 2001, Huttley et al. 1999, Jorde et
      al. 1994, Klitz et al. 1995). &nbsp;Selection is expected to
      produce linkage disequilibrium non-randomly across the genome,
      whereas all the other factors should act randomly over the
      genome. &nbsp;In study of the CEPH families, linkage
      disequilibrium was found to be non-randomly distributed
      throughout the genome (Huttley et al. 1999). &nbsp;Some regions,
      such as HLA, showed strong evidence of selection and significant
      linkage disequilibrium which spanned 3 cM or more, and an
      additional 10 genetic regions showed linkage disequilibrium
      equal to or greater than in the HLA region. &nbsp;Most recently,
      a series of papers in the October 2001 <emphasis>Nature
      Genetics</emphasis> present evidence that LD in humans exists in
      blocks of strong LD separated by short intervals across which
      all LD breaks down. &nbsp;Recombination hot spots and cold spots
      is one possible explanation for such a pattern. &nbsp;How
      general around the genome this pattern is remains to be
      seen.</para>

      <para>Population and evolutionary aspects of a genetic region
      are highly relevant to the study of Mendelian and complex
      diseases. &nbsp;These relate to our ability to localize and
      identify disease predisposing variants, and to our understanding
      of the mechanisms by which some disease predisposing genes can
      become relatively common in a population.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Haplotype estimation on population and patient data sets</title>

      <para><phrase role="strong"> </phrase>The accuracy of haplotype
      estimates is of increasing interest with regard to population
      data and disease association studies, for microsatellite, SNP,
      and protein level variation. &nbsp;Marker-disease associations
      that are not detected at the single locus level, may
      nevertheless be detected in a multi-locus analysis. &nbsp;This
      was the initial observation in the study of ch. 19q13.2 APOE
      region variation and multiple sclerosis (Barcellos 1996, <xref
      linkend="Barcellos et al. 1997a"/> and 1997c), and in analysis
      of ch. 19 markers and alcohol dependence (Valdes et
      al. 1999).</para>

      <para>Procedures that make use of the expectation-maximization
       (EM) algorithm to estimate haplotype frequencies (HFs) from
       unphased genotype data are in common use in genetic studies,
       e.g., HAUPT (Baur and Danilovs 1980), Arlequin (Schneider et
       al. 2000), HAPLO (Hawley and Kidd 1995), and 3LOCUS.PAS (Long
       et al. 1995). &nbsp;The EM algorithm uses these unphased
       genotype frequencies along with the assumption of
       Hardy-Weinberg proportions (HWP) to converge on HF
       estimates. &nbsp;The EM algorithm is an iterative algorithm for
       computing maximum likelihood estimates (MLEs) in an
       incomplete-data setting (Dempster et al. 1977, Lange
       1997). &nbsp;The algorithm is straightforward. &nbsp;Each
       iteration consists of two steps. &nbsp;The E-step calculates
       the conditional expectation, and the M-step maximizes the
       updated likelihood function. Although the convergence of the EM
       algorithm could be slow, the general theory has shown that each
       iteration increases the likelihood and the MLEs are generally
       achieved (Dempster et al. 1977). &nbsp;The accuracy of
       haplotype frequency estimates are in general relatively good,
       except in the case of low frequency haplotypes (see e.g.,
       Schipper et al. 1998, Fallin and Schork 2000, Tishkoff et
       al. 2000, Single et al. 2002). &nbsp;Large over and under
       estimates of particular HFs can occur even for common
       haplotypes, especially when the loci involved deviate
       significantly from HWP (Single et al. 2002). &nbsp;Estimating
       HFs for three or more loci and then collapsing over loci so as
       to generate two locus haplotypes can improve the accuracy of
       the estimation. &nbsp;The collapsing procedure is most
       beneficial when one of the loci in the two-locus haplotype of
       interest deviates significantly from HWP and the locus
       collapsed over is in linkage disequilibrium with the other loci
       (Single et al 2002).</para>

      <figure id="em-performance">
	<title>Performance of EM
       algorithm in recovering known haplotypes (see text for
       discussion)</title>
	<programlisting></programlisting>
      </figure>

      <para>The performance of the EM algorithm for the estimation of
      haplotypes in the HLA region is illustrated in <xref
      linkend="em-performance"/>These are results from a study
      reported in Single et al. (2002) where family data allowed
      haplotypes to be unambiguously inferred, so true and estimated
      haplotype frequencies could be compared. &nbsp;The graphs depict
      the performance of the EM algorithm in inferring two-locus
      haplotypes for selected pairs of sites. &nbsp;The circles
      represent true haplotype frequencies, and the lines represent
      estimated haplotype frequencies. &nbsp;Two-locus haplotypes for
      the DPB1 and A loci offer an example of how pairs of loci
      between which there is little LD allow only poor estimates of
      haplotype frequencies: notice the large discrepancies between
      true (circles) and inferred (lines) frequencies. &nbsp;In
      addition, note how for the DPB1-A haplotypes there are instances
      of missed haplotypes (true haplotypes not inferred - represented
      by circles with no lines) and incorrect haplotypes (inferred but
      not real - represented by lines with no circle). &nbsp;The locus
      pair DQB1-DRB1 exemplifies completely accurate
      inference. &nbsp;This results from the high LD values between
      these tightly linked loci. &nbsp;Finally, an intermediate
      scenario is exemplified by the inference of frequencies for the
      DQB1-B haplotype.</para>

      <para>The performance of the EM algorithm also differs depending
      on the true frequency of the haplotypes being
      estimated. &nbsp;The table below compares the true and estimated
      haplotype sets using a measure that takes into account the
      frequency differences among observed and inferred haplotypes
      (the If measure, see Single et al. 2002). &nbsp;High values
      imply poor estimates (maximum being 1) and low values imply
      accurate estimates (minimum being 0). &nbsp;Notice that when
      haplotypes that are present as a single copy (column 1), the
      estimation is very inaccurate, but improves as the true
      frequency increases. &nbsp;The haplotypes present as 4 or more
      copies are estimated most accurately. &nbsp;This confirms the
      intuition that low frequency haplotypes are difficult to infer
      using the EM algorithm. &nbsp;A similar result was obtained by
      Tishkoff et al. (2000).</para>

      <table id="em-performance-table.figure">
	<title>Performance of EM algorithm</title>
	<tgroup cols="5" align="center">
	  <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="2cm"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Haplotypes</entry>
	      <entry>1</entry>
	      <entry>2</entry>
	      <entry>3</entry>
	      <entry>4+</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DPB1-A</entry>
	      <entry>0.60</entry>
	      <entry>0.46</entry>
	      <entry>0.41</entry>
	      <entry>0.26</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DQB1-A</entry>
	      <entry>0.63</entry>
	      <entry>0.58</entry>
	      <entry>0.53</entry>
	      <entry>0.28</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DRB1-A</entry>
	      <entry>0.56</entry>
	      <entry>0.49</entry>
	      <entry>0.42</entry>
	      <entry>0.24</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

    </sect2>

    <sect2>

      <title>Testing for significance of linkage disequilibrium in a
      likelihood framework</title>

      <para>Two approaches can be used to quantify and test linkage
      disequilibrium (LD). &nbsp;The first consists of using known
      haplotype frequencies to obtain LD values. &nbsp;Overall
      measures of LD, which account for deviations from free
      association among all pairs of alleles at two loci, can be used
      to generate test statistics that can be tested using parametric
      tests. &nbsp;For example, the overall measure of LD, Q
      (discussed in Hedrick, 1987) follows a chi-square distribution
      with (k-1)(l-1) degrees of freedom for datasets under linkage
      equilibrium (where k and l are the number of alleles at the
      first and second locus, respectively). &nbsp;However, if
      haplotypes are inferred from unphased genotype data this
      approach is limited in that the uncertainty inherent in the
      haplotype estimation is not accounted for when LD values are
      estimated and tested. &nbsp;The following likelihood-based
      approach circumvents this limitation. </para>

      <para>Two likelihood values are defined: L_0 is the likelihood
      of observed genotypic data given the estimated haplotype set
      (this is the likelihood value obtained using the EM
      algorithm). L_1 is the likelihood of the observed data given
      haplotype frequencies expected under complete equilibrium
      (i.e. haplotype frequencies are given by the product of allele
      frequencies at each locus). The test-statistic is defined as:
      </para>

      <para>S = -2log(L_1/L_0)</para>

      <para>The significance (p-value) of the observed test statistic
      can be obtained from a permutation test. &nbsp;The logic behind
      a permutation test for the significance of linkage
      disequilibrium is that under the null hypothesis of no
      disequilibrium any genotype at one site is going to occur with
      any genotype at another site with the frequency equal to the
      product of those genotype frequencies. &nbsp;Thus, by randomly
      permuting the observed genotypes at the separate sites among the
      individuals in the sample, the marginal allele frequencies (and
      genotype frequencies) are unaltered, but the new genotype
      combinations for the individuals in the sample are one
      realization under the null hypothesis. &nbsp;By generating many
      such permuted datasets and evaluating each dataset by whatever
      statistic is being used, one generates a distribution of the
      statistic under the null hypothesis. &nbsp;The statistic for the
      observed data can then be compared to the distribution and the
      significance is the fraction of the permuted datasets with a
      statistic greater than the observed. &nbsp;As stated above, the
      statistic we use is the likelihood ratio for the observed data
      with the estimated haplotype frequencies compared to with
      equilibrium haplotype frequencies.</para>

      <para>An example is provided in <xref linkend="lr-stat-null"/>,
      where the distribution of S for a sample of Filipino individuals
      for haplotypes involving the DQB1 and DPA1 loci. &nbsp;The
      observed value of S is indicated by an arrow, showing that the
      probability of obtaining a value of S as extreme as that
      observed is 0.001 under the null hypothesis (no association
      between loci). Thus we reject the null hypothesis.</para>

      <figure id="lr-stat-null">
	<title>Distribution of likelihood ratio statistic, S, under the null hypothesis of linkage equilibrium</title>
	<programlisting></programlisting>
      </figure>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

  <sect1>
    <title>Tests of neutrality (or selection)</title>

    <sect2>
      <title>Homozygosity test of neutrality</title>

      <para>The neutral theory of evolution at a locus assumes that
      all alleles are selectively equivalent, that mutation is the
      source of new genetic variation, and that genetic drift results
      in loss of variation. Ewens (1972) developed a sampling theory
      that predicts the distribution of alleles at a locus drawn from
      a population at equilibrium under neutrality. Watterson (1978)
      developed a method, using a homozygosity measure, denoted by F,
      for the observed number of alleles and sample size, to compare a
      sample of allele frequencies to neutrality expectations. For a
      given number of observed alleles, a low value of the
      homozygosity measure F, compared to the neutrality expectation,
      corresponds to all alleles having similar frequencies. Some form
      of balancing selection is implied when the observed allele
      frequencies are more even than the neutrality expectation
      (Watterson 1978). A high value of F, compared to the neutrality
      expectation, corresponds to one allele predominating with the
      others at low frequencies. Directional selection is implicated
      in this case. Note that fit of a sample of allele frequencies to
      neutrality expectations does not mean that selection is not
      operating, but simply that one cannot reject the neutral
      model.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Methods</title>

      <para> The observed frequency distribution of alleles in a
      population is compared to neutrality expectations under an
      infinite alleles model. The expected proportion of homozygotes
      under Hardy-Weinberg, i.e., the statistic F = sum(pi to 2) of
      Watterson (1978) for an observed number of alleles k (or amino
      acids at a site) and sample size n individuals (2n chromosomes),
      was compared with the distribution expected under the neutral
      model (Ewens 1972). Note that the Watterson homozygosity test of
      neutrality does not examine deviations from Hardy-Weinberg
      proportions, but utilizes the expected Hardy-Weinberg
      homozygosity as a measure of the distribution of allelic
      frequencies, for a given sample size (k) and observed number of
      alleles (2n). The expected values of F, and the variance and
      quantiles under the neutrality model can be found at <ulink
      url="http://allele5.biol.berkeley.edu/homozygosity/homozygosity.html">http://allele5.biol.berkeley.edu/homozygosity/homozygosity.html</ulink>
      (Salamon H, Nelson M, Thomson G). The exact test developed by
      Slatkin (1994, 1996), which calculates the probability of the
      observed configuration under neutrality, can also be
      implemented.</para>

      <para> To allow comparison of homozygosity F statistics across
      populations with different numbers of alleles and sample sizes,
      the normalized deviate,
      <phrase>F<subscript>ND</subscript></phrase>, is considered
      (Salamon et al. 1999),</para>

      <informalequation>
	<alt role="tex">F_{ND} = (\frac{F_{observed} - F_{expected}}{Variance \cdot F_{expected}})^{\frac{1}{2}}</alt>

	<mediaobject>
	  <imageobject>
	    <imagedata fileref="fnd.png"/>
	  </imageobject>
	  <textobject>
	    <phrase>F<subscript>ND</subscript> =
      (F<subscript>observed</subscript> -
      F<subscript>expected</subscript>) / (Variance
      (F<subscript>expected</subscript>))1/2.</phrase>
	  </textobject>
	</mediaobject>
      </informalequation>

      <para>Under the neutral model, F<subscript>ND</subscript> has
      mean zero and variance 1. If we assume that samples from
      different populations are statistically independent, the Central
      Limit Theorem predicts that the distribution of the mean of
      F<subscript>ND</subscript> values across populations can be
      approximated by a standard normal distribution.</para>
    </sect2>

    <sect2>
      <title>Application of Ewens-Watterson test of neutrality to HLA
      allele data</title>

      <para> Allele frequencies within a population for serologically
      typed HLA class I A, B, and C and the class II DR locus, and for
      molecularly typed class II DRB1, DQA1, and DQB1, are often more
      even than expected under neutrality, suggesting that some form
      of balancing selection is operating on these genes (Hedrick and
      Thomson 1983, Klitz et al. 1986, 1992, Begovich et al. 1992). In
      contrast, the distribution of DPB1 alleles rarely differs
      significantly from neutrality expectations; usually there is a
      fairly common allele, which may differ between
      populations.</para>

      <para><phrase role="strong"> </phrase>In both Salamon et
      al. (1999) and Valdes et al. (1999) where HLA class II data were
      analyzed, DQB1 showed striking evidence (in individual
      populations and overall) for balancing selection (allele
      frequencies more even than expected under the neutral
      model). DQA1 and DRB1 also showed significant evidence of
      balancing selection. Individual and overall population
      statistics for DPB1 were compatible with neutrality expectations
      in both studies. DPA1 allele and DPA1-DPB1 haplotype frequencies
      showed no evidence of deviation from neutrality expectations in
      the CEPH data (Moonsamy et al. 1997). The results for class II
      loci demonstrate that departure from neutrality is locus
      specific, despite the linkage disequilibrium in the region,
      which is particularly strong for DR-DQ.</para>

      <para>The table below summarizes the findings of Valdes et
      al. (1999), illustrating (a) the large number of populations for
      which neutrality was rejected at certain loci; (b) the
      heterogeneity among loci with respect to deviation from
      neutrality. Notice than in all loci, except DPB1, the mean
      homozygosity across populations is lower than expected under
      neutrality.</para>

      <table id="ew-neutrality.table">
	<title>Ewens-Watterson test of neutrality</title>
	<tgroup cols="5">
	  <colspec colwidth="2.5cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="4cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="3cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="3cm"/>
	  <colspec colwidth="3cm"/>
	  <thead>
	    <row>
	      <entry>Locus</entry>
	      <entry>Populations surveyed</entry>
	      <entry>Neutrality rejected <!-- <footnote>

		  <para>Number of populations for which neutrality was
		  rejected at the 5% level (From Valdes et al.,
		  1999). The mean F value is the average of the
		  observed values of the homozygosity statistic in the
		  populations studied. The expected F values are the
		  averages of the expected homozygosity statistic
		  under neutrality.</para>

		</footnote> -->
               </entry>
	      <entry>Mean F</entry>
	      <entry>Expected F</entry>
	    </row>
	  </thead>
	  <tbody>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DPB1</entry>
	      <entry>20</entry>
	      <entry>1</entry>
	      <entry>0.278</entry>
	      <entry>0.238</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DQA1</entry>
	      <entry>19</entry>
	      <entry>5</entry>
	      <entry>0.255</entry>
	      <entry>0.405</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DQB1</entry>
	      <entry>20</entry>
	      <entry>9</entry>
	      <entry>0.195</entry>
	      <entry>0.280</entry>
	    </row>
	    <row>
	      <entry>DRB1</entry>
	      <entry>17</entry>
	      <entry>3</entry>
	      <entry>0.125</entry>
	      <entry>0.161</entry>
	    </row>
	  </tbody>
	</tgroup>
      </table>

      <para> In contrast to the allele level variation, at the amino
      acid level all 4 class II (DRB1, DQB1, DQA1, DPB1) loci showed
      evidence of balancing selection at many polymorphic codon sites,
      and consistently so across diverse populations. However,
      directional selection was seen for a few sites, and neutrality
      profiles were exhibited by other codons (Salamon et al. 1999,
      Valdes et al. 1999). Cases of amino acid variation showing
      balancing selection occurred at sites both within the highly
      polymorphic antigen recognition site (ARS) and outside it. Only
      for DRB1 was there evidence of more balancing selection for ARS
      sites compared to non-ARS sites. As the determination of DQ and
      DP ARS sites is based on theoretical models in lieu of the
      crystal structure, it is possible that many of the sites
      designated as non-ARS may actually be involved in antigen
      presentation. It is of particular interest in this context that
      two non-ARS sites identified as highly polymorphic and showing
      balancing selection (DQA1#47 and DQB1#26) have also been
      identified as amino acids involved in predisposition to type 1
      diabetes (Valdes et al. 1997).</para>
    </sect2>
  </sect1>

 <!--
  <section>
    <title>Gene mapping&#x2014;Linkage and association studies</title>

    <section>
      <title>Introduction</title>

      <para> The genetic and physical maps, and technologies for gene
      identification that have already emerged from the Human Genome
      Project (HGP) have had a tremendous impact on the research
      community's ability to discover the genes that underlie human
      genetic variation (Collins et al. 1997, Gelerhter et al. 1998,
      Thomson 2001a). Recent successes in the genetic mapping of
      Mendelian traits and diseases have been remarkable. However,
      progress has been exceedingly slow in elucidating the genetic
      components of complex diseases and traits, such as
      cardiovascular diseases, asthma, diabetes, rheumatoid arthritis,
      obesity, alcoholism, and schizophrenia. Complex diseases involve
      multiple genes, environmental effects, and their
      interactions. Rather than being due to specific and relatively
      rare mutations, complex diseases and traits may result
      principally from genetic variation that is relatively common in
      the general population. Examples include apolipoprotein E gene
      (<emphasis>APOE</emphasis>) variation and age of onset of
      Alzheimers disease, the angiotensin-converting enzyme gene
      (<emphasis>ACE</emphasis>) and myocardial infarction, the
      chemokine receptor CCR5 gene (<emphasis>CMKBR5</emphasis>) and
      the risk of infection in those exposed to HIV, and the many
      diseases for which immune response genes of the HLA region have
      been implicated.</para>

      <para>Diseases or traits caused by a single major gene or
      biochemical pathway defect are referred to as Mendelian, or
      single gene traits. Complicating factors such as incomplete
      penetrance&#x2014;not all genetically predisposed individuals
      manifest the disease, as in polydactyly, and variable age of
      onset effects, as in Huntington disease, are often
      present. However, the basic single gene nature of the
      inheritance pattern is often evident, with Mendelian segregation
      patterns according to recessive, dominant, or sex chromosome
      X-linked inheritance (see Gelehrter et al. 1998 for review). A
      Mendelian disease can have complex clinical effects, e. g.,
      sickle cell anemia affects many organ systems. Even with the
      same allelic mutation, as in individuals with sickle cell
      anemia, there may be considerable variation in disease severity,
      due to modifier genes. The majority of Mendelian traits also
      show allele and/or locus heterogeneity. Different alleles at one
      gene may give rise to disease, e.g., cystic fibrosis, and result
      in variation in the disease expression. Different genes may also
      be responsible for disease in different families, e.g., the
      BRCA1 and BRCA2 genes and early onset familial breast
      cancer.</para>

      <para> In contrast to Mendelian diseases, complex, or
      multifactorial diseases are generally more common, and result
      from the interaction of multiple genes and environmental
      factors. Studies of rates of occurrence of disease in twins and
      other family members compared to population level rates are used
      to demonstrate the role of genetic and environmental factors in
      complex diseases. Genetically complex diseases may exhibit the
      following properties: incomplete penetrance &#x2014;not all
      susceptible individuals are affected; the involvement of several
      disease-predisposing loci&#x2014;some of which may have a major
      effect, but many of which may have a relatively minor effect;
      interaction effects between these loci and with environmental
      factors; and heterogeneity&#x2014;so that different loci and/or
      alleles cause disease in different groups. As a result it is
      difficult with complex diseases to: localize disease genes;
      ascertain the number and relationship of disease loci involved;
      understand modes of inheritance and interaction effects;
      determine the molecular basis of disease; and understand the
      mechanism(s) by which these genetic changes give rise to
      disease, including all genetic and environmental factors and
      their interactions.</para>

      <para> The distinction in terminology between Mendelian and
      complex traits is not meant to imply that the genes underlying
      complex diseases do not follow the rules of Mendelian
      inheritance, but merely that a simple pattern of inheritance is
      not obvious. While the boundary between these two categories is
      not precisely defined, a large number of diseases clearly fall
      into each category. It is important to also remember that
      although we often use the shorthand notation of disease gene, or
      disease-causing gene, we are talking about variation at genes
      involved in normal human health and development, specific
      variations of which may lead to a disease state (Thomson and
      Esposito 1999).</para>

      <para> Sir Archibald Garrod's brilliant studies in 1908 of the
      genetics and biochemical pathways involved in &#x201c;inborn
      errors of metabolism.&#x201d; laid the conceptual foundation for
      all later studies in human genetics (Gelehrter et al. 1998). The
      single gene Mendelian nature of a large number of traits and
      diseases was subsequently identified. Gene mapping in humans
      before the 1970s was however essentially limited to the X
      chromosome, based on the specific pattern of inheritance. Future
      progress in biochemical genetics and gene mapping awaited
      advances in molecular biology.</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Mapping genes involved in disease</title>
      
      <para>There are three main approaches to mapping the genetic
      variants involved in a disease: functional cloning, the
      candidate gene strategy, and positional cloning (Gelehrter et
      al. 1998). In functional cloning, identification of the
      underlying protein defect leads to localization of the
      responsible gene
      (disease&#x2014;function&#x2014;gene&#x2014;map). Sickle cell
      anemia was the first human disease to be successfully understood
      at the molecular level and isolation of the mutant molecule led
      to the localization of the &#xf062;-globin gene on chromosome
      11. Functional cloning is, however, only useful in a subset of
      Mendelian traits where the biological basis is known, and in
      very few complex traits.</para>

      <para> In the candidate gene approach, genes with a known or
      proposed function with the potential to influence the disease
      phenotype are investigated for a direct role in disease
      (Gelehrter et al. 1998). The most successful application of the
      candidate gene approach to mapping complex diseases in humans
      has been with the HLA region on chromosome 6p21, the major
      histocompatibility complex of humans (see Section II.C
      above). Genes in the HLA region have been implicated in the
      etiology of over 200 diseases (Thorsby 1997).</para>

      <para>Positional cloning is used when the biochemical nature of
      a disease is unknown. Marker genes not related to disease
      physiology and genome-wide screens are then the starting point
      for mapping the genetic components of the disease. The aim is
      first to identify the genetic region within which a
      disease-predisposing gene lies and, once this is found, to
      localize the gene and determine its functional and biological
      role in the disease
      (disease&#x2192;map&#x2192;gene&#x2192;function). Most markers
      used nowadays are DNA based, (see Section I above).</para>

      <para>Landmarks in positional cloning have included genetic
      linkage of Huntington disease in 1983 to an RFLP (restriction
      fragment length polymorphism) marker (see section I above) on
      chromosome 4 (the gene was cloned in 1993) and the cloning of
      the cystic fibrosis gene on chromosome 7 in 1989. By 1990, when
      the HGP began, a handful of additional successes had accrued. In
      1994, the early onset familial breast/ovarian cancer (BRCA1)
      gene was cloned, and the early onset familial breast cancer
      (BRCA2) gene in 1995. By 1997 close to 100 Mendelian disease
      loci had been identified by positional cloning (Collins et
      al. 1997, Gelehrter et al. 1998). More are identified every
      month.</para>

      <para>A complementary array of approaches is available to
      uncover the different genetic facets of both Mendelian and
      complex traits and diseases (Lander and Schork 1994). Two
      complementary analytic methods, linkage analyses and association
      (linkage disequilibrium) mapping (see Sections 3 and 4 below),
      are used to detect the specific genetic regions and genes
      involved in the disease process. These approaches can be applied
      without prior knowledge of the biological basis of the disease
      using genome-wide studies, together with the candidate gene
      approach and comparative analyses using animal models of
      disease.</para>

      <para>While completion of a working draft of the human genome in
      the year 2000 has greatly aided studies of Mendelian and complex
      diseases, it does not provide an immediate solution to their
      genetics, especially for complex diseases. We must first address
      the daunting prospect of documenting the genetic variation of
      human genomes at the population level within and across ethnic
      groups. Only then, correlating this extensive genetic variation
      with disease, can we uncover the complete genetics of complex
      diseases and traits, and determine the environmental factors
      impacting on each disease (Thomson and Esposito 1999, Thomson
      2001a).</para>
    </section>

    <section>
      <title>Linkage mapping</title>
      
      <section>
	<title>Linkage analyses</title> 

	<para> Linkage analyses test for co-segregation of a marker
	and disease phenotype within a pedigree (implicating physical
	linkage between the marker gene and a gene involved in the
	disease process, and such loci are then said to be
	&#x201c;linked&#x201d;) (Ott 1999). Linkage analyses do not
	require linkage disequilibrium (LD) between the marker and
	disease loci. Different marker alleles may segregate with
	disease in each pedigree.</para>

	<para> Linkage analyses can be performed using single marker
	locus variation, and any kind of inherited difference can
	potentially be a genetic marker. For genome-wide linkage
	analyses, testing for co-segregation with disease of about
	300-400 highly polymorphic markers, usually microsatellites,
	distributed approximately evenly over the genome (average
	spacing between markers is then on the order of 10cM, i.e.,
	10% recombination) is the usual practice. The increasing
	availability of more markers across the genome, combined with
	multi-point analyses using a number of closely linked markers,
	such as microsatellites and SNPs&#x2014;hence increasing the
	informativeness with respect to co-segregation, will increase
	the power of linkage studies.</para>

	<para>When large multi-generation pedigrees are available,
	linkage analysis is a powerful technique for localizing
	disease genes and has been successfully applied to a number of
	monogenic traits, e.g., Huntington disease, and the familial
	breast cancer genes BRCA1 and BRCA2. With diabetes, it has
	been used to map MODY (maturity onset diabetes of the young)
	genes. The occurrence of multiple alleles at one genetic locus
	involved in disease, as in cystic fibrosis, does not affect
	the power of linkage analyses. However, if different Mendelian
	genes are involved in disease in different families as in
	MODY, power can be reduced if all the families are analyzed
	together.</para>

	<para>For complex diseases, the involvement of many genes and
	the strong influence of environmental factors means that large
	multi-generation pedigrees are rarely, or never, seen. Linkage
	analysis of nuclear families with both parents and two
	children affected with the disease, although less powerful, is
	therefore more commonly used to map complex traits (Thomson
	and Esposito 1999, Thomson 1995a, 1995b, 2001a,
	2001b). Consider an affected sib pair family (<xref
	linkend="affected-sib-pair"/>), and assume for simplicity we
	can distinguish all four parental chromosomes in the genetic
	region under study. Deviation from the Mendelian random
	expectations of 25%, 50%, and 25%, that the affected sibs will
	on average share 2, 1, and 0 parental chromosomes in common
	that are identical by descent (ibd) implicates a disease
	predisposing gene in the region.</para>

	<figure id="affected-sib-pair">
	  <title>Affected sib pair families</title>
	<programlisting></programlisting>
	</figure>

	<para>A nuclear family pedigree is shown with the father
         (square) and mother (circle) in the first row and the two
         affected children of either sex (shaded) in the 2nd
         row. Assume for simplicity we can distinguish all four
         parental alleles, denoted A, B, C, and D, in the genetic
         region under study, with the parental alleles ordered such
         that A and C are transmitted from the father and mother
         respectively to the first affected child (Thomson 1995a and
         1995b). Four possible configurations among the two offspring
         with respect to the alleles inherited from the parents are
         possible: they can share both parental alleles (AC); they can
         share an allele from the father (A) but differ in the alleles
         received from the mother (C and D); they can share an allele
         from the mother (C) but differ in the alleles received from
         the father (A and B); or they can share no parental alleles
         in common. These four configurations are equally likely if
         there is no influence of the genetic region under
         consideration on the disease. The parental alleles that are
         never transmitted to the affected sib pair in each family
         type are used as a control population in association studies
         using nuclear family data, the so-called AFBAC (affected
         family based control) sample (Thomson 1995a, 1995b and see
         Section 4.2 below).</para>

	<para><phrase role="strong">Affected Sib pairs</phrase></para>
	<para> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<phrase role="strong">AB</phrase> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<phrase role="strong">CD</phrase></para>
	<para> &nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;</para>
	<para>&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<phrase role="strong">AC AC share 2</phrase></para>
	<para><phrase role="strong"> AD share 1</phrase></para>
	<para><phrase role="strong"> BC share 1</phrase></para>
	<para><phrase role="strong"> BD share 0</phrase></para>

      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Linkage studies in complex diseases</title>

	<para> Linkage of the HLA region to type 1 diabetes was
	demonstrated initially with 15 affected sib pairs (Cudworth
	and Woodrow 1975) (Table 1a). This linkage, termed IDDM1, has
	been confirmed in many studies (Table 1b), with a mean ibd
	sharing of parental alleles for HLA of 72% (Payami et
	al. 1985, Pugliese 1999, Mein et al. 1998, Concannon et
	al. 1998). For some other HLA associated diseases, e.g.,
	multiple sclerosis and rheumatoid arthritis, the initial
	number of affected sib pairs required to show evidence of
	linkage has been larger, at least 50 and sometimes around
	100.</para>

<para><phrase role="strong">TABLE 1. HLA and IDDM affected sib pair values</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">a. Cudworth and Woodrow 1975</phrase></para>
<para>ibd sharing: 2 1 0 Total 15</para>
<para>observed: 10 4 1</para>
<para>observed %: 67% 27% 6%</para>
<para>&#x3c7; = 14.07, p &lt;&nbsp;0.001, mean ibd sharing = 0.805.</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">b. Payami et al. 1985, 538 families</phrase></para>
<para>ibd sharing: 2 1 0</para>
<para>observed: 373 283 55 Total 711</para>
<para>observed %: 52% 40% 8%</para>
<para>&#x3c7; = 314.03, p &lt;&nbsp;10-5, mean ibd sharing = 0.724.</para>


	<para> Given the relative ease with which linkage was
	demonstrated for many HLA associated diseases, it seemed a
	logical progression to use genome-wide linkage scans on
	affected sib pair families to investigate all complex
	diseases. Such studies of many complex disorders are in
	progress: to map the non-HLA genes in a number of diseases
	such as type 1 diabetes, multiple sclerosis, rheumatoid
	arthritis, celiac disease, and Crohn's disease; and for many
	other complex diseases, for example type 2 diabetes,
	hypertension, coronary artery disease, alcoholism, and
	schizophrenia.</para>

	<para>Type 1 diabetes was the first complex disease for which
	genome-wide linkage scans in affected sib pairs was carried
	out. Many other studies using genome-wide scans to detect
	non-HLA type 1 diabetes genes have followed since these papers
	(reviewed in Pugliese 1999). Apart from HLA, no evidence of
	major gene effects has been found. Using approximately 500
	affected sib pairs, linkages for the chromosomal regions IDDM4
	(11q13), IDDM5 (6q25), and IDDM8 (6q27) were confirmed (Luo et
	al. 1996) using the criteria of Lander and Kruglyak
	(1995). The mean ibd sharing values in these cases were much
	closer to the 50% expected randomly than seen with IDDM1:
	0.58, 0.58, and 0.60 respectively for IDDM4, IDDM5, and
	IDDM8. IDDM6 (18q12-21), IDDM10 (10p11-q11), and IDDM12 (2q33)
	have more recently been considered confirmed, using a
	combination of affected sib pair and association/linkage tests
	(see Pugliese 1999). Seven additional chromosomal regions have
	shown evidence of linkage to type 1 diabetes in one or more
	studies (reviewed in Pugliese 1999, Mein et al. 1998,
	Concannon et al. 1998).</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Observations from genome-wide linkage scans in complex
	diseases</title>
	
	<para>A common feature of all complex disease studies has been
	difficulty in both detecting and replicating linkages, with
	considerable heterogeneity seen between data sets both within
	and between populations and ethnic groups. The possible
	involvement in disease of relatively common alleles of a large
	number of loci, each with a relatively small effect overall,
	requiring study of many hundreds, and usually thousands, of
	affected sib pairs to establish linkage, can explain this
	phenomenon (reviewed in Thomson 2001a, 2001b).</para>

	<para>Two recent second generation type 1 diabetes genome
	scans continue to illustrate the heterogeneity seen in linkage
	studies in complex diseases (Mein et al. 1998, Concannon et
	al. 1998). Even more surprising, little or no support was
	found for most reported type 1 diabetes loci in one of these
	studies (Concannon et al. 1998) even with a very large sample
	size. The use of stratification analyses based on known IDDM
	loci such as in the HLA region (IDDM1) may have contributed to
	more examples of evidence of IDDM loci in the second study
	(Mein et al. 1998).</para>

	<para> Despite initial anxieties with genome-wide linkage
	scans that we would be flooded with false positives (Lander
	and Krugylak 1995), this has not been the case. An excess of
	false linkages has never been a problem with complex
	diseases. Instead we are scrambling to find any evidence of
	disease-predisposing genes.<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>In
	an insightful review of the many factors that need to be
	considered in the design of genome-wide scans and
	interpretation of linkage results, Rao (1998) pointed out that
	application of stringent criteria drastically reduces power,
	and leads to many disease genes remaining undetected. Rao's
	recommendation was that &#x201c;we tolerate/accept, on
	average, one false positive per individual scan.&#x201d; The
	issue is to have a reasonable balance between false positives
	and false negatives, while understanding that false negatives
	are the more serious concern.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Association (linkage disequilibrium) mapping</title>

	<section>
	  <title>Association analyses in case/control data</title>

	  <para> Association studies compare marker frequencies in
	  unrelated cases and controls, and test for the co-occurrence
	  of a marker and disease at the population level; a
	  significant association with disease may implicate a
	  candidate gene in the etiology of a disease. Alternatively,
	  an association can be due to linkage disequilibrium of a
	  marker allele(s) with the disease predisposing gene, and
	  this will usually imply close physical linkage of the marker
	  and disease predisposing gene (see section III.E above)
	  (Lander and Schork 1994), reflecting the historical origin
	  of a mutation on a specific chromosome with a characteristic
	  set of variation. In association studies it is essential
	  that the patient and control groups be ethnically
	  matched. If they are not, a spurious association of an
	  unlinked marker with disease can result from population
	  stratification, i.e., if there is a mixture of two groups in
	  the patient and control samples with different frequencies
	  of the marker allele and the disease. Given the large
	  variation in allele frequencies among populations (see
	  Section II above) even among populations from different
	  parts of Europe, precise matching of ancestry for the cases
	  and controls can be very difficult and historically many
	  false positives have been reported (Kidd 1993), Kang et
	  al. (1999) discuss one likely false positive for a complex
	  trait.</para>

	  <para>The success of association (linkage disequilibrium LD)
	  studies to fine map Mendelian traits following initial
	  localization of chromosomal regions by linkage analysis is
	  well documented in many different populations (Jorde et
	  al. 1994). In these studies linkage disequilibrium extended
	  on average over 500kb (0.5% recombination). There are
	  exceptions to the use of association data in localizing
	  disease genes; the breast cancer gene BRCA1 could not be
	  localized using linkage disequilibrium mapping as different
	  mutations were implicated in each family.</para>

	  <para>Association mapping may in many cases be more
	  efficient than linkage analyses in detecting genetic regions
	  involved in disease (Risch and Merikangas
	  1996). IDDM2&#x2014;the minisatellite VNTR (variable number
	  of tandem repeats) 5' to the insulin gene, which is easily
	  detected by association, is difficult to detect by linkage
	  analysis (Spielman et al. 1989). The well established and
	  strong HLA association with multiple sclerosis is not picked
	  up in all genome linkage scans (Sawcer et al. 1997). As with
	  linkage studies, haplotype level analyses can be more
	  powerful than single locus analyses (<xref linkend="Barcellos et al. 1997a"/>, Valdes et al. 1999a).</para>

	  <para>At least 12,000 highly polymorphic, evenly spaced
	  markers, giving an average distance between markers of 0.25
	  cM (250 kb), is required for an initial disease genomic
	  association scan. Association scans are thus over an order
	  of magnitude higher than the 300 to 400 markers at 10 cM
	  typically used for linkage genome scans. The use of pooled
	  samples of DNA for the study of RFLP (see e g., <xref linkend="Barcellos et al. 1997b"/>), and SNP variation (Germer et al. 1999), as well
	  as the current development of DNA chip technology for the
	  study of SNPs, has opened the way for future routine and
	  extensive use of association mapping in the study of complex
	  diseases. Genome-wide association scans in complex diseases
	  are starting to be used, currently with DNA pooling and
	  microsatellites.</para>

	  <para>Many researchers feel that the number of false
	  positives that will result from genome-wide association
	  scans make them unmanageable. A preliminary discussion of
	  power and a multi-stage strategy to reduce false positives
	  in genome-wide association studies is outlined in <xref
	  linkend="Barcellos et al. 1997b"/>. As with linkage studies
	  (Rao 1998), power should be high in an initial association
	  scan, to reduce missing associations (false negatives), and
	  sample sizes of 500 - 1,000 are recommended (<xref
	  linkend="Barcellos et al. 1997b"/>, Long and Langley
	  1999). Long and Langley (1999) have demonstrated that
	  greater power is achieved in association genome scans by
	  increasing the sample size than by increasing the number of
	  markers.<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>Association mapping
	  is appropriate for monogenic and complex diseases, and may
	  always be preferable to linkage analyses for late onset
	  diseases where it is difficult to obtain nuclear families,
	  rare diseases for which multiplex pedigrees may not be
	  available, e.g., type 1 diabetes and multiple sclerosis in
	  China, and infectious diseases.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
	  <title>Association analyses in nuclear family based data</title>

	  <para>The use of nuclear family data in association studies
	  was initially developed to avoid possible ethnic mismatching
	  between patients and randomly ascertained controls. The
	  parental marker alleles not transmitted to an affected
	  child, or never transmitted to an affected sib pair, form
	  the so-called AFBAC population (Thomson 1995a, 1995b, 2001a)
	  (see Fig. 1). In a random mating population, when there is a
	  marker association with disease, the AFBAC population
	  provides an unbiased estimate of the overall population
	  (control) marker alleles when the recombination fraction
	  between the marker and disease genes is sufficiently small
	  that it can be taken as zero (&#xf071; = 0), and differences
	  between patient and AFBAC frequencies can be tested for
	  example by a contingency table analysis for
	  heterogeneity.</para>

	  <para>Of more importance, however, is the fact that concerns
	  about population stratification effects creating
	  associations between unlinked loci are completely removed
	  with family-based data. Testing for a 50% transmission ratio
	  from parents heterozygous for a marker allele (the
	  TDT&#x2014;transmission disequilibrium test) detects
	  significant differences with marker alleles that are in both
	  linkage disequilibrium and linked to the disease
	  predisposing gene (Spielman et al. 1993, Martin et al. 1997,
	  Monks et al. 1998). This is because a compound null
	  hypothesis is always being tested which involves a term
	  which is zero if the marker and disease are unlinked, and a
	  term which is zero if there is no linkage disequilibrium at
	  the population level. Thus, associations at the population
	  level of unlinked marker loci with disease caused by
	  population stratification, migration or admixture, are
	  eliminated, and significant effects are only seen for marker
	  loci linked and in linkage disequilibrium with the disease
	  loci. Further, results across populations can be combined
	  using the TDT statistic, although it is important to keep in
	  mind that power could be reduced if the same association(s)
	  is not seen in all populations, association screens.</para>
	</section>

	<section>
	  <title>Association studies in complex diseases</title>

	  <para>Association mapping has been the main approach in
	  implicating genes of the HLA region in disease etiology
	  (Table 2). Association studies in the early 1970s
	  distinguished type 1 (HLA associated) from type 2 (not HLA
	  associated) diabetes. Association mapping has also been
	  involved in mapping non-HLA genes. In a small subset of type
	  2 diabetes cases association studies have identified the
	  role of candidate genes in disease, e.g., the insulin gene,
	  insulin receptor gene, glukokinase gene, and genes in the
	  mitochondrial genome (see Thomson (1997) for
	  references).</para>

	  <table>
	    <title>HLA associated diseases</title>
	    <tgroup cols="3">
	      <colspec colname="col1"/>
	      <colspec colname="col2"/>
	      <colspec colname="col3"/>
	      <thead>
		<row>
		  <entry>HLA</entry>
		  <entry>Patients <footnote>
		      <para>For each disease, the frequency of the associated
	  HLA allele is given in patients and controls. The letter
	  designation denotes the HLA gene, while the number is
	  assigned to a specific allele at the gene. For ease of
	  reading, the data shown are older serological level HLA
	  typing, rather than more recent molecular typing. The data
	  are modified from Thorsby (1997).</para>
		    </footnote></entry>
		  <entry>Controls</entry>
		</row>
	      </thead>
	      <tbody>
		<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Ankylosing spondylitis</entry></row>
		<row>
		  <entry>B27</entry>
		  <entry>90%</entry> 
		  <entry>9%</entry>
		</row>
		<row><entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Type 1 diabetes</entry></row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR3</entry> 
		  <entry>52%</entry>
		  <entry>23%</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR4</entry>
		  <entry>74%</entry>
		  <entry>24%</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR3 or DR4</entry>
		  <entry>93%</entry>
		  <entry>43%</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Multiple sclerosis</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR2</entry>
		  <entry>86%</entry>
		  <entry>33%</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Rheumatoid
		  arthritis</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR4</entry>
		  <entry>81%</entry>
		  <entry>33%</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry namest="col1" nameend="col3">Narcolepsy</entry>
		</row>
		<row>
		  <entry>DR2</entry>
		  <entry>&gt;95%</entry>
		  <entry>33%</entry>
		</row>
	      </tbody>
	    </tgroup>
	  </table>

	  <para><phrase role="strong"> </phrase>The potential of
	  association studies as the optimal strategy for follow-up of
	  regions showing preliminary evidence of linkage for complex
	  diseases has been demonstrated (Mein et al. 1998), and
	  awaits full utilization. As with linkage studies,
	  heterogeneity in association results for complex diseases is
	  also seen between studies, especially between populations,
	  and is expected (Mein et al. 1998, Long and Langley
	  1999). In their simulation study, Long and Langley (1999)
	  concluded that association studies have a low repeatability
	  unless sample sizes are on the order of 500
	  individuals.</para>

	  <para>Association mapping is appropriate for monogenic and
	  complex diseases, and may always be preferable to linkage
	  analyses for late onset diseases where it is difficult to
	  obtain nuclear families, rare diseases for which multiplex
	  pedigrees may not be available, e.g., type 1 diabetes and
	  multiple sclerosis in China, and infectious diseases. Study
	  design can incorporate disease heterogeneity and interaction
	  effects between loci.</para>
	</section>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>Determining the genetic components involved in disease,
	the haplotype method</title>

	<para> Determining the precise HLA components of disease is
	difficult for the following primary reasons: multiple genetic
	factors are involved; the HLA genes are in strong linkage
	disequilibrium; HLA region loci have many polymorphic
	residues; common HLA alleles may be involved in disease; and
	interaction effects among HLA, and/or non-HLA, disease loci
	may be important. These characteristics make necessary a
	multi-strategy approach, in which complementary methods are
	used. These include analysis of data from various ethnically
	or geographically defined groups, as differences in HLA
	polymorphism and disease prevalence across groups can point
	toward the precise genetic factors that are important in
	disease. The methods which have been applied to HLA data to
	identify the actual disease predisposing factors, and to
	determine all disease factors in the region, and the
	difficulties encountered, apply equally to non-HLA
	regions.</para>

	<para>While linkage disequilibrium is our ally in detecting
	genetic regions involved in disease, it confounds attempts to
	identify the actual gene in the region involved in disease and
	to identify additional genes in the region contributing to
	disease. The so-called haplotype method to identify
	disease-predisposing alleles and amino acids in a genetic
	region is a stratification analysis to take account of the
	effects of linkage disequilibrium (Valdes et al. 1997, Valdes
	and Thomson 1997). If all alleles, or amino acid sites,
	directly involved in disease in a genetic region have been
	identified, then considering haplotypes (chromosome
	combinations) containing all these sites, the relative
	frequencies of alleles and amino acid sites on these
	haplotypes not involved in disease should be the same in
	patients and controls. The absolute frequencies of these
	haplotypes will differ between patients and controls, but the
	ratio of variants at sites not involved in disease will not
	differ between patients and controls, provided all alleles or
	amino acids involved in disease have been identified and all
	these sites are included in the haplotypes
	considered. Obviously, the haplotype method cannot distinguish
	between sites which are very highly correlated in a
	population, however ethnic comparisons can help identify the
	predisposing factors. The method however can unequivocally
	determine if all disease predisposing amino acid sites in
	linkage disequilibrium in a genetic region have
	<emphasis>not</emphasis> been identified. At the amino acid
	level, a combination of sites at the HLA class II loci DRB1,
	DQA1, and DQB1 was shown to be highly correlated with the
	DR-DQ contribution to type 1 diabetes and to correlate with
	disease incidence (Valdes et al. 1997). In the alcohol
	dehydrogenase gene cluster variants at two tightly linked
	genes (ADH1B and ADHIC) cause altered enzyme activities. The
	high activity alleles at both loci are very common in East
	Asian populations and appear to protect against alcoholism
	when tested individually. Osier et al. (2000) showed by this
	haplotype method that the variant at ADH1B was responsible for
	the protective effect while the variant at ADH1C showed the
	statistical association only because of linkage disequilibrium
	with the variant at ADH1B.</para>
      </section>

      <section>
	<title>The Future: Overview</title>

	<para>With completion of the HGP, the functional and
	positional cloning of Mendelian traits and diseases will
	become fairly routine (Gelehrter et al. 1998). For genetically
	complex human diseases and traits the HGP will not provide an
	immediate solution to their genetics, although the ability to
	identify candidate genes de novo and in a region identified by
	positional cloning will greatly reduce the time required to
	home in on the actual genes involved in complex
	diseases.</para>

	<para>A multi-strategy approach to the mapping of complex
	diseases and traits is still appropriate: no single method is
	sufficient or optimal (Thomson 2001a). Genome-wide linkage
	studies are now routine, although still expensive and time
	consuming. Despite extensive efforts by many groups, progress
	in the mapping of complex diseases has been exceedingly slow;
	only a few genes and some genetic regions involved in complex
	diseases have been identified. The general picture is one of
	difficulty in locating disease genes and replication of
	reported linkages.</para>

	<para>The practical application of association studies in
	Mendelian and complex diseases in fine-mapping of genetic
	regions identified by linkage analyses has been demonstrated
	for many, but not all, disease predisposing loci. Also, while
	association mapping can narrow down a genetic region
	implicated via a linkage study, complete sequencing of this
	region, which may be many Mb long, is still an arduous
	task. Genome-wide association studies are now feasible with
	pooled DNA samples and are starting to be used. As with
	linkage studies, the overall power of association genome scans
	to detect disease genes is unknown. Power for both linkage and
	association studies depends on a number of unknown parameters,
	will vary across the genome, and also between populations and
	ethnic groups.<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>The increasing
	availability of more markers across the genome, combined with
	multi-point analyses using closely linked markers will
	increase the power of linkage and association studies,
	including the follow-up of regions potentially involved in
	disease.</para>

	<para>Increasing technological advances in molecular biology,
	such as the development of SNPs combined with DNA chip
	technology, and biocomputing will allow screening and analysis
	of large sample sizes, with predicted future rates of data
	output which are astronomical. The full development of SNPs
	will eventually permit routine typing for variation in every
	human gene, and their regulatory regions, the ultimate
	association study.</para>
	</section>
      </section>
    </section>
-->
</appendix>

<bibliography>
  <title>References</title>
  
  <warning><para>Bibliography is incomplete, still
    converting...</para></warning>
  
  <biblioentry id="Barcellos et al. 1997a">
    <biblioset relation="article">
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>L</firstname>
	  <othername>F</othername>
	  <surname>Barcellos</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>W</firstname>
	  <surname>Klitz</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>L</firstname>
	  <othername>L</othername>
	  <surname>Field</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>R</firstname>
	  <surname>Tobias</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>A</firstname>
	  <othername>M</othername>
	  <surname>Bowcock</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>R</firstname>
	  <surname>Wilson</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <surname>Nelson</surname>
	  <firstname>M</firstname>
	  <othername>P</othername>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
      <citetitle>Association mapping of disease loci, by use of a pooled DNA genomic screen</citetitle>
      <volumenum>61</volumenum>
      <pagenums>734-47</pagenums>
      </biblioset>
      <biblioset relation="journal">
	<citetitle>Am J Hum Genet</citetitle>
      </biblioset>
    </biblioentry>

  <biblioentry id="Barcellos et al. 1997b">
    <biblioset relation="article">
      <authorgroup>
	<author>
	  <firstname>L</firstname>
	  <othername>F</othername>
	  <surname>Barcellos</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>G</firstname>
	  <surname>Thomson</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>M</firstname>
	  <surname>Carrington</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>J</firstname>
	  <surname>Schafer</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>A</firstname>
	  <othername>B</othername>
	  <surname>Begovich</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>P</firstname>
	  <surname>Lin</surname>
	</author>
	<author>
	  <firstname>X</firstname>
	  <othername>H</othername>
	  <surname>Xu</surname>
	</author>
      </authorgroup>
      <pubdate>1997</pubdate>
      <citetitle>Chromosome 19 single-locus and multilocus haplotype associations with multiple sclerosis. Evidence of a new susceptibility locus in Caucasian and Chinese patients</citetitle>
      <volumenum>278</volumenum>
      <pagenums>1256-61</pagenums>
    </biblioset>
    <biblioset relation="journal">
      <citetitle>Jama</citetitle>
    </biblioset>
  </biblioentry>
</bibliography>


<!--
<para>Baur M, Danilovs J (1980) Population genetic analysis of HLA-A, B, C, DR, and other genetic markers. In: Terasaki P (ed) Histocompatibility Testing, 1980. UCLA Tissue Typing Laboratory, Los Angelas, pp 955-993.</para>
<para>Begovich AB, McClure GR, Suraj VC, Helmuth RC, Fildes N, Bugawan TL, Erlich HA, et al (1992) Polymorphism, recombination, and linkage disequilibrium within the HLA class II region. J Immunol 148:249-58.</para>
<para>Chen JJ, Hollenbach JA, Trachtenberg EA, Just JJ, Carrington M, Ronningen KS, Begovich A, King MC, McWeeney SK, Mack SJ, Erlich HA, Thomson G. 1999. Hardy-Weinberg testing for HLA class II (DRB1, DQA1, DQB1 and DPB1) loci in 26 human ethnic groups. Tissue Antigens 54: 533-542.</para>
<para>Chen JJ, Thomson G (1999) The variance for the disequilibrium coefficient in the individual Hardy- Weinberg test. Biometrics 55:1269-72.</para>
<para>Cochron W (1954) Some methods for strengthening the common Chi-Squared tests. Biometrics 10:417-451.</para>
<para>Daly, M.J., J.D. Rioux, S.E. Schaffner, T.J. Hudson, and E.S. Lander. 2001. High-resolution haplotype structure in the human genome. Nature Genetics 29:229-232.</para>
<para>Dempster A, Laird N, Rubin D (1977) Maximum likelihood estimation from incomplete data using the EM algorithm. J Royal Stat Soc 39:1-38.</para>
<para>Dienard AS, Kidd KK. 1995. &nbsp;Levels of DNA polymorphism in extant and extinct hominoids. &nbsp;In:The Origin and Past of Modern Humans as Viewed from DNA. &nbsp;Eds. S. Brenner and K. Hanihara, World Scientific, New Jersey, pp 149-170.</para>
<para>Elston R, Forthofer R (1977) Testing for Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium in small samples. Biometrics 33:536-542.</para>
<para>Emigh T (1980) A comparison of tests for Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium. Biometrics 36:627-642.</para>
<para>Ewens W (1972) The sampling theory of selectively neutral alleles. Theor. Pop. Biol. 3:87-112.</para>
<para>Fallin D, Schork NJ (2000) Accuracy of haplotype frequency estimation for biallelic loci, via the expectation-maximization algorithm for unphased diploid genotype data. Am J Hum Genet 67:947-59.</para>
<para>Guo SW, Thompson EA (1992) Performing the exact test of Hardy-Weinberg proportion for multiple alleles. Biometrics 48:361-72.</para>
<para>Hacia JG, Fan J-B, Ryder O., Jin L., Edgemon K, Ghandour G, Mayer RA, Sun B., Hsie L., Robbins CM, Brody LC, Wang D, Lander ES, Lipshutz R, Fodor SPA, Collins FS. &nbsp;1999. Determination of ancestral alleles for human single-nucleotide polymorphisms using high-density oligonucleotide arrays. &nbsp;Nature Genetics 22: 164-167.</para>
<para>Hartl, D.L. and A.G. Clark. 1997. Principles of population genetics. 3<superscript>rd</superscript> Edition. Sinauer Associates, Inc. Publishers. Sunderland, MA.</para>
<para>Hawley M, Kidd K (1995) HAPLO: a program using the EM algorythm to estimate the frequencies of multi-site haplotypes. Journal of Heredity 86:409-411.</para>
<para>Hedrick P, Thomson G (1983) Evidence for balancing selection at HLA. Genetics 104:449-456.</para>
<para>Hollenbach JA, Thomson G, Cao K, Fernandez-Vi&#x2013;a M, Erlich HA, Bugawan TL, Winkler C, Winter M, Klitz W. 2001. HLA diversity, differentiation, and haplotype evolution in Mesoamerican natives. Human Immunology 62: 378-390.</para>
<para>Hollenbach JA, Thomson G, Cao K, Fernandez-Vina M, Erlich HA, Bugawan TL, Winkler C, et al (2001) HLA diversity, differentiation, and haplotype evolution in Mesoamerican Natives. Hum Immunol 62:378-90.</para>
<para>Howell WM, Jobs M, Gyllensten U, Brookes AJ, 1999. &nbsp;Dynamic allele-specific hybridization. &nbsp;Nature Biotechnology 17: 87-88.</para>
<para>Huttley GA, Smith MW, Carrington M, O'Brien SJ (1999) A scan for linkage disequilibrium across the human genome. Genetics 152:1711-22.</para>
<para>Iyengar S, Seaman M, Deinard AS, Rosenbaum HC, Sirugo G, Castiglione, CM, Kidd JK, Kidd KK, 1998. &nbsp;Analysis of cross-species polymerase chain reaction products to infer the ancestral state of human polymorphisms. &nbsp;DNA sequence 8: 317-327.</para>
<para>Kidd, K.K. and L.L. Cavalli-Sforza, 1974. The role of genetic drift in the differentiation of Icelandic and Norwegian cattle. Evolution 28:381-395.</para>
<para>Kidd, J.R., A.J. Pakstis, H. Zhao, R.-B. Lu, F.E. Okonofua, A. Odunsi, E. Grigorenko, B. Bonne-Tamir, J. Friedlaender, L.O. Schulz, J. Parnas, and K.K. Kidd, 2000. Haplotypes and linkage disequilibrium at the phenylalanine hydroxylase locus (PAH) in a global representation of populations. American Journal of Human Genetics 66:1882-1899.</para>
<para>Klitz W (1992) Evotutionary and popualtion perspectives of the human HLA complex. In: (eds) HM (ed) Evolutionary Biology. Vol. Hecht MK (eds), pp 35-72.</para>
<para>Klitz W, Thomson G, Baur MP (1986) Contrasting evolutionary histories among tightly linked HLA loci. Am J Hum Genet 39:340-9.</para>
<para>Levene H (1949) On a matching problem arising in genetics. Ann Math Stat 20:627-642</para>
<para>Long JC, Williams RC, Urbanek M (1995) An E-M algorithm and testing strategy for multiple-locus haplotypes. Am J Hum Genet 56:799-810.</para>
<para>Louis E, Dempster ER (1987) An exact test for Hardy-Weinberg and multiple alleles. Biometrics 43:805-811.</para>
<para>Louis EJ, Dempster ER (1987) An Exact Test for Hardy-Weinberg and Multiple Alleles. Biometrics 43:805-812.</para>
<para>Metropolis N, AW R, Teller AH, E T (1953) Equations of state calculations by fast computing machines. Journal of Chemical Physics 21:1087-1092.</para>
<para>Meyer D, Thomson G. 2001. How selection shapes variation of the human major histocompatibility complex: a review. Annals of Human Genetics 65: 1-26.</para>
<para>Moonsamy PV, Klitz W, Tilanus MG, Begovich AB (1997) Genetic variability and linkage disequilibrium within the DP region in the CEPH families. Hum Immunol 58:112-21.</para>
<para>Mullis KB, Faloona FA, 1987. &nbsp;Specific synthesis of DNA in vitro via a polymerase-catalyzed chain reaction. &nbsp;Pp 335-350 in J. N. Abelson and M.I. Simon (eds.) Methods in Enzymology 155: R. Wu, ed. Recombinant DNA, part F. &nbsp;Academic Press, New York.</para>
<para>Osier, M., A.J. Pakstis, J.R. Kidd, J.-F. Lee, S.-J. Yin, H.-C. Ko, H.J. Edenberg, R.-B. Lu, and K.K. Kidd, 1999. Linkage disequilibrium at the ADH2 and ADH3 loci and risk of alcoholism. American Journal of Human Genetics 64:1147-1157.</para>
<para>Reich, D.E., M. Cargill, S. Bolk, J. Ireland, P.C. Sabeti, D.J. Richter, T. Lavery, R. Kouyoumjian, S.F. Farhadian, R. Ward, and E.S. Lander. 2001. Linkage disequilibrium in the human genome. Nature 411:199-204.</para>
<para>Reynolds, J., B.S. Weir, and C.C. Cockerman. 1983. Estimation of the coancestry coefficient: Basis for a short-term genetic distance. Genetics 105-767-779.</para>
<para>Robinson WP, Asmussen MA, Thomson G (1991) Three-locus systems impose additional constraints on pairwise disequilibria. Genetics 129:925-30.</para>
<para>Salamon H, Klitz W, Easteal S, Gao X, Erlich HA, Fernandez-Vina M, Trachtenberg EA, et al (1999) Evolution of HLA class II molecules: Allelic and amino acid site variability across populations. Genetics 152:393-400.</para>
<para>Salamon H, Klitz W, Easteal S, Gao XJ, Erlich HA, Fernandez-Vi&#x2013;a M, Trachtenberg EA, McWeeney SK, Nelson MP, Thomson G. 1999. Evolution of HLA class II molecules: allelic and amino acid site variability across populations. Genetics 152: 393-400.</para>
<para>Schipper RF, D'Amaro J, de Lange P, Schreuder GM, van Rood JJ, Oudshoorn M (1998) Validation of haplotype frequency estimation methods. Hum Immunol 59:518-23.</para>
<para>Schneider (2000) Arlequin: A software for population genetics data analysis.</para>
<para>Single R, Meyer D, Hollenbach J, Nelson M, Noble J, Erich H, Thomson G (2002) Haplotype Frequency Estimation in Patient Populations: The Effect of Departures from Hardy-Weinberg Proportions and Collapsing over a Locus in the HLA Region. Genetic Epidemiology, In press.</para>
<para>Single RM, Meyer D, Hollenbach J, Nelson M, Noble JA, Erlich HA, Thomson G. 2002. Haplotype frequency estimation in patient populations: an example from the HLA region. Genetic Epidemiology, In press.</para>
<para>Slatkin M (1994) An exact test for neutrality based on the Ewens sampling distribution. Genetical Research 64:71-74.</para>
<para>Slatkin M (1994) Linkage disequilibrium in growing and stable populations. Genetics 137:331-336.</para>
<para>Slatkin M (1996) A correction to the exact test based on the Ewens sampling distribution. Genetical Research 68:259-260.</para>
<para>Thomson G (1977) The effect of a selected locus on linked neutral loci. Genetics 85:753-88.</para>
<para>Thomson G, Esposito MS. 1999. The genetics of complex diseases. Trends in Genetics 15: M17-M20.</para>
<para>Valdes AM, McWeeney SK, Meyer D, Nelson MP, Thomson G (1999) Locus and population specific evolution in HLA class II genes. Annals of Human Genetics 63:27-43.</para>
<para>Valdes AM, Thomson G (1997) Detecting disease-predisposing variants: The haplotype method. American Journal of Human Genetics 60:703-716</para>
<para>Watterson G (1978) The homozygosity test of neutrality. Genetics 88:405-417.</para>
<para>Wright, S. 1931. Evolution in Mendelian populations. Genetics 16:97-159.</para>
<para>Xiao W, Oefner PJ, 2001. &nbsp;Denaturing high-performance liquid chromatography: A review. &nbsp;Human Mutation 17: 439-474.</para>
<para>Yates F (1963) Contingency tables involving small numbers and the Chi-square test. J Royal Stat Soc (supp) 1:217-235.</para>
<para>Zhao H, Pakstis AJ, Kidd JR, Kidd KK (1999) Assessing linkage disequilibrium in a complex genetic system. I. Overall deviation from random association. Annals of Human Genetics 63:167-179.</para>
<para>Zhao, H., A.J. Pakstis, J.R. Kidd, and K.K. Kidd, 1999. Assessing linkage disequilibrium in a complex genetic system I. Overall deviation from random association. Annals of Human Genetics 63:167-179.</para>
<para>31</para>
<para>PSB Tutorial on Genetic Variation 11/15/01 3:19 PM</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Figure I.D.1. RFLP: Restriction Fragment Length Polymorphism</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
</section>
-->

<!--
Local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("biostat.xml" "appendix" "article" ("sect1" "glossary" "appendix"))
End:
-->