<?xml version="1.0" encoding="ISO-8859-1"?>
<!-- <section>
<title></title>
<para><phrase role="strong">Human Genetic Variation</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Kenneth K. Kidd, Judith R. Kidd, Glenys Thomson, Diogo Meyer</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Natures of the different types of polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A terminology note</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">DNA polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para>Biallelic polymorphisms (SNPs and InDels)</para>
<para>Multiallelic polymorphisms (STRPs and VNTRs)</para>
<para>Haplotypes</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Polymorphism detection methods</phrase></para>
<para>Introduction</para>
<para>Polymerase chain reaction</para>
<para>Gel electrophoresis</para>
<para>Resequencing</para>
<para>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis</para>
<para>Denaturing high performance liquid chromatography</para>
<para>SSCP</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Typing methods</phrase></para>
<para>Gel electrophoresis-based</para>
<para>Non-gel-based</para>
<para><phrase role="strong"> Overview of the distribution of variation</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in the genome</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in populations</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Variation in a gene of interest:  HLA</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong"> Methods for analysis of genetic variation</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Background</phrase></para>
<para>Statistical aspects of genetics</para>
<para>Simple rules of probability</para>
<para>Likelihood and maximum likelihood</para>
<para>Genotype-phenotype relationships</para>
<para>Gene frequency in a population</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Calculation of allele frequencies and heterozygosity</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Hardy-Weinberg ratios</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Measuring genetic variation among populations</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Measuring non-randomness of alleles on chromosomes</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Tests of neutrality (or selection)</phrase></para>
<para>
<phrase role="strong">Gene mapping&mdash;Linkage studies, TDT, etc</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">References</phrase></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">I. Natures of the different types of polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A.  A terminology note</phrase></para>
<para> The term <emphasis>polymorphism</emphasis> means <quote>many forms</quote>.  Thus, it applies to the gene or site in the DNA and not to a single allele.  There is a common misuse of the term to apply to the less common allele (<quote>The frequency of the polymorphism was 5% in patients.</quote>) This is incorrect; a polymorphism does not have a frequency but does have a heterozygosity.  Another common misuse is to apply the term to any site that varies, as in the term <emphasis>SNP</emphasis>, when nothing is known about the heterozygosity of the polymorphism.  The term <emphasis>polymorphism</emphasis> is meant to apply to sites/genes with <quote>common</quote> variation.  Specific guidelines differ among authors, but a common rule is that the most common allele must have a frequency of less than 99%.  For a two-allele polymorphism, this means the less common allele has to have a frequency of at least 1%.  If the less common allele is less frequent than this, the allele can be called a rare variant and the locus is not polymorphic.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">B.  DNA polymorphisms</phrase></para>
<para> Markers such as variation at protein and blood group loci were initially used in the analysis of genetic traits; however most were of limited use owing to low levels of variation, low heterozygosity. Early in the 1980s, these markers began to be replaced with DNA polymorphisms.  About then was the discovery of the first restriction fragment length polymorphism (RFLP).  Such polymorphisms are detected by the ability of a segment of DNA to be cut, or not, by a specific restriction enzyme that recognizes between 4-6 specific DNA base pairs and then visualized by the Southern blotting technology with a specific cloned piece of DNA used as a probe.  Two important advances in molecular biology have since made possible the rapid development of highly informative markers for genetic mapping: the discovery of the polymerase chain reaction (PCR) methodology and the discovery that microsatellite markers exist across the genome and can be PCR amplified. </para>
<para> There are at least two classes of polymorphic markers that we shall deal with - those that are by their nature biallelic, and those which tend to be multiallelic.  Among the biallelic polymorphisms are single nucleotide polymorphisms and insertions (or deletions); the multiallelic polymorphisms include micro- and mini- satellites.  There is a third class of polymorphisms that consists of combinations of two or more polymorphisms from either or both of the first two classes; these are called haplotypes.   We shall describe each class separately.</para>
<para></para>
<para> 1.  Biallelic polymorphisms  (SNPs and InDels)</para>
<para></para>
<para> Single-nucleotide<phrase role="strong"> </phrase>polymorphisms (SNPs) are the most common type of human DNA genetic variation, occurring on average 1 per 1,000 base pairs.(See Figure I.B.1) Insertion/deletion polymorphisms are more rare, but otherwise similar analytically to SNPs.  They are both mostly biallelic and less informative than microsatellites; however, they are more frequent, mutationally more stable than microsatellites, and more amenable to automation and DNA chip technology.  By <quote>mutationally more stable</quote> we mean that SNPs and InDels generally can be considered as one-off events.  That is, they are caused by a single mutational event that occurred once in the history of a species.  We do not expect to see recurrent mutations at the same site except as extremely rare events.  We can determine the ancestral state in almost all cases simply by determining the genotype of our nearest phylogenetic relatives, the other great apes, following the logic in Iyengar et al. (1998) (see also Hacia et al., 1999).  In nearly all cases, we have found that we share a single allele with them, and, by inference, this is the <emphasis>ancestral</emphasis> or original allele in humans and the other allele is the <emphasis>derived</emphasis> allele. </para>
<para></para>
<para>Figure I.B.1. SNPs: Single Nucleotide Polymorphisms</para>
<para></para>
<para>The actual mutational mechanism for the two kinds of polymorphisms is different.  A SNP is caused initially by a change of one base to another on one single chromosome of one single person in the world.  That change is probably due to a relatively simple mistake in the cell's DNA-replicating machinery.  Thus, for example an A (adenosine) may be substituted for a C (cytosine) in a certain position in the DNA sequence.  As in any polymorphism, if the mutational event occurs in a germ line cell, it may be transmitted to offspring and either dropout or increase over successive generations to a detectable or polymorphic frequency in the population and species.  In the case of an InDel, there are several mechanisms.  A very short InDel (1-3 bp) may be caused by simple replicating mistakes just as SNPs are.  A second type of InDel has a much more complicated mechanism of "mutation".  These are called inserted elements and tend to be considerably longer.  Some of these longer elements may be PolII or PolIII transcribed elements that are inserted more or less randomly into the genome.  The inserted elements belong to various families of DNA ranging in length from perhaps 100-7,000 bp or longer and they seem to be inserted more-or-less randomly throughout the genome.  Some of the longer elements (<emphasis>long interspersed elements,</emphasis> <emphasis>lines</emphasis>) exist in the genome 50,000 times.  Whereas some of the shorter elements (<emphasis>short interspersed elements, sines</emphasis>) exist in the genome 500,000-1,000,000 times.  They may be present as either <emphasis>fixed</emphasis> (present on all chromosomes) or polymorphic insertions.  Alternatively, an element (having been inserted and becoming fixed) may be deleted on one single chromosome, and the deletion condition might rise in frequency, becoming polymorphic.  Because some of these elements are not excised precisely, there is often a small vestige sequence left behind - a footprint.  Thus, these "interspersed" elements may be polymorphic coming (insertions) or going (deletions). It is important to note that not all of this huge number of inserted (or inserted and subsequently deleted) elements is polymorphic - only a very small percentage of them seem to be so.  Most of these interspersed elements were inserted long ago in primate evolution and are completely fixed in the genome of humans; only the recently inserted (or deleted) elements will possibly be polymorphic.   Other InDels have other mechanisms such as unequal recombination where meiotic recombination is not perfectly symmetric and the products of recombination have a deletion on one chromosome and a corresponding insertion on the other chromosome.  There are undoubtedly many other mechanisms.  But these are probably the most common for SNPs and InDels.</para>
<para>SNPs are very common in the genome, probably existing at a frequency of &gt;1/1000 bp.  InDels are thought to be less common and may occur at a similar rate to STRPs and VNTRs (see below).  Very small indels (1 or 2 base pairs) may be more common, but still less common than SNPs.  The commonness of SNPs makes them extremely useful in linkage and gene mapping studies.  There will nearly always be a marker in the genomic region of interest.   However, the fact that they (along with InDels) have only two alleles (and hence low heterozygosity - maximum heterozygosity = 50%) means that they will be less informative for such studies.  "Less informative" in this context means that in many families there will be no variation at a given polymorphic site - i.e., the alleles are not segregating in those families.  (Furthermore, Murphy's Law states that the polymorphic site nearest the gene for the trait being mapped will not vary in the most informative families for the trait.)  In addition to their frequent occurrence, the fact that SNPs are very stable (i.e., essentially no recurrent mutations) makes them very useful for human population and evolutionary studies.  Wherever a derived allele is seen (be it in Africa or Patagonia), that allele is identical by descent with every other such allele.  Such identity means that these polymorphisms are very good markers of migration, admixture or random genetic drift.  The ability to determine polarity of the polymorphism (ancestral or derived) is important to interspecies and other evolutionary studies.</para>
<para></para>
<para> 2.  Multiallelic polymorphisms (STRPs and VNTRs)</para>
<para></para>
<para> Microsatellites consist of approximately 10&mdash;50 copies of particular DNA sequence motifs ranging from 1-6 nucleotide base pairs that occur in tandem repetition.  (See Figure I.B.2) These repeat sequences occur frequently and randomly across the human genome.  When the repeat number is polymorphic, microsatellites are called <emphasis>short tandem repeat polymorphisms (STRPs).</emphasis>  STRP loci usually have multiple alleles and high levels of variation, i.e., high heterozygosity.  They have rapidly replaced RFLP markers in gene mapping (especially disease genes) studies owing to these features and to their ease of typing, including the small amount of template DNA required.  Remember that heterozygosity can never exceed 50% for a biallelic marker whereas STRPs can easily have heterozygosities &gt;75%.</para>
<para></para>
<para>     Figure I.B.2. STRP: Short Tandem Repeat Polymorphism</para>
<para></para>
<para>Microsatellites are named by analogy with larger minisatellite arrays (also referred to as variable number of tandem repeats&mdash;VNTRs). VNTRs are also highly polymorphic and powerful markers in forensic and paternity studies (DNA fingerprinting). (See Figure I.B.3) However, they are less common than STRPs and are not evenly distributed throughout the genome. Their larger sequence motifs make them less amenable to PCR technology and use in genomic screening analyses.  STRPs and VNTRs, on the other hand, tend to be much more dynamic than the biallelic SNPs and InDels.  The mutation rates are higher, there are more alleles, and it is usually impossible to determine which is the ancestral allele.  Very often, if there is an STRP or VNTR at a given position in <emphasis>Homo sapiens,</emphasis> there is also an STRP or VNTR at the homologous position in the genomes of the other great apes.  However, even when the copy number is overlapping and alleles seem to be shared between species and or genera, it has been shown (see Deinard and Kidd, 1995) that the mutations giving rise to the alleles have recurred.  Another way of stating this is that the coalescent of the alleles is recent and distinct across the species.  Even within humans it may be impossible to state that alleles of the same number of repeated units are <quote>identical by descent</quote> because mutations can increase and decrease the repeat number.  In general, STRP loci with a small number of repeat units have low mutation rates and those with a large number have a higher mutation rate. This correlates with the number of alleles seen in a population and with the observations in haplotypes that a particular haplotype will be characterized by a single STRP allele when the STRP has a low number of repeats.  [example: DRD2]  Thus, the mutation rates for STRPs may vary by three orders of magnitude in humans.  </para>
<para></para>
<para> Figure I.B.3. The DRD4 VNTR</para>
<para></para>
<para>The actual mutational mechanisms generating STRPs and VNTRs are generally poorly understood, but with some hand waving, we shall describe some possibilities.  Both of these types of polymorphism are characterized by their tandem nature - they are multiple repetitions of either short or longer blocks of DNA several to many times.  The most tempting explanations are that the STRPs are a "stuttering" effect of the replicating mechanism where the enzyme responsible for replicating has trouble "counting" or keeping track of how many copies of a given sequence it is making.  The VNTRs, on the other hand, seem most likely to be caused by unequal recombination. </para>
<para>STRPs, VNTRs, and InDels occur in the genome less often than do SNPs, However, when they do occur in a region of interest, the heterozygosity of the STRPs and VNTRs can be high (often ranging from 70%-90%).  This high average heterozygosity means that these polymorphisms are extremely informative for linkage or mapping studies.  (That is, the polymorphism is likely to be segregating in every family of interest.)  While the mutation rate may be high, it is generally low enough that transmission in most families will be faithful.  On the other hand, because the mutation rate is relatively high, the utility for human population and evolutionary studies is somewhat to greatly reduced relative to that of SNPs.  The inability to infer polarity is a disadvantage for studies of evolution (gene evolution or human evolution).  </para>
<para></para>
<para> 3.  Haplotypes</para>
<para></para>
<para>There is a final form of variation that we can study:  Polymorphisms of any type can be studied individually and combined into groups of two or more polymorphisms tightly clustered on the chromosome  - <emphasis>haplotypes</emphasis>.  If two or more polymorphisms exist in close proximity in the DNA (e.g., 1 to several thousands of bases apart), they can be studied jointly as a haplotype.  A haplotype is the <emphasis>haploid genotype</emphasis> of the alleles at polymorphisms along a rather short stretch of the chromosome.  For example, consider three two-allele polymorphisms:  the first has alleles named 1 and 2, the second has alleles named A and B, and the third has alleles named 5 and 6.  These alleles can occur on a chromosome in any of the following eight possible combinations:</para>
<para>(a) 1-A-5</para>
<para>(b) 1-B-5</para>
<para>(c) 1-A-6</para>
<para>(d) 1-B-6</para>
<para>(e) 2-A-5</para>
<para>(f) 2-B-5</para>
<para>(g) 2-A-6</para>
<para>(h) 2-B-6.</para>
<para>If alleles 1, A, and 6, for example, have been inferred from the sequence in other great apes to be ancestral, then haplotype (c) (1-A-6) is the ancestral haplotype (or ancestral chromosome); and haplotype (f) (2-B-5) is the <emphasis>triply derived</emphasis> haplotype.  Because recombination is very infrequent in in molecularly very short regions, each of the possible haplotypes can be considered for analytic purposes as a separate allele exactly analogous to alleles at any other polymorphism (SNP, InDel, etc.).  We can compute the haplotype frequency, haplotype heterozygosity, etc.  Additionally, there is an aspect to haplotypes not available at single polymorphisms, <emphasis>linkage disequilibrium (LD).</emphasis>  In the equilibrium state, allele 1 should be associated with alleles 3 and 5 exactly in proportion to their respective frequencies.  In nature, however, equilibrium very rarely exists within sufficiently small segments of DNA.  Thus we are afforded the opportunity to study how often and in what ways allele 1 is not randomly associated with alleles A and 5, or to study linkage disequilibrium.  LD is, thus, a characteristic of a population, not of an individual, and is dependent on the frequencies of the alleles at each polymorphism composing the haplotype.  Analytic methods for testing for the amount of LD and its significance will be discussed in Section III.  Important aspects of haplotypes are that LD for a given length of DNA differs in different parts of the genome and that LD at a specific locus often differs in different populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">C.  Polymorphism Detection Methods</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Introduction</para>
<para></para>
<para>Since all, or almost all, detection and typing methods start with the <emphasis>Polymerase Chain Reaction (PCR)</emphasis> and involve gel electrophoresis, we shall first describe very briefly those technologies and then some of the most commonly used post-PCR procedures.</para>
<para></para>
<para><emphasis>a.  Polymerase chain reaction.  </emphasis>DNA is collected - with all of the problems of sample design - from cell cultures, blood samples, cheek swabs, hair follicles, forensic evidence such as skin under the nails of a victim of violence, etc., and purified from "contaminating" proteins or chemicals. In the case of humans, once that has been done one has about 6 billion bp of DNA (3x109 bp, or one haploid genome, from each parent).  The first step is to isolate the DNA of particular interest (i.e., the polymorphic fragment) from all the rest for further scrutiny.  The technique for this is PCR (Mullis and Faloona, 1987).  In PCR we imitate nature <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> (with several cute twists) by using the same enzyme (PolI) the cells use to replicate or repair DNA to replicate <emphasis>in vitro</emphasis> millions-fold specific regions of DNA.  The cute twists include causing the replication to begin and end at specific sites, and then amplifying the DNA between those sites dozens of times with the consequent doubling of the amount of DNA at each replication (hence "Polymerase chain reaction").  More specifically, the PCR reaction is:</para>
<para></para>
<para> DNA is initially and by default double stranded but the two strands are separated (denatured) by heating to a temperature of 88-100C.  If the temperature is then lowered, the double strandedness will be reestablished (reannealing) because double strandedness is the preferred or default condition of genomic DNA.  (Total genomic DNA will reanneal very slowly because it is very complex.) If a pair of synthetic oligonucleotides ("oligo", single stranded DNA usually about 18-24 bases long and exactly complementary to the 5' end of each strand of each fragment of DNA to be amplified), is present in the reaction tube at high concentration, the reannealing will preferentially favor the reannealing of a shorter oligonucleotides to each of the long strands rather than the reannealing of the two long complementary strands.  The PolI enzyme will then "prime" off the end of the 3' end of the oligo and generate the second strand from "loose" nucleotides (G, A, T, and C) provided in the reaction.  The temperature is then again raised to separate the two strands, lowered to allow reannealing of the oligos and extension once again allowed to proceed.  Usually there are three temperatures for the complete reaction:  94C to denature, 52-64C for oligo reannealing, and 72C for extension between the oligos.  Another of the "cute twists" is that the enzyme, PolymeraseI, used for most of these reactions has been isolated from a bacterium, <emphasis>Thermus aquaticus,</emphasis> allowing the enzyme to retain its activity at high temperatures. (On the Life at High Temperatures by Thomas D. Brock Web site &lt;http://www.bact.wisc.edu/bact303/b27&gt; one can see a picture of the home of  <emphasis>Thermus aquaticus.)</emphasis> </para>
<para></para>
<para>That, in a nutshell is PCR, and it is at this point that one of the many errors in polymorphism typing can occur.  If one is typing an InDel, VNTR, or STRP of a heterozygous individual whose two alleles differ considerably in length (i.e., 300 bp more or less), it often happens that there is preferential PCR amplification of the shorter allele.  In such a case, all homozygotes - long or short - will amplify properly, but all or some heterozygotes will amplify as homozygotes of the shorter type.   For these and other errors of typing, there are often laboratory methods that can be used to minimize them, if they are detected.    We shan't discuss those methods here, however we shall describe in Section III some of the statistical methods of determining whether some of the systematic typing errors may have occurred. </para>
<para>Having amplified to abundance the particular fragment of DNA that contains the polymorphism of interest, it is now necessary to detect which alleles are in each sample - to type the samples.  There are at least three major techniques for typing the PCRed samples:  Many of the detection and typing methods utilize gel electrophoresis.</para>
<para></para>
<para><emphasis>b.  Gel electrophoresis (agarose or acrylamide)</emphasis>.  Gel electrophoresis is probably the oldest and still most commonly used method of separating two DNA fragments of differing length (InDels, VNTRs, and STRPs).  The technique depends on the fact that DNA carries a negative charge and that various gel matrices have specific sieving qualities.  In practice DNA (in our case the PCR product) is applied to one end of a gel and a direct current is applied across the gel.  The DNA is pushed/pulled though the gel from the negative pole toward the positive pole.  Larger fragments move more slowly than smaller fragments and two fragments will separate in the matrix over time in the current.  It remains only to stain the DNA so that the fragments can be visualized and photographed.  </para>
<para>There is a vast number of detection methods that range in complexity, comprehensiveness, time required, and expense.  They include sequencing, DHPLC, DGGE, SSCP and many others. </para>
<para></para>
<para>Resequencing</para>
<para></para>
<para>Of course the most obvious and comprehensive method of polymorphism detection is <emphasis>resequencing </emphasis>a number of people for a given region of the genome and simply noting every difference in the sequences.  There is an increasingly used variant of the resequencing method - <emphasis>in silico </emphasis>resequencing.  <emphasis>In silico</emphasis> resequencing is data mining of the public databases.  Wherever two or more independent clones have been sequenced, the two (or more) sequences can be compared and differences tested for polymorphism.  As noted earlier, the sequence difference itself is not necessarily a polymorphism; the frequencies in the population determine whether it is a polymorphic site. Very often the sequence differences arise from an underlying error rate in the sequencing procedure or from the accidental sequence of a very rare variant.  In those cases, of course, no polymorphism exists.  Nevertheless, a fair number of the discrepant sequences result from real polymorphic differences between the clone donors.  Strategy for resequencing (e.g., number of different samples, origin of the samples, length of the sequence) is determined by the specific research questions being posed.  Examples: (1) If variation is found by resequencing only a few samples, that variation is likely to be present at high frequency in the population in which it was found.  The smaller the sample, the higher the heterozygosity is likely to be - polymorphisms involving uncommon alleles (and/or variants) are likely to be missed.  Conversely, the larger the sample, the more likely one is to find polymorphisms, even if they have low heterozygosity in the population.  (2) The population origin of the samples to be resequenced also determines the number of polymorphisms found, but in a different way: On average, samples from Africa will contain more variation than samples from Europe, Europe more than those from East Asia, and East Asia more than those from native Americans.  Not only does the amount of variation decrease with increasing distance from Africa, but the variation that does exist is largely a successive subsetting of that in Africa. If the study is one of a particular population, it might be best to look for variation in that population.  If, on the other hand, the study requires variation in all populations around the world, it might be best to search for the polymorphisms in aboriginal Americans.  (3) Length of the sequence is often determined by less theoretical and more physical factors.  For example, if coding sequence variation is of most interest, the length of the sequence will be determined by the length of an exon or of a cDNA clone.  More basically, length may be determined by the maximum length possible with a given sequencing technology, etc.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Denaturing gradient gel electrophoresis (DGGE) </emphasis>detects polymorphisms by taking advantage of the capacity of DNA to form <emphasis>heteroduplexes.</emphasis>  A heteroduplex is a chimeric double stranded DNA.  During the course of PCR, the double stranded DNA is denatured into two single strands.  Since each person has two copies of his/her DNA (one from the mother, <emphasis>M</emphasis>, and one from the father, <emphasis>F) </emphasis>and each is double stranded, each individual's DNA will thus contain four single strands of DNA upon denaturation.  If these strands are allowed to slowly reanneal, (or renature), the products will be <emphasis>MM, MF, FM, </emphasis>and <emphasis>FF.  </emphasis>The MM and FF products are <emphasis>homoduplexes</emphasis> and the MF (or FM) products are <emphasis>heteroduplexes. </emphasis> The homoduplexes contain no mismatches.  The heteroduplex, however, may contain one (or more) mismatches if the individual is a heterozygote&mdash;that is, if the individual received one allele from the mother and a different allele from the father.  If the heteroduplex contains a mismatch, the DNA will denature at a lower temperature than will a homoduplex or a heteroduplex without a mismatch.  Denaturation can be promoted chemically as well as by termperature and the denaturation is dependent on concentration of the denaturing compound (in the case of DGGE, urea).  Reannealed DNA is loaded on a gradient gel with the urea concentration in the gel increasing with distance from the origin.  Electrophoresis is begun and as the DNA migrates through the matrix, it will eventually reach the place in the matrix where the urea concentration is high enough to begin to denature the DNA.  When denaturation begins, the DNA is immobilized in  the matrix.  If the DNA is perfectly complementary, the denaturation point will be further along than if there is a mismatch in the heteroduplex.  The DNA in the matrix (gel or column) can be stained and the distance the DNA progressed through the gel determined.  The heteroduplex DNA of a heterozygote will be stalled in the gel at a point closer to the origin than will the homoduplexes, and a variant will thus be detected.  </para>
<para></para>
<para>Denaturing high performance liquid chromatography</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Denaturing High Pressure Liquid Chromatography (DHPLC)</emphasis>(Xiao and Oefner, 2001)<emphasis> </emphasis>also depends on the formation of heteroduplexes, but DHPLC is non-gel based.  In DHPLC a capillary tube is packed with tiny alkylated particles.  DNA is injected into the column and forced chemically and electrically through the column; under certain chemical conditions double stranded DNA will be retained by the column and single stranded DNA will elute through the column.  Additionally, under completely denaturing conditions, the double stranded DNAs will not only remain in the column, but will be separated in the column based on sequence content as well as length, allowing discrimination of the two homozygotes.  Detection is by laser induced fluorescence.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Single Strand Conformation Polymorphisms</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>Single Strand Conformation Polymorphisms (SSCP)</emphasis> is both the name of the method and the name of the type of polymorphism detected.  SSCP depends on the formation of secondary structure by single stranded DNA&mdash;it folds back on itself, forming loops.  This secondary structure will cause the DNA to slow its movement through a gel during electrophoresis.  When single stranded or denatured DNA (PCR product of an individual sample) is loaded onto a gel and electrophoresis begun, the DNA enters the gel and eventually begins to form secondary structure.  If the different strands of DNA have different sequences, the secondary structures will be slightly different and, consequently, mobility over distance in the gel will be different.  Thus, mobility differences between the single strands of an individual or among individuals will be indicative of variation within the specific PCR product.</para>
<para></para>
<para> There are many other methods of detecting polymorphisms and more are coming on line every day.  Most of them use principles described above.  </para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">D.  Typing methods</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para> Almost any way used to discover polymorphisms can be used also to type those polymorphisms in individuals.  However, most of the methods for detection mentioned above are generally far too costly (time and money) for high throughput and the interpretation of results are also very time consuming.  Many other methods of typing have been developed and we shall describe some of them here.</para>
<para></para>
<para>1.  Gel electrophoresis-based typing</para>
<para></para>
<para>As described above gel electrophoresis is used to force DNA through a gel-like matrix.  DNA is inserted into a well in the gel near the positive pole and the negatively charged DNA will migrate through the gel from the negative pole toward the positive pole.  When DNA fragments are of varying length, they will migrate across the field at varying speeds with the longer fragments of DNA migrating more slowly through the gel than shorter fragments.  All the DNA of the same length remains in a tight band as it migrates through the gel.  The amount of separation between different size fragments (bands) of DNA will depend on the sieving qualities of the gel, relative size differences of the DNA fragments, and amount and duration of the current.  Many polymorphisms are length polymorphisms (STRPs, VNTRs, InDels), and the regions containing such polymorphisms can be PCR amplified and the products run on a gel.  The various alleles will separate under gel electrophoresis gels, and it remains only to devise a way to visualize the differences in length of the DNA in the gel.  Since intercalating dyes such as Cybr Green and Ethidium Bromide will cause DNA to fluoresce under UV light allowing the DNA in a gel to be visualized directly under UV light.  Sometimes the size differences are so small that UV discrimination is not possible.  In those cases the gel matrix can be changed to polyacrylamide which has much finer sieving qualities, and one end of the DNA fragments can be labeled, with a fluor.  In this way very tiny size differences can be visualized.</para>
<para></para>
<para>There is at last one pitfall in gel based typing:  The co-migration of two bands.  Sometimes either oligos will prime products from two regions of the genome (due to homology of the oligos to more than a single location in the genome.).  The may often be the case when DNA from a gene family is being amplified.  If the co-amplified DNA is of the same length as one of the expected alleles in the deliberately amplified DNA, the end result in a gel is that we will see correctly the homozygotes with the co-migrating band as homozygotes, all heterozygotes will correctly appear as heterozygotes, however the homozygote of the type without the co-migrating band will appear to the a heterozygote.  A second type of gel error can occur especially when the size difference between alleles is very small - one, two, or three bases.  There are certain gel matrices (such as polyacrylamide) that have extremely fine sieving qualities - so fine that single base differences in size can be discerned.  When such gels are used, gel to gel differences may make discrimination of alleles very close in size difficult or make identifying two identical alleles on different gels problematic.  When there is not a difference in size between two alleles (SNP), it is sometimes possible to induce a difference that will be detectably by gel electrophoresis as described above for InDels, VNTRs and STRPs.  As we said earlier, an SNP, the most common type of polymorphism, is a single base pair change at a specific site in the DNA. Enzymes (called <emphasis>restriction enzymes </emphasis>exist in nature that recognize and cut DNA at very specific short sequences (usually 4-12 bp and often palindromic). If the changed site either produces or abolishes a restriction site, one can use the enzyme to reduce the size of the allele containing the site relative to the allele that does not contain the site and proceed with gel electrophoresis as described above.  Polymorphisms recognized in this way are a subset of SNPs - <emphasis>restriction fragment length polymorphisms (RFLPs).</emphasis> (See Figure I.D.1).  Unfortunately, there is also a possible error associated with this procedure: The restriction enzyme reaction may not proceed to completion (i.e., not all of the fragments with the restriction are actually cut).  The effect of this incomplete reaction (or <emphasis>partial digestion)</emphasis> is that all homozygotes of the large size fragment will be scored correctly, all heterozygotes will be scored correctly, however the homozygotes of the smaller size fragment will be scored as heterozygotes (because some of the fragments that should have been shortened by the enzyme were not).  </para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>2.  Non-gel typing methods</para>
<para></para>
<para>Among the PCR but non-gel based methods of typing polymorphisms are some that are particularly useful when there is neither a size difference between alleles nor is a size difference inducible by restriction enzyme.  These include a number of procedures based on differential florescent color tagging of the two alleles: <emphasis>Florescence polarization (FP)</emphasis>, and <emphasis>TaqMan.</emphasis></para>
<para>Florescence polarization depends on the ability of perfectly complementary single stranded DNAs to anneal with each other and of Taq polymerase to extend from primers.  PCR as described above is again the first step in FP typing.  The PCR product is purged of leftover reagents from the PCR reaction and fluor-labeled single base nucleotides - each different nucleotide is labeled with a different colored fluor - are added to the reaction along with a synthetic oligo very similar to those used for PCR; however, this oligo ends at, but does not include, the polymorphic site.  With the addition of a special polymerase and cycling the temperatures to denature (separate the double strands of the DNA) and anneal, the enzyme extends off the oligo by adding the base <emphasis>(single base extension)</emphasis> that is complementary to the specific allele(s) present.  Detection of what color base has been added depends on the effect of anchoring a fluor to the DNA compared to that fluor loose in the solution. If a fluor is anchored by being incorporated into the sequence of the oligo, laser light passed through it is polarized; if the fluor is not anchored onto an oligo, the light passes through it unpolarized.  The ratio of polarized to unpolarized light determines which base was added to fill in the polymorphic site.  In any given reaction, if only one fluor is polarized, that sample is a homozygote and the type of homozygote is determined by the color of the polarized fluor (that is the wavelength or the polarized signal).  If there are two different fluors that are polarized, the individual is a heterozygote.</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>DASH </emphasis>is a non-gel-based SNP typing system (Howell et al., 1999) that depends on the property of certain dyes (e.g., Cybr green or Ethidium Bromide) to intercalate <emphasis>double stranded DNA, </emphasis>and to fluoresce only when intercalated and stimulated with UV light.  In the DASH procedure, two 20 to 25 bp long synthetic oligos are designed to compliment each of the alleles exactly.  The oligos are designed such that the variable site is in the middle.  Then very short DNA fragments (about 50 bp) are PCR amplified with the variable site also in the middle.  The typing is done in duplicate with one oligo (identical to one of the alleles) used in one reaction and the other allele-specific oligo used in the other.  The PCR product is denatured (caused to become single stranded), and the allowed to anneal to one of the allele-specific oligos.   The resulting product will fluoresce under UV light.  The temperature of the reaction is then slowly raised until the oligo denatures (or drops off) causing the dye to cease to fluoresce.   The temperature at which the oligo denatures depends on how well matched the oligo is to the PCR product.  If there is a mismatch in the oligo at the variable site, the oligo denatures at a lower temperature than if the match is perfect.  The procedure is repeated with the second allele-specific oligo.  If the sample being typed is a homozygote matching the first oligo, when that oligo is used the fluorescence will disappear at a high (relatively) temperature when the first oligo is annealed and heated and at a lower temperature if the second oligo is annealed and heated.  If the sample being typed is from a heterozygote, the fluorescence will significantly decrease at a lower temperature and then disappear altogether at a higher temperature in both reactions.  If the sample being typed is a homozygote matching the second allele-specific oligo, the fluorescence will disappear altogether at a lower temperature in the reaction with the first allele-specific oligo and in the second reaction with the second allele-specific oligo disappear altogether at a higher temperature.  The amount of fluorescence is measured continuously as the temperature is gradually raised and the second derivative of the fluorescence and temperature is plotted.  A homozygote has a single high peak in the reaction with the perfectly matching oligo and a single low peak in the reaction with the mismatching oligo; and a heterozygote has two peaks&mdash;one at each temperature in both reactions.</para>
<para></para>
<para> <emphasis>TaqMan</emphasis> is a method of typing SNPs developed by ABI that takes advantage of the annealing properties of perfectly matched DNA and the capacity of quencher dye in close proximity to a fluor to quench the fluor's signal.  PCR of the region containing the site to be typed proceeds in the usual way, except that there is an additional oligo in the reaction mix.  This extra oligo is designed to be allele-specific in that it is a perfect complement of one of the alleles being typed.  In addition, the primer has a fluor on one end and a quencher on the other.  Initially the fluor and quencher are in close proximity because the distance between them is maintain constant and close by the primer to which they are both attached - the fluor does not fluoresce.  During the annealing phase of the PCR cycle, this third primer anneals perfectly to the sequence it complements.  If there is no perfect complement in the reaction, the oligo will not anneal.  During the extension phase, the Taq Polymerase that generates the product from the template DNA, upon coming to an oligo annealed to the strand it is amplifying, will <quote>chew</quote> away, or cleave, the interfering oligo, thus separating the quencher from the fluor.  This is repeated at every cycle.  By the end of the PCR cycling, if the sample DNA contains the allele complementing the allele-specific oligo, the reaction mix will fluoresce in the wavelength of the fluor attached to the allele-specific oligo.  This detection procedure can be done in duplicate with a single allele-specific oligo in each reaction, or it can be done in a single reaction with both allele-specific oligos, each with a different fluor.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The use of <emphasis>microarrays</emphasis> is one of the most potentially useful methods of high throughput typing coming on line today.  For polymorphism typing, microarrays are a still-emerging technology so not all the details are worked out yet.  However a thumbnail sketch of microarray typing once again would start with PCR reactions, or PCR reactions multiplexed with several sets of primers in one tube with DNA from one individual.  This pool of PCR products for each individual is then micro-spotted at high density such that there may be as many as 6,000 spots of pooled DNA on a single 1 x 3 inch slide.  This could correspond to duplicate spots of DNA from 3,000 samples.   Slides can be made in duplicate, triplicate or however many as necessary for the number of PCR products in each individual DNA PCR product pool.  Once again we shall rely on fluor-labeling in different colors of fluor.  This time, however, we would add two oligos to the mix, each with a different color fluor attached directly to the fluor.  The two oligos are designed such that the final base at the 3' end of the oligo corresponds to one or the other of the variable bases in the polymorphism.  If conditions are perfect, the oligo will only anneal to the DNA with an exact match.  Thus, either oligos of one color will anneal (homozygote), oligos of both colors will anneal (heterozygote), or only oligos of the second color will anneal (the opposite homozygote).  The excess reagents are washed off, and the slide is read by a microreader.  Because multiple copies of the slides are made of pooled samples, a second, third, fourth, etc. set of oligos can be <emphasis>hybridized</emphasis> to the second, third, fourth, etc. slide.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">II.  Overview of the distribution of variation</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Patterns of variation may be may be considered in several ways - across the genome, in or between populations, or in a particular locus/gene of interest.  In the first case it is the genomic location of the polymorphism (telomeric, centromeric, intragenic, in areas of particular nucleotide content, etc.) that is of interest.  In the second case, it is the frequency of the alleles in different populations around the world - populations of higher or lower endogamy, more or less admixture, defined geographically, linguistically, by self-report, or in any other way - that is of interest.  And in the third case, variation in a gene may cause a disorder or susceptibility to a disorder, may be important in personal identification, or may even be selectively advantageous.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">A. Variation in the genome</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para>Much work is ongoing to identify sites of variation in the human genome.  The number of sites in the genome that show variation among individuals is in the millions.  The SNP Consortium and others have identified more than 2 million sites across the genome with variation.  Work is ongoing to determine whether the variation is polymorphic with an appreciable heterozygosity or whether one of the forms seen is just a rare variant (or even a sequencing error).  Databases such as dbSNP &lt;http://www.ncbi.nih.gov/SNP/index.html&gt;, The SNP Consortium &lt;http://SNP.cshl.org/index.html&gt;, and HGBASE &lt;http://hgbase.cgr.ki.se/&gt; all maintain and regularly update information on SNPs and other polymorphisms.  There are other types of variation  -  STRPs, VNTRs  - that are not so routinely cataloged in these databases but can be found in GDB &lt;http://www.gdb.org/gdb/gdbtop.html&gt; and the Marshfield database &lt;http://research.marshfieldclinic.org/genetics&gt;, for example.  Moreover, most of the SNP surveys are based on relatively few individuals; consequently, many less common variants or variants restricted to particular groups or peoples in a specific geographic region may not have been found.  Conversely, some of the SNPs found could be based on observing a very rare variant and not be likely to show variation in subsequent samples.  In fact, both under- and over-counting do occur.  It is possible that virtually every nucleotide varies at least once among the 6 billion humans = 12 billion genomes present on the earth.  A more relevant question than how many sites vary is how many sites show common variation.  That question is unanswerable as yet, but the number is certainly large.  But, what is meant by <emphasis>common</emphasis>?  The appropriate measure for quantifying variation at a site is heterozygosity.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Heterozygosity may be measured as either the <emphasis>observed</emphasis> proportion of heterozygotes in a population, or that proportion <emphasis>expected</emphasis> based on Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium and given the allele frequency.  This estimate for the population is easily calculated as <emphasis>2pq</emphasis> for a biallelic locus or as <emphasis>1-&#x3a3;p</emphasis><emphasis><subscript>i</subscript></emphasis><emphasis><superscript>2</superscript></emphasis> for a multiallelic locus.  The value of a polymorphism as a research tool depends on the type of study to be undertaken but in general heterozygosities should be greater than 0.2 for a marker to be very useful.  Because SNPs are biallelic, the largest heterozygosity for a single SNP is 0.5.  For multiallelic polymorphisms, such as the STRPs, heterozygosities can be &gt;0.7 and some are &gt;0.9 because there are many distinguishable alleles and none is very common.</para>
<para></para>
<para>While the global level of variation and the numbers of common variants cannot yet be addressed precisely, the average level of variation in a European population has been addressed in various studies.  The standard way to measure overall amounts of variation is as nucleotide diversity, often represented by &#x3c0; (Nei and Li, 1979; see also Li, 1997).  This is the probability that in two copies of a DNA sequence taken at random from the population a specific nucleotide position will have two different nucleotides.  It is logically analogous to heterozygosity in individuals &ndash; the probability that the maternal copy of a gene, the one inherited from one's mother, differs from the paternal copy of the gene, the one inherited from one's father.  Alternatively, nucleotide diversity can be considered to be the average number of nucleotide differences per site between two randomly chosen sequences.  Numerous estimates of &#x3c0; in global samples of modern humans have now been generated (reviewed in Przeworski et al. 2000, Wall and Przeworski 2000; Yu et al. 2001), with consistent estimates falling near the early value of 0.11% as estimated by Li and Sadler (1979).  This would translate to an average of one heterozygous site every 900 basepairs in an individual.  Polymorphic nucleotide positions would occur even more commonly in the population since any one site will be homozygous at least half the time.  (Because SNPs are biallelic, the largest heterozygosity for a single SNP is 0.5.)  Clearly, there is a great deal of DNA sequence variation that is common and normal.  In the context of this common normal variation neither allele can be considered "wild type".  Only in the context of rare, usually deleterious, mutations is the normal allele the "wild type".</para>
<para></para>
<para>As genomic locations and heterozygosities in at least some populations are known, researchers are beginning to address questions of how the variation is distributed around the genome and how the variation is organized in local regions of the genome.</para>
<para></para>
<para>There have been recent reports that mutations (the ultimate source of most polymorphisms) tend to occur in regions of high recombination.  One might infer, therefore, that polymorphisms should aggregate in regions of high recombination.  There is not much data as yet on this subject.</para>
<para></para>
<para>In several recent papers the question of how the variation is organized in local regions of the genome has been addressed (Daly et al., 2001; Reich et al., 2001).  The general finding is that across short segments of DNA, on the order of 10 kilobases, varying sites are associated so that chromosomes with a particular allele at one site will tend to have some particular allele at each of the other sites within the region.  This non-random arrangement of DNA variants along the chromosome is referred to as linkage disequilibrium (LD).  The particular combinations of alleles at the nearby sites are called haplotypes.  Interestingly, the evidence for European populations is that only a small number of the combinations of alleles, i.e., haplotypes, actually occurs and a subset of those accounts for &gt;90% of all copies in the population.  However, the span of this set of associated markers appears to have discrete boundaries defining blocks of sequence with strong LD within the block but essentially no LD between the blocks.  The length of a block of DNA showing strong LD appears to be different for different parts of the DNA; some blocks can extend for over 100 kb.  An active area of research currently is how general these initial findings are for different parts of the genome and for different populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> As an example of linkage disequilibrium and haplotypes, consider the following.  For three SNPs with equal allele frequencies, p<subscript>i</subscript> = q<subscript>i </subscript> = 0.5, there are 8 (=2<superscript>3</superscript>) possible haplotypes at equal frequencies of 1/8 if there is no linkage disequilibrium.  If there is LD, then some of those haplotypes occur more frequently than expected by chance and others less frequently, even absent.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">B.  Variation among populations</phrase></para>
<para></para>
<para> Discussions of how many sites show common variation, how much variation there is at a specific site, how variation is distributed along the genome, and how variation is organized in locally are all population dependent.  In all areas for which we have information different populations differ.  Table II.B.1 gives the allele frequencies in 33 populations from around the world.  The frequency of the Rsa+ allele (restriction site present) varies from high values &gt;90% in African and Native American populations to low values of &lt;20% in some East Asian populations.  The heterozygosity at this site varies from zero (the Rsa+ allele is fixed, i.e., the Rsa- allele is not seen) up to 0.47, close to the maximum possible value of 50%.  Clearly, any quantitative measures of allele frequency or heterozygosity for this polymorphic site must reference some specific population.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Table II.B.1. RsaI restriction site polymorphism at ADH1B. This is an example of gene frequency variation among populations for a SNP in an intron (non-coding segment). The Fst for this site is 0.409 which is unusually large, probably because selection has operated on a nearby coding region SNP. The ANCESTOR is inferred (Iyengar et al., 1998) based on the identical sequence chimpanzees gorillas, and organutans.</para>
<para></para>
<para>                            2N  f(Rsa+) f(Rsa-)  het</para>
<para> 0 ANCESTOR                       1.0     0               </para>
<para><phrase role="strong">AFRICA</phrase></para>
<para> 1 Biaka Pygmy             138   .935  .065  .122</para>
<para> 2 Mbuti Pygmies            78   .974  .026  .051</para>
<para> 3 Yoruba                  144   .986  .014  .028</para>
<para> 4 Ibo                      96   .979  .021  .041</para>
<para> 5 Hausa                    74   .919  .081  .149</para>
<para> 6 Ethiopian Jews           62   .903  .097  .176</para>
<para> 7 African Amer            178   .893  .107  .191</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">MIDDLE EAST</phrase></para>
<para> 8 Yemenite Jews            78   .910  .090  .164</para>
<para> 9 Druze Unrelated         144   .736  .264  .389</para>
<para>10 Samaritans               78   .731  .269  .393</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">EUROPE</phrase></para>
<para>11 Adygei                  104   .721  .279  .402</para>
<para>12 Russians, Vologda        94   .745  .255  .380</para>
<para>13 Finns                    64   .812  .188  .305</para>
<para>14 Danes (unrelateds)       96   .688  .312  .429</para>
<para>15 Irish                   190   .795  .205  .326</para>
<para>16 Eur.Mixed               182   .692  .308  .426</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">EAST ASIA</phrase></para>
<para>17 Chinese, S.F.           108   .185  .815 .302</para>
<para>18 Chinese, Taiwan          98   .143  .857  .245</para>
<para>19 Hakka                    84   .190  .810  .308</para>
<para>20 Japanese                 98   .153  .847  .259</para>
<para>21 Ami                      80   .350  .650  .455</para>
<para>22 Atayal                   84   .179  .821  .294</para>
<para>23 Cambodians               48   .396  .604  .478</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">PACIFIC</phrase></para>
<para>24 Nasioi Melanesians       46   .696  .304  .423</para>
<para>25 Micronesians             64   .625  .375  .469</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">SIBERIA</phrase></para>
<para>26 Yakut                    98   .755  .245  .185</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">NORTH AMERICA</phrase></para>
<para>27 Cheyenne                112   .982  .018  .035</para>
<para>28 Pima, Arizona           100   1.00     0  0</para>
<para>29 Pima, Mexico unrelated  104   .942  .058  .109</para>
<para>30 Maya                    102   .990  .010  .02</para>
<para><phrase role="strong">SOUTH AMERICA</phrase></para>
<para>31 Ticuna                  132   1.00     0  0</para>
<para>32 Rondonian Surui          84   1.00     0  0</para>
<para>33 Karitiana               106   1.00     0 0</para>
<para></para>
<para> When we consider the average heterozygosity for a single population, averaging across many different polymorphic loci, we see a general pattern of greatest heterozygosity in the sub-Saharan African populations with average heterozygosity among non-African populations decreasing with increasing distance from Africa.  The lowest average heterozygosity is seen in small isolated populations and in South American populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para> In general, one can quantify the variation among populations as the standardized variance, F<subscript>st</subscript>, calculated as &#x3c3;<subscript>p</subscript><superscript>2</superscript>/(), where  and  are the average allele frequencies among the populations and &#x3c3;<subscript>p</subscript><superscript>2</superscript> is the variance of the allele frequency across the populations studied.  Note, even for this measure of variation the value will depend on the set of populations for which allele frequencies are available.  F<subscript>st</subscript> is basically the ratio of the variation at a locus in one population compared to the average variation at that locus across all the populations - it is, thus, a measure of the <emphasis>interpopulation</emphasis> difference for a given polymorphic locus, or the ability of that polymorphism to discriminate between populations.  F<subscript>st</subscript> can range in value from 0 (which occurs when all populations have exactly the same allele frequency) to 1 when each population is at fixation (that is, has an allele frequency of 1.0) but different populations are fixed for different alleles.</para>
<para></para>
<para>The range of F<subscript>st</subscript> values for nearly 100 SNPs across 33 populations (the same ones that are in Table II.B.1) is 0.04 to nearly 0.4.  Figures II.B.1 and II.B.2 give examples of allele frequency variation for the 4 SNPs with the lowest F<subscript>st</subscript> values and the 4 SNPs with the highest F<subscript>st</subscript> values.  The frequency of one allele at each biallelic locus is presented in the graphs.  Because these 33 populations originate from around the world, it is likely that this range is representative of the global range for neutral variation affected only by random genetic drift.  The F<subscript>st</subscript> values for all such loci form a single distribution.</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.1.</phrase> Population variation for SNPs with low interpopulation variation. The Fst values are 0.041 for D4S10 TaqI"A", 0.046 for HOXB4 MspI, 0.049 for D13S2PstI, and 0.052 for DBH MwoI"A".</para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.2.</phrase> Population variation for SNPs with high interpopulation variation. The Fst values are 0.255 for D4S10 Hind3"b", 0.268 for DRD2 Taq "d", 0.295 for PAH XmnI, and 0.374 for MSO-1 AvaI.</para>
<para></para>
<para>Haplotype frequencies vary among populations just as allele frequencies at individual sites.  Populations that are geographically close tend to have similar haplotype frequencies.  Figure II.B.3 shows the haplotype frequencies for different regions of the world for haplotypes at PAH based on six polymorphic sites spanning the gene.  Linkage disequilibrium also varies among populations as a function of several factors, several of which involve the demography - past and present - of the populations and even of the ancestral populations of present day populations.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para><phrase role="strong">Figure II.B.3</phrase>.  PAH 6-site haplotype frequencies by geographic region.  The number of populations in each region is given in parentheses.  The alleles comprising each haplotype are listed in the order of the sites across the gene.</para>
<para></para>
<para></para>
<para>Our observations on the molecular extent of disequilibrium in various regions of the genome and in various populations are the opposite of the average heterozygosity variation around the world.  The molecular extent tends to be shortest in African populations and longest in Native American populations, as was seen at PAH (Kidd et al., 2000).  Other factors are also operating such that LD extends over shorter intervals in all populations near telomeres and longer intervals near centomeres, though there are exceptions.  Biological factors that may be responsible for the genomic distribution of variation and LD include many that are positional (such as whether the DNA is coding or non-coding regions, intragenic or intergenic).</para>
<para></para>
-->


<!--
Local variables:
sgml-parent-document: ("biostat.xml" "appendix" "article" ("sect1" "glossary" "appendix"))
sgml-indent-step: 1
sgml-indent-data: 1
End:
-->